<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
<tag>history</tag>
<title>Historical comments</title>

<text>
Before we start the study of a new discipline, it is always a good idea to learn something about its origins, the motivations that led people towards the problems that will be addressed, and hopefully solved, with the help network concepts. At the same time, we will get acquainted with the scientists whose pioneering work has shaped the field now called <term>network science</term> <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>. As we will see during the next few pages, the network hall of fame includes mathematicians, sociologists, physicists, and computer scientists.  
</text>


<text>
Graph theory is the starting point of modern network theory. In fact network theory rests on two main bodies of knowledge from a formal point of view: graph theory and game theory. Graph theory studies network structure, whereas game theory serves as the foundation for the study of network behavior, as it provides models of individual behavior in settings where outcomes depend on the behavior of others.
</text>

<!-- 18th Century: Euler -->

<document>
<tag>history-konigsberg</tag>
<title>Eulerian circuits: The Königsberg bridges</title>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-konigsberg</tag>
  <image scale="80" file="image/history/konigsberg"/>
  <title>The seven bridges of Königsberg</title>
</figure>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-konigsberg-graph</tag>
  <image scale="30" file="image/history/konigsberg-graph"/>
  <title>The graph representing the seven bridges of Königsberg problem</title>
</figure>

<text>
The origins of graph theory can be traced back to the work of Leonhard Euler, the famous 18th-century Swiss mathematician, on the Königsberg seven bridges problem. His paper on the solution to this problem in 1736 <cite>Euler 1736</cite> led to the development of two branches of mathematics: the already-mentioned graph theory but also topology, the study of shapes and their properties.
</text>

<text>
Königsberg is a seaport city known today as Kaliningrad, the Russian exclave between Poland and Lithuania on the Baltic Sea. The city was annexed by the Soviet Union at the end of World War II in 1945 and renamed in 1946 after the death Mikhail Kalinin, a Bolshevik who was the Chairman of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the USSR, i.e. the de jure head of state in the Soviet Union. When Euler lived, Königsberg was a Prussian city, located on the banks of the Pregel river, which also occupied two islands in the middle of the river. Four bridges connected the banks of the river to one of the islands, two bridges crossed the river to connect to the second island, and a seventh bridge connected the two islands, as shown in Figure <ref>fig-konigsberg</ref>.
</text>

<text>
At the time, nobody knew whether it was possible to take a walk from any point in the city, cross each bridge once, and return to the starting point, what is now known as an Eulerian circuit. Well, nobody was able to explain why it seemed so hard to find such a circuit until Euler proved that it was, in fact, impossible.
</text>

<text>
The banks of the Pregel river, the two islands on it, and the seven bridges in Königsberg can be modeled as a graph, a sketch of the problem that retains its key properties. The banks and the islands become the points in that sketch, i.e. the nodes in the graph. The seven bridges can now be displayed as curved lines that connect those four points, the network links in modern terms. Technically, such a sketch of the problem is a multigraph because there are multiple links between some pairs of nodes. The resulting network, therefore, contains four nodes and seven links, as depicted in Figure <ref>fig-konigsberg-graph</ref>.
</text>

<text>
As it always happens with good models, the graph representation of the Könisberg bridges problem removes unnecessary detail, such as the precise shapes of the islands and the forks of the river. This graph retains the essence of the problem and lets us focus on its connectivity properties. The number of links that arrive to a particular node is known as the node degree and a simple observation of this quantity solves the problem. Even nodes are those nodes with an even degree, whereas odd nodes are those nodes with an odd degree.
</text>

<text>
Euler went beyond the particular Königsberg bridges problem and he gave the necessary and sufficient condition for any arbitrary graph to admit a circular tour through all its nodes without going through the same link twice. It is just not possible to traverse such a network when there are more than two odd nodes.
</text>

<text>
How can be prove such a general result? Let us first consider even nodes. Every time we arrive to an even node through a particular link, we must leave that node through a different link, using up a pair of links. Obviously, we can easily traverse all the links that lead to an even node without problems. At odd nodes, however, there will always be a final single link, which we can use to return to the node. Once there, we will be stuck, since there are no remaining links that have not been traversed. Euler observed this fact to conclude that we cannot traverse a network without revisiting some links when there are more than two odd nodes. These nodes will necessarily be the starting and ending points of our tour through the network.
</text>

<text>
For the particular case of seven bridges of Königsberg, an Eulerian tour is impossible because all its four nodes have odd degrees: <q>the network cannot
be traced by one continuous stroke of a pencil without having to double back over paths that have already been traced</q> <cite>Danesi 2004</cite>.
</text>

<note>
<text>
It should also be noted that there will always be an even number of odd nodes, since links always connect pairs of nodes.
</text>
</note>

</document>

<!-- 19th Century -->

<!-- Trees -->


<document>
<tag>history-trees</tag>
<title>Trees: Electrical circuits and isomers</title>


<text>
Already in the 19th century, a particular kind of graph attracted the attention of some scientists: trees. From a formal point of view, trees are connected acyclic graphs. When there are no cycles, any pair of nodes in a network is connected by just a single path and the network becomes disconnected if a single link is removed. In this sense, trees are the smallest of the possible connected networks.
</text>

<text>
If we look at natural trees, those belonging to the plant category, and observe their branching structures, which are also without cycles, we can easily recognize why mathematicians borrowed some terms from biology to describe this kind of graphs. Apart from the tree term itself, the leaf term is often used to describe tree nodes with degree 1. Another analogy is established with forests, which are networks whose connected components are trees, i.e. sets of trees.
</text>

<text>
Trees implicitly appeared in the study of currents in electrical networks performed by Gustav Kirchhoff <cite>Kirchhoff 1847</cite>. Gustav Kirchhoff was a German physicist who, rather curiously, was born in our well-known city Königsberg, then in East Prussia. He established the foundations of circuit analysis and electrical engineering with his famous circuit laws in 1845:
</text>

<list>

<item>Kirchhoff's current law, KCL, also known as Kirchhoff's first law, Kirchhoff's point rule, Kirchhoff's junction rule, or Kirchhoff's nodal rule: At any node in an electrical circuit, the sum of currents flowing into that node is equal to the sum of currents flowing out of that node.</item>

<item>Kirchhoff's voltage law, KVL, also known as Kirchhoff's second law, Kirchhoff's loop rule, and Kirchhoff's mesh rule: The directed sum of the electrical potential differences, i.e. voltages, around any closed network is zero.</item>

</list>


<figure>
  <tag>fig-isomers</tag>
  <image scale="50" file="image/history/tree-n-butane"/>
  <text></text>
  <image scale="41" file="image/history/tree-i-butane"/>
  <title>The two structural isomers of isobutane, <eqn>C_{4}H_{10}</eqn>: normal butante or n-butane (top) and isobutane or i-butane (bottom), also known as 2-methylpropane</title>
</figure>


<text>
Arthur Cayley, a British mathematician, introduced the term tree in 1857 without defining it formally <cite>Cayley 1857</cite>. Cayley used trees to count the number of different alkanes, chemical compounds also known as paraffins or saturated hydrocarbons. Alkanes, as all hydrocarbons, consist only of hydrogen and carbon atoms. They are bonded by single bonds, i.e. they are saturated compounds, and they do not contain cycles. Carbon atoms have 4 bonds, either C-C or C-H in hydrocarbons, i.e. their valency is 4. Hence the use of the term valency to refer to node degree in early graph theory monographs. The valency of hydrogen is 1: hydrogen atoms have a single bond to another atom, which is always an H-C bond in hydrocarbons. The resulting chemical formula for alkanes is always <eqn>C_{n}H_{2n+2}</eqn>. However, alkanes can present different structures depending on how their carbon atoms are bonded together: alkanes with more than three carbon atoms can be arranged in various different ways, forming structural isomers. Cayley studied such structures and organized them.
</text>


<text>
In graph theory, for any arbitrary connected network, we can define a spanning tree as a tree connecting all of its nodes. Kirchhoff's matrix tree theorem, which was named after Gustav Kirchhoff, shows that the number of spanning trees in a graph can be computed in polynomial time as the determinant of a matrix that is derived from the graph. In fact, it is a generalization of Cayley's formula <cite>Cayley 1889</cite>, which provides the number of different spanning trees in a complete graph. From an alternative point of view, Cayley's formula establishes that we can define <eqn>n^{n-2}</eqn> different trees on <eqn>n</eqn> labeled nodes.
</text>

</document>


<!-- Hamilton -->

<document>
<tag>history-icosian</tag>
<title>Hamiltonian circuits: The icosian game</title>

<text>
Sir William Rowan Hamilton, an Irish physicist and mathematician, is known to mathematicians for the quaternions, a number system that extends the complex numbers, and the theorem of Cayley-Hamilton in linear algebra (yes, the same Cayley we have just met when talking about trees). Hamilton was interested in the study of symmetries in the icosahedron, for which he devised the icosians, a specific set of quaternions.
</text>

<text>
A regular icosahedron is a regular polyhedron with 20 identical equilateral triangular faces, five of them meeting at each vertex. The regular icosahedron has 12 vertices and 30 edges. It is one of the five Platonic solids, which also include the tetrahedron, the cube or hexahedron, the octahedron, and the dodecahedron that eventually led to the icosian board game. A dodecahedron is, in general, any polyhedron with 12 flat faces. In particular, regular dodecahedrons are composed of 12 regular pentagonal faces, with three of them meeting at each vertex, 20 vertices and 30 edges.
</text>

<note>
<text>
You might have noticed that both icosahedrons and dodecahedrons have 30 edges. But, where the dodecahedron has 12 faces and 20 vertices, the icosahedron has 20 faces and 12 vertices. In fact, they are duals: the vertices of one correspond to the faces of the other.
</text>
</note>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-hamiltonian</tag>
  <image scale="30" file="image/history/Hamiltonian-path"/>
  <title>A Hamiltonian cycle in the dodecahedron graph. Source: Wikipedia Commons</title>
</figure>


<text>
At the same time that Arthur Cayley introduced the term tree in his study of isomers, Hamilton devised the icosian game. The game was invented in 1857 with the name of <q>Around the World</q> and sold to a London game dealer for 25 pounds in 1859, just over 2500 current pounds if we adjust for inflation, i.e. somewhat more than 4000 current U.S. dollars. The goal of the game was finding a cycle along the edges of a dodecahedron so that every vertex is visited just once, no edge is visited twice, and the ending point is the same as the starting point. The game was commercialized as a pegboard with holes at the nodes of the dodecahedral graph, which is shown in Figure <ref>fig-hamiltonian</ref> with a solution to the game. Each node was labeled with the name of a city and players had to travel around the world following the edges of the map and visiting each city exactly once.
</text>

<text>
While we were interested in visiting all links without repeating them in Eulerian circuits, we have imposed a similar constraint on the icosian game, but defined over the nodes of the graph. Given the inventor of the icosian game, it comes as no surprise that circuits in which each node is visited just once are known as Hamiltonian circuits. Computers scientists know them well, since they are at the heart of the traveling salesman problem, an NP-hard problem in combinatorial optimization with important applications in many domains. Eulerian circuits, in contrast, can be found in linear time when they exist.
</text>

<note>
<text>
It should be noted that we can find Hamiltonian circuits in graphs that may or may not be Eulerian. The dodecahedral graph in Figure <ref>fig-hamiltonian</ref> is clearly Hamiltonian but not Eulerian, since all its nodes have an odd degree, i.e. 3.
</text>
</note>

</document>


<!-- Terminology -->

<document>
<tag>history-graphs</tag>
<title>The graph term: From linkages to graphs</title>

<text>
Historically, <term>linkage</term>s was the term sometimes employed to refer to graphs. The graph term was standardized by James Joseph Sylvester, a 19th-century British mathematician <cite>Gross and Yellen 2003</cite> <cite>Chartrand et al. 2011</cite>. 
</text>

<text>
J.J. Sylvester was known for his extraordinary ability to coin new terms and create notations for mathematical concepts. For instance, he invented terms such as discriminant, i.e. functions that give information about the roots of a polynomial. Many results in mathematics have been named after Sylvester, apart from a crater on the Moon and the Sylvester Medal. This medal, awarded by the Royal Society in London for the encouragement of mathematical research, has been received by Henri Poincaré, Georg Cantor, Alfred North Whitehead, and Bertrand Russell, among others.
</text>

<text>
Sylvester was the inaugural professor of mathematics at the new Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore, Maryland, where he founded the American Journal of Mathematics in 1878. The American Journal of Mathematics is the oldest continuously published mathematical journal in the United States. When it was created at the John Hopkins University, the only other mathematical journal in the U.S. was the Analyst, originally edited by Joel E. Hendricks and published in Des Moines, Iowa, from 1874 to 1883. The Analyst later became the Annals of Mathematics, published by the University of Virginia since 1884 and continued by the University of Harvard since 1899, until it finally settled at Princeton University in 1911. Since 1933, it is jointly published by Princeton University and the Institute for Advanced Study, also in Princeton, New Jersey, one of the most famous theoretical research centers in the world. Albert Einstein, John von Neumann, Kurt Gödel, and J. Robert Oppenheimer worked there, next to other prominent theoretical physicists, mathematicians, and economists at Princeton, such as Oskar Morgenstern, Paul Dirac, or Paul Erdös, who we will meet later in this chapter.
</text>

</document>


<!-- 20th Century -->

<document>
<tag>history-social-networks</tag>
<title>Sociometry and social network analysis</title>

<text>
Jacob L. Moreno was a Romanian-born Austrian-American psychotherapist who developed sociometry as a quantitative method for measuring social relationships in small groups. Sociometry is the precursor to social network analysis and much of social psychology.
</text>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-sociogram</tag>
  <image scale="80" file="image/history/sociogram1938"/>
  <title>A sociogram from <cite>Moreno and Jennings 1938</cite></title>
</figure>

<text>
While at Columbia University, Moreno devised the sociogram as a means for depicting the interpersonal structure of groups of people. In a sociogram, people are represented as points and relationships between pairs of people are represented by lines linking the corresponding points. First used at a meeting of the Medical Society of the state of New York in April 1933, sociograms were featured by The New York Times and they immediately caught on as a visual display of the effect of networks in, for example, the propagation of diseases.
</text> <!-- The New York Times, April 3, 1933, page 17 -->

<text>
The sociogram jumpstarted the study of sociometry <cite>Moreno 1934</cite>, which was further developed by Jacob Moreno and Helen Jennings <cite>Moreno and Jennings 1938</cite> <cite>Moreno and Jennings 1945</cite> with the goal of analyzing the relationship between social structures and psychological well-being, i.e. social and psychological behavior.
Pioneering work on sociometry was published in the journal Sociometry, edited and published by Moreno in 1937. The journal was transferred to the American Sociological Association in 1955. It as renamed as Social Psychology in 1978 and obtained its current name in 1979: Social Psychology Quarterly.
</text>

<text>
Sociometry focused on small group dynamics by representing positive and negative affective relations within human groups, such as linking, disliking, friendship, or enmity.
The visual display of social relations eventually led to the development of analytic techniques. Data collected to make relations explicit, a.k.a. relational data, can also be represented in matrix form. The resulting matrices are called sociomatrices by sociologists. In a sociomatrix, each cell quantifies the tie between two particular actors in the relation. When the relation is dichotomous or binary, i.e. 0/1, the sociomatrix is just the adjacency matrix of the graph depicted by the sociogram.
</text>

<text>
Leo Katz, Robert Duncan Luce, and Leon Festinger were among the first to use matrices to represent social network data:
</text>

<list>

<item>Elaine Forsyth and Leo Katz preferred the use of sociomatrices over sociograms <q>to present sociometric data more objectively, and to make possible a more detailed analysis of group structure</q> <cite>Forsyth and Katz 1946</cite>. Even though matrices are easier to manipulate from an algebraic point of view, Jacob Moreno still believed that the sociomatrix was not <q>superior and more objective in its presentation than the sociogram</q> <cite>Moreno 1946</cite>. At the time, when computers were not as available as they are today, he preferred direct visualization for making precise observations, sociograms over sociomatrices.</item> <!-- Moreno used his position as editor of Sociometry frequently to interject editor's notes into articles in his journal -->


<item>
Leo Katz, from Michigan State College, thought that the sociogram <q>had apparently reached the limits of its usefulness in the interpretation of sociometric data</q> <cite>Katz 1947</cite> and he proceeded to develop methods for quantifying relational data with the help of matrices and <q>matric operations</q> (sic). He considered some matrix operations and showed their interpretation in sociological terms. Some years later, in 1953, he would introduce a centrality measure or <q>status index</q> that computed the influence of an actor in a social network <cite>Katz 1953</cite>. This index, currently known as Katz centrality, is the forerunner of algorithms such as PageRank, the algorithm employed by Google to rank its search results <cite>Page et al. 1998</cite>, and Kleinberg's HITS ranking algorithm <cite>Kleinberg 1998</cite>.
</item>

<item>
Robert Duncan Luce, a renowned social scientist who held positions at Columbia University, the University of Pennsylvania, the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton, and the University of California at Irvine, introduced graph-theoretic methods into the social sciences. For instance, the French term <q>clique</q> refers to a complete subgraph in graph theory and, as a graduate student at MIT, Luce developed the first techniques for finding cliques in social networks by observing that cliques <q>have simple relationships to the powers of certain matrices</q> <cite>Luce and Perry 1949</cite> <cite>Luce 1950</cite>. His pioneering work set the stage for community detection algorithms, the name received by clustering algorithms when they are applied to network data.
</item>

<item>
At around the same time, Leon Festinger also applied matrix multiplication to sociomatrices and he described how the cube of the sociomatrix can determine the existence of cliques of various sizes and with various degrees of <q>cliquishness</q> <cite>Festinger 1949</cite>, a rather crude method for finding subgroups of similar actors in a network. No wonder Festinger is better known by his work on other areas of psychology, such as the Theory of Cognitive Dissonance, which suggests that an uncomfortable psychological tension appears when people are induced to behave in ways that are inconsistent with their beliefs.
</item>

</list>

<text>
A  monograph describing the application of graph theory to the social sciences was published by Frank Harary and Robert Z. Norman as early as 1953 <cite>Harary and Norman 1953</cite>.
The historical development of sociometry and other related areas that led to the social network analysis field is described, e.g., in <cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>, <cite>Kadushin 2012</cite>, and <cite>Prell 2012</cite>. 
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>history-random-graphs</tag>
<title>Random graphs</title>

<text>
From a mathematical point of view, the earliest statistical analysis of networks were done in the 1950's. The first researchers to study how networks affect to the spread of epidemics were Ray Solomonoff, a student at the University of Chicago who later became one of the 10 participants at the 1956 Darmouth Conference that led to the development of artificial intelligence as a field of study within computer science, and Anatol Rapoport, a Russian-born American mathematical psychologist. They studied the connectivity of random networks and how it determines the diffusion of an epidemic under certain conditions, first by an approximation <cite>Solomonoff and Rapoport 1951</cite> and later more rigorously <cite>Solomonoff 1952</cite>. The formal problem they addressed, which falls within the category of diffusion problems, spurred the study of how resources are distributed through a network, let them be information, ideas, rumors, fads, or viruses.
</text>

<text>
Even though Solomonoff and Rapoport were the first to study random networks and the relation between their connectivity and the spread of epidemics, the model they proposed is currently known as the Gilbert model of random graphs. Edgar Nelson Gilbert was a researcher at Bell Laboratories who formalized the first generative procedure, i.e. algorithm, for creating random graphs <cite>Gilbert 1959</cite>. Basically, a random network with a particular number of links can be created by first constructing a complete graph and then deleting randomly selected links until the desired number of links is achieved.
</text>

<text>
Gilbert's procedure for creating random graphs is not too efficient, since it requires the creation of a complete graph, a step that requires a quadratic number of operations given that a complete graph with <eqn>n</eqn> nodes contains <eqn>{n \choose 2} = \frac{n(n-1)}{2}</eqn> links, i.e. a link between every pair of nodes in the graph. The Hungarian mathematician Paul Erdös, who published more papers than any other mathematician in history with hundreds of collaborators, also wrote on random graphs. In papers he coauthored with Alfréd Rényi, another Hungarian mathematician, they developed the Erdös-Rényi random graph model <cite>Erdos and Renyi 1959</cite> <cite>Erdos and Renyi 1960</cite>. Instead of removing links from a complete network, as in the Gilbert model, the ER model starts with a set of isolated nodes, a network with no links. The ER generative procedure to create a random graph is then just a linear-time iterative algorithm that inserts links between randomly-selected pairs of nodes until the desired number of links is reached.
</text>

<text>
Random graph models, although they might seem to be just mathematical curiosities, are important in practice because they are used as benchmarks to determine whether a network is random or non-random. We can compare actual networks with synthetic random graphs in order to assess whether the properties we observe in the real networks are just the logical consequence of their connectivity or there is something more behind the scenes.
</text>

</document>



<document>
<tag>history-small-worlds</tag>
<title>Small worlds</title>

<text>
One of the interesting properties of random networks is that their diameter rapidly shrinks with the addition of a small number of random links. In other words, even random networks exhibit the small-world effect, which is mathematically defined as the diameter of the network growing with the logarithm of the number of nodes. In contrast, if we arrange nodes using a regular pattern, as in a lattice, the diameter would be proportional to the number of nodes in the lattice.
</text>

<text>
Random graph theory has shown that even networks with no real topological structure exhibit the small-world phenomenon. Random networks are, in network parlance, highly link-efficient because, as their density increases, they become <q>smaller</q>. A small increase in number of links in the network has a major impact on the decline of average path length between nodes in the network. Can we observe that phenomenon in real-world networks, such as the social networks that weave modern societies?
</text>

<text>
Stanley Milgram, a famed social psychologist, resolved to answer that question while he worked at Harvard. For psychologists, he is also known by his experiments on obedience to authority. In those experiments, which raised serious ethical issues in psychological research, most participants were induced by the experimenter to administer (fake) deathly electric shocks to an actor. These frightful experiments illustrated how, at least under some circumstances, participants easily shift their responsibility to another person while they execute horrendous acts.
</text>

<text>
Returning to our discussion on networks, Milgram is also credited with the introduction of the notion of small worlds in networks. Milgram wanted to measure the average path length between between any two individuals in the United States and determine whether social networks are small worlds or not, so he designed experiments that would let him count the number of ties between any two people, at least an approximate count given that the resulting paths might not be the shortest ones. His famous experiments were reported in the inaugural issue of the popular magazine Psychology Today in May 1967 <cite>Milgram 1967</cite> and, two years later, in the research journal Sociometry <cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite>. Randomly-selected participants from Wichita, Kansas, and Omaha, Nebraska, were asked to forward a letter to an unfamiliar target through their acquaintances. Milgram, therefore, estimated how closely-knit our society is by measuring the number of steps required by the letters to achieve their destination.
</text>

<!-- Milgram's experiments -->

<text>
Milgram invited participants, first from Kansas and later from Nebraska, to participate in his <q>communications project</q> to <q>better understand social contact in American
society.</q> These cities were selected because they were thought to represent a great distance in the United States, both socially and geographically <cite>Barabasi 2003</cite>. In Milgram's words, they were chosen because, from Cambridge, Massachusetts, they <q>seem vaguely out there, on the Great Plains</q> <cite>Milgram 1967</cite>. Participants were asked to send an official-looking folder to a target person in Massachusetts: the wife of a divinity school student in Cambridge, in the first experiment, and a stockbroker who worked in Boston and lived in Sharon, a Boston suburb, in the second experiment.
</text>

<text>
The folder contained the name of the target person and some information about him. In addition to his name, address, occupation and place of employment, participants were told his college and year of graduation, his military service dates, and his wife's maiden name and hometown. One question under investigation was the type of information which people would use in reaching the target <cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite>. 
</text>

<text>
A roster was also in the folder, on which each person in the chain had to write his name. This roster prevented the formation of loops in the chains and was also supposed to motivate people to continue the chains. 
</text>

<text>
Finally, the participants received the following specific instructions <cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite>:
</text>

<list>

<item>Add your name to the roster so that the next person who receives this folder will know whom it came from.</item>

<item>Detach one postcard from the bottom of this folder. Fill it out and return it to Harvard University. No stamp is needed. The postcard is very important. It allows us to keep track of the progress of the folder as it moves toward the target person.</item>

<item>If you know the target person on a personal basis, mail this folder directly to him (her). Do this only if you have previously met the target person and know each other on a first name basis.</item>

<item>If you do not know the target person on a personal basis, do not try to contact him directly. Instead, mail this folder to a personal acquaintance who is more likely than you to know the target person. You may send the booklet on to a friend, relative, or acquaintance, but it must be someone you know personally.</item>

</list>

<!-- RESULTS -->

<text>
Using his small budget, Milgram needed two attempts to complete his experiments: the first one starting from Wichita, Kansas, and the second one from Omaha, Nebraska. The one starting in Wichita resulted in only 3 completed chains. However, Milgram obtained a surprising result. Just four days after the folders had been sent, an Episcopalian instructor approached the target person on the street and handed her a folder. This folder only took two intermediate acquaintances, an Episcopalian minister in Kansas and the Episcopalian instructor in Cambridge, to arrive from a farmer in Kansas to the wife of the student in Cambridge.
</text>

<text>
Milgram's second attempt, the one starting in Nebraska with a stockbroker as target, was more successful. In this attempt, the study comprised 296 volunteers: 196 residents of Nebraska, solicited by mail, and 100 Bostonians solicited through an advertisement in a Boston newspaper. The Nebraska group was biased: 100 participants were systematically chosen owners of blue-chip stocks, i.e. known stockholders, while the rest were chosen from the population at large. Overall, 217 out of the 296 chains were started, and 64 of them were completed. Of the 160 chains that got started in Nebraska, only 44 were completed. A significant proportion of the participants simply did not cooperate <cite>Milgram 1967</cite>.
</text>  

<text>
Milgram reported completed chains varying in length from 2 to 10 intermediate acquaintances, with an average of 5.2 and a median of 5. Since their median length was 6, this led to the idea of <q>six degrees of separation</q>. Even though many folders never arrived, Milgram found striking that so many of them reached their destination by such short paths.
</text>

<text>
Milgram also found that many of the completed chains passed through a small number of penultimate individuals. Of the 24 folders that reached the target at his home address, 16 were given to the target by the same person: a clothing merchant called <q>Mr. Jacobs</q> in <cite>Milgram 1967</cite>. That is, 25 percent of the total number of chains that were ever completed reached their target through a single person. At the Boston brokerage house where he worked at, the target also received 10 folders from <q>Mr. Jones</q> and 5 more from <q>Mr. Brown</q>. Somewhat surprisingly for Milgram, just three people handed almost one half of the folders that were ever received by the target.
</text> <!--Of those that reached him at his office, more than half came from two other men.-->

<text>
For folders that never reached their destination, 232 out of 296, the incoming postcards helped identify the break points in the chains. For those that arrived, Milgram examined the chains that were created. Folders quickly reached geographic proximity to the target. Provided that geographic information was available to identify the target, it seems reasonable to use that information to forward the folder. Once the folders were geographically close to the target, they tended to circle the target almost randomly until they hit the target's inner circle of friends.
</text>

<text>
Analyzing the chains, Milgram also observed that the number of steps required to reach the destination was sometimes higher than expected because there were social structural barriers, e.g. links between men and women were less frequent than same-sex connections. Similar barriers have also been observed between social classes.
</text>

<!-- Criticisms -->

<text>
Milgram's experiments have been criticized for his small sample size and also for biasing his results. Results are biased both by the method employed to recruit the starting population in Nebraska, which contained one half of stockholders who were instructed to reach a stockbroker, and by not taking into account incomplete chains in his estimate of average path length. <!--  Starters were recruited through an advertisement that specifically sought for people who considered themselves as well-connected. -->
Assuming a constant probability of non-response by each person in a chain, longer chains will be underrepresented since it is more likely that they will be broken somewhere along the path from the starter to the target. Therefore, Milgram underestimates the true average path length. Some methods have been proposed to correct these estimates, e.g. by taking into account information collected from partially-completed chains <cite>Schnettler 2009b</cite>.
</text>

<text>
Another aspect that should be taken into account is that participants might not properly choose the person most likely to know the target, much less who is actually closer to the target. Since we only have a local and incomplete knowledge of the whole social network around us, Milgram's experiment results would therefore tend overestimate the true average path length between individuals in a social networks. Sometimes, folders move away from their target rather than closer to him.  
</text>

<text>
Finally, we should also consider the existence of completely isolated communities. Uncontacted people, also known as lost tribes, live without significant contact with the external world, either by choice, i.e. in voluntary isolation like cloistered monks and hermits, or by circumstance, as some indigenous tribes in remote islands or in the forest. These groups of people, who may lack immunity to common diseases, do not take part in the global chains suggested by Milgram's small world experiments. Even when they are known to exist and might have some contact with the rest of the world, they will still be farther from the vast majority of individuals in the modern world, but not much farther than average, since a single contact point serves as a bridge to those isolated communities. 
</text>



<!-- More experiments -->

<text>
Due to the difficulty in obtaining exhaustive data from actual social networks, social network research on the small world problem is often based on targeted local search procedures similar to those in Milgram's experiments <cite>Schnettler 2009a</cite>. Below we describe some of the follow-up studies that have been performed on small worlds:
</text>

<list>

<item>
<b>Reverse small world experiments</b> ask participants how they would find a particular person in a given town with a given occupation, together with information about sex and ethnic background. <cite>Killworth and Bernard 1978</cite> found that about one half of the people would choose location and another half would choose occupation to determine the person who might help them complete the chain in a small-world experiment. Ethnicity and other reasons were rarely used. People typically chose friends or acquaintances rather than family members. 
In their decision, most participants invoked the use of Blau space, a theoretical construct named after the sociologist Peter Blau that considers socio-demographic variables as dimensions in a multidimensional coordinate system <cite>McPherson 1983</cite>.
</item>

<item>
<b>The Columbia Small Worlds Project</b> is a more recent experiment that used the Internet to reproduce Milgram's results <cite>Dodds et al. 2003</cite>. Using e-mail, more than 60,000 participants from 166 countries attempted to reach 18 target persons in 13 different countries. 24,163 distinct message chains were started, but only 384 reached their target, a completion rate below 2 percent. Researchers assumed that chains were terminated because of individual apathy or disinclination to participate, probably due to the lack of incentives to continue the chains. Even though the individual participation rate was relatively high, at least when compared to conventional e-mail surveys, the compounding effect of attrition resulted in the exponential attenuation of chains in terms of their length. The difficulty of gathering empirical data on large-scale social networks becomes manifest in this experiment. As in previous studies, senders resorted to friends much more frequently than they used business or family ties, even though almost half of these friendships were reported to be originated by either work or school affiliations. Successful chains, however, disproportionately involved professional ties and were likely to entail links that originated through work or higher education. As observed by Milgram, same-sex links were more common: men passed messages more frequently to other men, and women to other women. Geographical proximity of the acquaintance to the target and similarity of occupation accounted for at least half of all choices, thus corroborating the results of previous reverse small world experiments. However, the presence of highly-connected individuals, the hubs that appeared in Milgram's original experiments, was not found in this study: at most <eqn>5\%</eqn> of messages passed through any single acquaintance of any target. Participants rarely nominated an acquaintance because he or she had many friends. Moreover, individuals in successful chains were less likely than those in incomplete chains to send messages to hubs.
</item>

<item>
A larger experiment was performed on a snapshot of the <b>Microsoft Messenger</b> instant-messaging network. The whole Microsoft Messenger network contained 240 million nodes and 9.1 billion edges, but researchers analyzed a communication graph with 180 million nodes and 1.3 billion links, which was the largest social network analyzed at the time <cite>Leskovec and Horwitz 2008</cite>. The communication graph only included a link between two people if they had communicated during a one-month observation period. Therefore, experimenters did not consider friendship links through which no communication was detected during the observation period. They reported an average path length of 6.6 using this communication graph, an overestimation of the actual number.
</item>

<item>
A similar experiment involved the entire <b>Facebook social network</b> in May 2011, which then comprised more than 10 percent of the whole Earth's human population <cite>Ugander et al. 2011</cite> <cite>Backstrom et al. 2011</cite>. Lars Backstrom, a data scientist at Facebook, and his collaborators from the University of Milan analyzed a social network that included 721 million people and 69 billion friendship relationships, and they did so using just a single 24-core computer with a 1 terabyte hard disk!  Most Facebook users have less than 200 friends, and the median number of friends was 99 in this study <cite>Ugander et al. 2011</cite>, just above one tenth of a millionth of the global Facebook user base. Despite this small number, the team of researchers found that <eqn>99.6\%</eqn> of all pairs of users were connected by five degrees of separation, and <eqn>92\%</eqn> were connected by four degrees. The world, according to Facebook, is actually smaller than expected: the average distance between any two Facebook users was 3.74 degrees. Actually, it was even smaller than the average 4.28 degrees of separation registered by Facebook in 2008, when the network was smaller, a shrinking phenomenon that had already been observed in the evolution of networks over time <cite>Leskovec et al. 2005</cite>. In summary, four intermediary friends are usually enough to introduce anyone to a random stranger: <q>When considering another person in the world, a friend of your friend knows a friend of their friend, on average</q> <cite>Backstrom et al. 2011</cite>.
</item>

</list>



<!-- SIX DEGREES -->

<text>
The idea of six degrees of separation is often attributed to Milgram's original experiments on small worlds, where he reported an average length of 6 for the letter chains that were completed, somewhere between the results obtained from the analysis of the Microsoft Messenger and Facebook networks. However, the phrase <q>six degrees of separation</q> was popularized by a 1990 Broadway play of the same name written by John Guare, which would become a movie in 1993. One of the characters in that play states: <q>I read somewhere that everybody on this planet is separated by only six other people. Six degrees of separation. Between us and everyone else on this planet.</q> Guare, in an interview, attributed his awareness of the idea of six degrees of separation to the Italian inventor Guglielmo Marconi, who is often credited as the inventor of the radio. Milgram's findings, loosely interpreted, reinforced the notion of six degrees of separation, although he never used the phrase <q>six degrees of separation</q>. In his original paper <cite>Milgram 1967</cite>, however, he observed that the apparent closeness of the ends of the chains is misleading. Five is a small quantity, but five intermediate acquaintances represent <q>an enormous psychological distance</q>, <q>five circles of acquaintances apart</q> rather than just <q>five persons apart</q>. In some sense, people are not just six short steps apart, but six worlds apart, a change in the frame of reference that makes six degrees a much larger number.
</text>

<text>
The phrase <q>six degrees of separation</q> caught on and it has been incorporated into the scripts of many television shows and movies. Its widespread acceptance might also be related to the proliferation of some games:
</text>


<list>

<item>
The party game <term>Six Degrees of Kevin Bacon game</term>, was created in early 1994 by four Albright College students, Craig Fass, Christian Gardner, Brian Turtle, and Mike Ginelli. The game consists of linking any actor to Kevin Bacon through no more than six connections, where two actors are considered to be connected if they have appeared together in the same movie. The game became popular once it was featured by the mass media, it led to newsgroup thread with gripping titles such as <q>Kevin Bacon is the Center of the Universe</q>, and its creators even published a book whose prologue was written by Bacon himself. The web version of the game, called the <term>Oracle of Bacon</term>, was originally conceived and implemented in 1996 by Brett Tjaden at the University of Virginia. Available at <url>http://oracleofbacon.org/</url>, the Oracle builds on top of the Internet Movie Database, <url>http://www.imdb.com</url>, and, when queried by users, it automatically finds the shortest paths between any pair of actors on the graph defined by the IMDb. The Bacon number of an actor or actress is the number of degrees of separation between he/she and Kevin Bacon. Analyzing the IMDb, researchers have found that the average Bacon number for most actors is about 2.99, even though a significant fraction of the actors in the IMDb cannot be connected to Bacon. Curiously, analyses of the IMDb have shown that Kevin Bacon is not even in the top 400 list of the most central actors in the network, so we can conclude that he is certainly not the center of the Hollywood universe. Dennis Hopper, Harvey Keitel, Donald Sutherland, David Carradine, Udo Kier, Martin Sheen, Michael Caine, Max von Sydow, Michael Madsen, and Seymour Cassel are currently the top 10 actors in this list.
</item>

<item>
Mathematicians also have their own version of the Kevin number. A mathematician's <term>Erdös number</term> is the distance from him or her to Erdös in a graph connecting pairs
of mathematicians who have jointly authored a paper. Paul Erdös, a peculiar mathematician who was known for his Diogenes-like austerity<!-- and his battered suitcases-->, published 1,500 papers during his career, more than any other mathematician. Erdös has Erdös number 0, his 507 coauthors have Erdös number 1, his coauthors' coauthors have Erdös number 2, and so on. The average distance from a mathematician to Erdös is around 5 and many mathematicians indicate their Erdös number on their personal web pages.
</item>

</list>


<text>
Our desire to believe in a small world might bias our judgment and make us believe that the world is smaller than it is, actually. Psychological research provides explanations of why people may fall prey to the six degrees of separation illusion. When people experience an unexpected social connection, the event is likely to be vivid and salient in their memory <cite>Kleinfeld 2002a</cite>. Because of this, the small world might be just an urban myth <cite>Kleinfeld 2002b</cite>, we just do not know. Social networks tend to include very short paths between arbitrary pairs of people, but this fact might not have broader consequences. Whether there is always a path connecting every two people in the world is still a mystery.
</text>

<text>
Thanks to Milgram's experiments and others that followed, we know that society is not a random network. The folders in Milgram's experiments did not reach their destination bouncing randomly from person to person. Using local information and distributed knowledge, people were able to find and navigate paths that were not planned ahead of time, sometimes surprisingly short paths. In other words, large-scale social networks tend to have a very  small diameter, a feature we will discover in many other kinds of networks.
</text>

</document>



<document>
<tag>history-weak-ties</tag>
<title>Weak ties</title>

<text>
L: The small-world idea is related to the "weak ties" theory of Granovetter, who postulated
that social networks contain both strong (direct) and weak ties (long-distance
connections) that bind society together <cite>Granovetter 1973</cite>. In a cleverly titled paper,
"The strength of weak ties," Granovetter suggests that social networks are held
together by strong connections between friends and family members, as well as
weaker, long-distance connections among casual acquaintances. This explains why
it is possible to span a large sparse network in a small number of hops. The links
of a social network are like freeways and streets—freeways have few intersections
(nodes) and allow you to travel long distances without stopping. City streets, on
the other hand, allow you to pinpoint a single person or house within a dense neighborhood.
Freeways (weak ties) get you to a local neighborhood quickly, while streets
(strong ties) zero in on a specific person or house.

The strength proportional to the frequency (or intensity) of social interactions: 
- close friends (strong ties) vs. acquaintances (weak ties)
- dense clusters (strong ties) vs. low-density network (acquaintances)
- Information: local (received from strong ties) vs. from other parts of the network (received through weak ties)
- Lack of weak ties = disadvantaged position in the labor market
i.e. weak ties interconnect dense communities (the strength-of-weak-ties hypothesis)
i.e. weak ties provide access to remote information


K: ... the communication is balanced between staying within small organizational units and
cutting across organizational boundaries. This is an example of a much more general
principle in social networks – that strong ties, representing close and frequent social
contacts, tend to be embedded in tightly-linked regions of the network, whereas weak
ties, representing more casual and distinct social contacts, tend to cross between these
regions. Such a dichotomy suggests a way of thinking about social networks in terms
of their dense pockets of strong ties and the ways in which they interact with each
other through weaker ties. In a professional setting, it suggests a strategy for navigating
one's way through the social landscape of a large organization by finding the structural
holes between parts of the network that interact very little with each other. At a global
scale, it suggests some of the ways in which weak ties can act as “shortcuts” that link
together distant parts of the world, resulting in the phenomenon colloquially known as
six degrees of separation.
</text>

cf. <cite>Granovetter 1983</cite>

 
USN'2012: The most authoritative statement of the idea is Granovetter's 1982 reprise:

  
[O]ur acquaintances (“weak ties') are less likely to be socially involved with one another than are our close friends (“strong ties”). Thus the set of people made up of any individual and his or her acquaintances will constitute a low-density network (one in which many of the possible ties are absent), whereas the set consisting of the same individual and his or her close friends will be densely knit (many of the possible lines present).

  ...Ego will have a collection of close friends, most of whom are in touch with one another—a dense “clump” of social structure. Ego will [also] have a collection of acquaintances, few of whom know one another. Each of these acquaintances, however, is likely to have close friends in his or her own right and therefore to be enmeshed in a closely knit clump of social structure, but one different from Ego's… These clumps would not… be connected with one another at all were it not for the existence of weak ties. (Granovetter 1982, 105–106)

Interesting consequences of weak ties:

1) weak ties facilitate the flow of information from otherwise-distant parts of a network. Individuals with few weak ties will be deprived of information from distant parts of the social system and will be confined to the provincial news and views of their close friends.

2) weak ties help to integrate social systems. The macroscopic side of this communication argument is that social systems lacking in weak ties will be fragmented and incoherent. New ideas will spread slowly, scientific endeavors will be handicapped, and subgroups that are separated by race, ethnicity, geography, or other characteristics will have difficulty reaching a modus vivendi.

Complications

1) the definition of what constitutes a weak tie or relationship can be somewhat slippery. Is it the length of time one knows someone else, the frequency of interaction, the subjective “closeness” one feels, or whether the others one is connected with are defined as relatives, friends, or acquaintances? 

2) it is important to understand that the critical function of weak ties is one of bridges between network segments. As Granovetter puts it, “The importance of weak ties is asserted to be that they are disproportionately likely to be bridges as compared to strong ties, which should be underrepresented in that role. This does not preclude the possibility that most weak ties have no such function” (Granovetter 1982, 130). 

3) it must be the case that “(1) something flows through these bridges—they actually serve as conduits bearing information and influence to groups they otherwise would not get, and (2) whatever it is that flows actually plays some important role in the social life of individuals, groups, and societies” (ibid.). A flow can occur only under some circumstances. Passing along information or exercising influence should not be too costly to the weak tie that constitutes the bridge; otherwise, strong ties that are willing to bear the cost will be more effective in making the bridge. For example, if a mere acquaintance knows about a job (the original context of Granovetter's study), and the acquaintance does not need the job himself or herself, then there is little cost in passing along the information. It would take a strong tie to pass along information that might cause a loss to the person passing it along.


<cite>Granovetter 1973</cite>
<cite>Granovetter 1983</cite>

</document>

<!-- Network models -->

<document>
<tag>history-models</tag>
<title>Network models</title>

<text>
L: ... scientists in other fields began to use networks as models of physical and biological phenomena... pioneering work of Duncan Watts, Steven Strogatz, and Albert-Laszlo Barabasi ...
</text>

<text>
Small worlds (sparse networks with small diameter): <cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite>

Algorithm: initially construct a graph with regular structure. Next, apply rewiring to every link with probability p, such that p*m links are randomized (redirected to a randomly selected node). Parameter p is the rewiring probability, and m is the number of links in the original regular graph.

Watts and Strogatz: small worlds as networks with relatively short distances (hops) between node pairs chosen at random, even as the size of the network grows. Specifically, the diameter of a network increases as ln(n) while its size increases by O(n), where n is number of nodes.

</text>

<text>
Scale-free networks (nonrandom networks with hubs): <cite>Barabasi and Albert 1999</cite>


L: "the probability that a site has k links obeys a power law, which drops off quickly for large k"
... A network that follows a power-law distribution means that it has a
hub, and many other nodes with many fewer links than the average. This lopsided
preference for hubs seemed counter to nature, which typically follows a normal distribution.

L: "a microrule called preferential attachment - that the probability a site will obtain a new link is directly proportional to the number of links it already has" (the <q>rich get richer</q> phenomenon).

L: scale-free networks... The name came from observing that a function f(x) scales if f(ax) = a*f(x), which is
what a power law does. Therefore, if the degree sequence distribution obeys the power law, h(x) = x ^-q, then it is clear that h(ax) = (ax)^-q = (a ^-q)h(x) = a' h(x).
</text>

<text>
A small-world network has relatively small diameter and average path length, and a scale-free network has hubs.
= Small worlds had characteristic short path length, but power-law networks had hubs—nodes with extremely high degree.
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>history-timeline</tag>
<title>Timeline</title>

<text>
TIMELINE shown in Table <ref>table-milestones</ref>.
</text>

<dataset>
 <tag>table-milestones</tag>
 <title>Some milestones in the history of networks</title>
 <metadata>
  <field width="07">Year</field>
  <field width="50">Milestone</field>
  <field width="23">Reference(s)</field>
 </metadata>
 <record>
  <field>1736</field>
  <field>Bridges of Königsberg</field>
  <field><cite>Euler 1736</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1933</field>
  <field>Sociograms</field>
  <field><cite>Moreno 1934</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1951</field>
  <field>Spread of infection in random networks</field>
  <field><cite>Solomonoff and Rapoport 1951</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1953</field>
  <field><q>Status index</q>, i.e. Katz centrality index</field>
  <field><cite>Katz 1953</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1955</field>
  <field>Power law observed in word analysis</field>
  <field><cite>Simon 1955</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1959</field>
  <field>First generative procedure for random graphs</field>
  <field><cite>Gilbert 1959</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1960</field>
  <field>Random graphs</field>
  <field><cite>Erdos and Renyi 1959</cite> <cite>Erdos and Renyi 1960</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1967</field>
  <field>Small-world experiments</field>
  <field><cite>Milgram 1967</cite> <cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1972</field>
  <field>Influence in social networks</field>
  <field><cite>Bonacich 1972</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1973</field>
  <field>Granovetter: <q>Weak links</q> between clusters in job seeking</field>
  <field><cite>Granovetter 1973</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1978</field>
  <field>First theoretical examination of small worlds</field>
  <field><cite>Pool and Kochen 1978</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1995</field>
  <field>Generation of networks with arbitrary degree distributions</field>
  <field><cite>Molloy and Reed 1995</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1998</field>
  <field>HITS ranking algorithm</field>
  <field><cite>Kleinberg 1998</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1998</field>
  <field>Google PageRank</field>
  <field><cite>Page et al. 1998</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1998</field>
  <field>Watts-Strogatz small-world network model</field>
  <field><cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1999</field>
  <field>Barabasi-Albert scale-free network model</field>
  <field><cite>Barabasi and Albert 1999</cite></field>
 </record>
</dataset>



</document>

</document>
