<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [
  <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml">
  <!ENTITY history      SYSTEM "00-introduction-1-history.xml">
  <!ENTITY networks     SYSTEM "00-introduction-2-networks.xml">
  <!ENTITY properties   SYSTEM "00-introduction-3-properties.xml">
  <!ENTITY data         SYSTEM "00-introduction-4-data.xml">
  <!ENTITY tools        SYSTEM "00-introduction-5-tools.xml">
  <!ENTITY notes        SYSTEM "00-introduction-6-notes.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<title>Mining Network Data</title>


<quote author="Hal R. Varian" source="The McKinsey Quarterly, January 2009">
I keep saying the sexy job in the next ten years will be statisticians. People think I’m joking, but who would’ve guessed that computer engineers would’ve been the sexy job of the 1990s? The ability to take data—to be able to understand it, to process it, to extract value from it, to visualize it, to communicate it—that’s going to be a hugely
important skill in the next decades... Because now we really do have essentially free and ubiquitous data. So the complimentary scarce factor is the ability to understand that data and extract value from it.

<!--
Hal R. Varian
Google’s Chief Economist
Professor of Information Sciences, Business, and Economics
at the University of California at Berkeley 

During an interview for The McKinsey Quarterly...
 "Hal Varian on how the Web challenges managers"
 JANUARY 2009
 http://www.mckinseyquarterly.com/Strategy/Innovation/Hal_Varian_on_how_the_Web_challenges_managers_2286
-->
</quote>



<text>
Data mining can be defined as a set of techniques, the <q>non-trivial extraction of implicit, previously unknown and potentially useful information from data</q> <cite>Frawley et al. 1991</cite>, or a process, the <q>exploration and analysis, by automatic or semi-automatic means, of large quantities of data in order to discover meaningful patterns</q> <cite>Berry and Linoff 1997</cite>. Data miners need expertise on databases, due to the large data volumes they must deal with; artificial intelligence, for both knowledge representation and machine learning; human-computer interaction, for the presentation of results; and also statistics, for data summarization and model evaluation.
</text>

<text>
Most existing data mining techniques have been designed to work on highly structured data <cite>Han et al. 2011</cite> <cite>Tan et al. 2006</cite>. For example, many data mining algorithms have been devised to identify frequent patterns and sequences in transactional, relational, and multidimensional databases. Today's data, however, doesn't take the familiar form of the database. Many scientific and enterprise applications have to deal with more complex data. From the perspective of the data modeler, sophisticated structures and their relationships are best represented by non-linear data structures, which include trees, lattices, graphs, and, in general, networks. Chid Apte, director of analytics research at IBM and chair of the KDD'2011 conference, puts it bluntly: <q>The information's not coming at you in a clean tabular form, it's coming at you in a network form</q> <cite>Naone 2011</cite>. 
</text>

<text>
In their broadest sense, networks are no more than potentially heterogeneous multi-relational datasets that can be represented by means of attribute graphs (or hi-graphs, if we allow for hierarchical structures within networks). Nodes in such graphs represent objects, whereas edges or arcs represent links or relationships between those objects. Finally, attributes can be employed to label both nodes and links, thereby attaching information to network elements or their relationships. 
</text>

<text>
Networks are extremely useful for studying social phenomena (i.e. social network analysis), but also for modeling important biological and economic problems, which range from the the spread of infectious diseases to the dynamics of power distribution networks. They are also key for the analysis of the so-called content networks, which explicitly represent links between web pages, references in blog postings, retweets in Twitter, and citations in scientific papers or patents. 
</text>

<text>
The analysis of network data is crucial for many different application domains because, in complex systems, network topology (i.e. structure) is a often key factor in network behavior (i.e. dynamics). In other words, existing links between the elements within a network influence the behavior of the network as a whole. This influence, however, cannot be attributed to individual network elements. It is now widely recognized that complex systems cannot be described using a reductionist approach, i.e. teasing them apart and analyzing their components in isolation. In complex systems, the whole is more than the sum of its parts: interactions between individual components lead to a phenomenon known as emergence in the complex systems literature.
</text>


<text>
Understanding the dynamics of complex systems requires the analysis of their underlying networks, since results seem to correlate form with function, structure with behavior <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>. It is then no surprise that the study of network structure is fundamental in the construction of realistic models for complex systems.
</text>


<!-- The study of networks -->

<document>
<tag>study</tag>
<title>The study of networks</title>

<text>
<q>The ability for a graph to denote objects and their relationships to one another allow for a surprisingly large number of things to be modeled as a graph. From the dependencies that link software packages to the wood beams that provide the framing to a house, most anything has a corresponding graph representation.</q> <cite>Rodriguez and Neubauer 2010</cite>. 
</text>

<text>
If we keep a keen eye on our daily activities, we easily realize that networks of many different kinds permeate our lives. From the friendship networks that provide us support and leisure to the transportation networks that let us buy groceries at the supermarket down the street, from the complex social networks that shape modern societies to the communication networks that let us send instantaneous messages across the globe, we are surrounded by networks. Often unbeknownst to us, networks play a central role in determining who we meet, which job opportunities we get, which products we buy, how fads catch on, and how diseases spread. Social relationships, economic transactions, web pages, man-made technology, and natural processes all weave networks around us.
</text>


<!-- The field of study -->

<document>
<title>The field of study</title>

<text>
As a field of study, networks help us understand the behavior on complex systems. Complex systems are composed of many interacting parts that, as a whole, display collective emergent properties, which does not follow from the properties of the individual parts <cite>Newman 2011</cite>. If the behavior of such systems could be predicted by the behavior of their individual parts, they would be merely complicated, but not complex. The qualitative understanding of complex systems requires the development of (simplified) theoretical models, whereas its quantitative understanding involves the use of data mining techniques and computer simulation.
</text>


<text>
The study of networks, or complex systems if you like, is an interdisciplinary field that has attracted the attention of physicists, psychologists, anthropologists, sociologists, economists, information theorists, and computer scientists. Physicists, for instance, study networks as complex systems where nonlinear dynamics effects become clearly visible. Non-linear systems are highly sensitive to initial conditions and nonlinearity can lead to the emergence of chaos, deterministic non-periodic behavior that looks like randomness <cite>Gleick 1988</cite>. The sensitive dependence on initial conditions of non-linear systems leads to unpredictability and the provebial butterfly effect, a term coined by the mathematician and meteorologist Edward Lorenz, the father of chaos theory, from the thought experiment describing the formation of a hurricane depending on a remote butterfly flapping its wings. The interest of psychologists, anthropologists, and sociologists on networks is self-evident, given the importance of social networks for human individuals. Economists approach them from a different perspective, focusing on the behavior of markets and the spontaneous order that results from human action without the execution on any central plan. Information theorists focus on the ability to change and learn from experience in complex adaptive systems. Finally, computer scientists are fascinated by the algorithmic details of network-related problems and the possibilities that data mining and computer simulation offer to the analysis of complex phenomena.
</text>


<text>
It should be noted, however, that the study of networks often raises more questions than answers it provides, hence its scientific interest. Scientists studying networks try to understand:
</text>

<list>

<item>How interactions between elements give rise to the collective behavior of complex systems (emergence).</item> 

<item>How those systems interact with their environment (complexity).</item>

<item>The common principles that govern network behavior (network science).</item>

</list>

</document>


<!-- static structure and dynamic interactions -->

<document>
<title>Structure and dynamics</title>

<text>
Many fundamental scientific and technological problems can be posed in term of networks. For the analysis of the structural and dynamic properties of such networks <cite>Newman et al. 2006</cite>, novel data mining techniques, algorithms, and tools must be developed:
</text>

<list>

<item>Tools for analyzing the structural properties of complex networks (static point of view), but also</item>

<item>tools to make sense of the observable behavior that is caused by the interactions among the elements in a complex system (dynamic point of view).</item>

</list>

<text>
This simplistic categorization corresponds to the two key ingredients of the so-called network science <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>: the study of the structure of networks and the study of their dynamic behavior. But before we delve into the development of such tools, which will let us discover patterns in network structures and rich feedback effects in their dynamics, we must first establish a common ground.
</text>

<text>
A network is described <q>by its structure (e.g., nodes and links), and its behavior (what the network 'does' as a result of the interactions among the nodes and links).</q> In other words, networks are graphs that represent something real, <q>a representation or model of observable reality</q> <cite>NRC 2005</cite>. In some sense, we can view networks as graphs on steroids. In networks, graph vertices represent objects, which can be of different kinds, can be labeled, and can have attributes. Likewise, graph edges represent links between pairs of objects and they can also be of different kinds and have their own attributes. Formally, those links are called arcs when they are directed and edges when they are not.
</text>


<text>
The study of networks, as aggregations of nodes and links, encompasses the formulation of theories, the development of models, and their use in applications expressed in terms of <q>relational concepts</q>, i.e. <q>relationships defined by linkages among units</q> <cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>. Due to the interdisciplinary nature of the field, the particular terminology often varies depending on the background of the scientist, as the preceeding example from social network analysis illustrates. However, in the end, all we have are binary relationships between system elements, which are made explicit by the links that connect the nodes in a network.
</text>

</document>


<!-- Nodes and links -->

<document>
<title>Nodes and links</title>

<text>
Nodes and links are the constituent elements of networks:
</text>

<list>

<item><term>Nodes</term> represent elements in complex systems. They are also known as agents in complex systems, actors in social network analysis, and vertices in graph theory. In networks, nodes are supposed to be autonomous yet interdependent. Nodes in a social network might be people from a given group, departments within a corporation, whole corporations, public agencies, neighborhoods, cities, regions, and even nation-states. In other kinds of networks, they might represent atoms, molecules, genes, neurons, transistors, routers, transformers (in power grids), airports, geographical locations, Web pages, research papers, patents, legal cases...
</item>

<item><term>Links</term> coonect elements and they can receive many different names: connections, ties, arcs, edges, relations, and even <q>relational contents</q>. They represent the only channels through which resources can flow, let them be material (e.g. network packets in the Internet) or immaterial (e.g. information or gossip in social networks).
Connections in a social network may represent kinship, friendship, liking, romantic involvement, supervisor-employee relationships, interactions, transactions, resource flows, group co-membership, and other kinds of social ties, even several of these at the same time. In other kinds of networks, links might represent chemical bonds, gene interactions, contagions, synapses, wires, data links, power lines, airline routes, roads, Web links, citations...
</item>
</list>


<text>
In both natural and man-made systems, networks are created by the autonomous and spontaneous action of independent nodes that voluntarily come together and establish connections among them, rather than through central control or central planning <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>. Of course, this is not always the case, but centrally-planned networks are easier to analyze (provided that we know their plan) and we will be often more interested in unraveling the complexity of self-organized networks consisting of semi-autonomous individuals. Connections in a network provide opportunities for and impose constraints on the nodes of the network. 
</text>

</document>


<!-- Attributes -->

<document>
<title>Attributes</title>

<text>
From a network perspective, links between nodes (ties between actors in social network terms) are considered to be primary, whereas <term>attributes</term> are seen as secondary. However, they can often play an important role within networks, so we will have to take them into account. For example, a phenomenon known as homophily is common in social networks: people literally choose other people like them. Even though this sorting is not always easy to differentiate from peer effects, i.e. when we change our behavior to match those of people around us, both mechanisms create groups of people who look similar to each other (i.e. have similar attribute values).
</text>

<text>
In social networks analysis, attributes are known as <term>structural variables</term> when they are measured on pairs of actors, i.e. links. When they are defined at the level of individual actors, i.e. nodes, they are known as <term>actor variables</term> or <term>composition variables</term>. In the latter case, they are <q>of the standard social and behavioral science variety</q> <cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>, those which are measured in non-network studies.
</text>

</document>


<!-- Modes -->

<document>
<title>Modes</title>

<text>
<term>Modes</term> are the distinct sets of entities on which attributes are defined. In computer science terms, they represent the different types within a network. Most applications focus on networks that consist of elements of the same type (<term>one-mode networks</term>), albeit you can also find networks that are conformed by elements of different types (<term>multi-mode networks</term>). The mode of the network is then defined as the number of different types, i.e. different sets of entities on which structural or composition variables are measured.
</text>

<text>
When there are exactly two different kinds of nodes within the network, and also when there are two different kinds of links, networks are said to be <term>two-mode networks</term>. As particular examples, we can find: 
</text>

<list>

<item><term>Dyadic two-mode networks</term> that contain two sets of actors of the same kind: relations are dyads with the first actor in one set and the second actor in the other set (e.g. romantic relationships in a heterosexual population).</item>

<item><term>Non-dyadic two-mode networks</term>, or <term>affiliation networks</term>, that contain two different kinds of nodes, typically one set of actors and one set of events or activities, which define subsets of actors (e.g. club membership, attendance to social events, countries belonging to supranational organizations...).</item>

</list>

<text>
In both examples, the resulting networks can be formally interpreted as <term>bipartite networks</term>, whose links always connect nodes from two different sets that partition the set of nodes in the network. The difference lies in whether those nodes represent elements of the same nature (dyadic) or they correspond to elements of a different nature (non-dyadic).
</text>

</document>


<!-- Levels of analysis -->

<document>
<title>Levels of analysis</title>

<text>
Networks can be analyzed at different levels of detail <cite>Prell 2012</cite>. The basic modeling units that can be used in network studies include:
</text>

<list>

<item>Actors (nodes), as independent entities at the individual level.</item>

<item>Dyads (pairs of actors with or without a link without them).</item>

<item>Triads (triplets of actors).</item>

<item>Communities (subsets of actors).</item>

<item>The network as a whole.</item>

</list>

<text>
Specific techniques have been developed for each one of these modeling units or levels of analysis. The results they provide offer alternative perspectives on networks and they are  often complementary. Looking at individual actors corresponds to traditional non-network studies, which assume that the whole is just the sum of its parts, a reductionist approach that does not bode well on complex systems. Dyads and triads are the local building blocks of networks, whose census can provide some insight into the overall properties of the network (a rather crude form of network analysis). Communities correspond to clusters in AI terms and they can be detected by non-supervised machine learning techniques, which are known as community detection algorithms in this context. Finally, considering the network as a whole, metrics can offer a glimpse into the network structure at the macroscopic level.
</text>

<text>
A combination of techniques from each and every level will hopefully let us understand the connectivity of networks, who individual nodes link to, how communities are created and interact, and how whole networks evolve. The study of networks might help us understand how complex systems, why they are like they are, and what we can do about them. Often, however,  we will have to make do with mere hypothesis and rough models, which can still be useful in practice.
</text>

</document>

</document>


<!-- Sections -->
&history;
&networks;
&properties;
&data;
&tools;
&notes;

</document>
