<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>

<document>
<tag>kinds</tag>
<title>Kinds of networks</title>

<text>
++ Application domains with different terminology:
- Communication engineers think of networks as systems of routers and switches; 
- sociologists think of networks as influence diagrams representing the social interactions among humans;
- marketing business people think of networks as populations of buyers; 
- physicist thinks of networks as models of phase transition, magnetism...
- Biologists use the network metaphor to understand epidemics, genetics, and metabolic systems within cells
- Power engineers think of electrical power grids.
</text>

<document>
<tag>social</tag>
<title>Social networks</title>


<text>
e.g.
- nodes: individuals
- edges: social interaction
• “six degrees of separation”: the social distance between people is small

++
actor collaboration 
- nodes: actors
- edges: cast jointly
scientific coauthorship
- nodes: scientists
- edges: wrote a paper
</text>

<text>
The first use of the <q>social network</q> term is often attributed to John Arundel Barnes <cite>Barnes 1954</cite>, an anthropologist who conducted a field study to analyze the social structure and decision-making processes in Bremnes, a small island in western Norway. Since then, social networks denote patterns of ties that encompass many concepts used by the social sciences, including bounded groups (e.g., tribes or families) and social categories (e.g., gender or ethnicity).
</text>

<text>
Sociometry can be considered to be the precursor of social network analysis (and much of social psychology), as it was founded to measure interpersonal relations in small groups of people. Jacob Levy Moreno, the founder of sociometry, also pioneered the use of <q>sociograms</q> in the 1930's, e.g. <cite>Moreno and Jennings 1938</cite>. Sociograms are standard graph drawings used to depict the social links that determine the interpersonal structure of groups.
</text>

<text>
Widely used in the social and behavioral sciences, social network analysis focuses on the relationships among social entities <cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>. Depending on the particular context, these social entities can be individuals belonging to groups, corporations making economic transactions with other corporations, or nations signing treaties and trade agreements. The key ingredient in social network analysis is its focus on relationships, in contrast to reductionist approaches that limit their attention to the attributes of individual social entities.
</text>

<text>
Kinds of relations in a social network: 
- John Barnes (1972): attitudes, roles, and transactions.
- Knoke/Kuklinski (1982): individual evaluations (sentiments: friendship, liking, respect...), kinship (family ties: marriage and descent relationships), transactions or transfers of material resources (lending/borrowing, buying/selling, exchange of gifts), transfer of non-material resources (communication, i.e. sending/receiving information, let it be e-mail messages, advice, or mere gossip), interactions (e.g. attending the same event, hitting...), movement (physical, between locations, or social, between occupations), formal roles (boss/employee, teacher/student, doctor/patient...)...
</text>


Understanding social networks '2012:

"Some of the questions that are addressed, though hardly solved, are: What is the relationship between basic personality constructs and social relations? How do groups form? What is the nature and source of leadership? How can we best describe the way social positions relate to one another? What is the nature of authority in organizations and society? What are the ways of constructing efficient organizations that benefit their stakeholders? What is the nature of community, and how are people world-wide related to one another? How do new ideas spread and develop? What are the basic social resources of individuals and societies and how can they best be utilized? From time to time, we will reference classic social theorists to see to what extent social network ideas illuminate the problems that they posed. In this view, social networks are not only structural abstractions and the study of networks is not an alternative to classic ways of understanding society, but is a way of gaining greater insight into social life. Though networks also characterize the inanimate world such as electrical power grids, social networks have to be understood, to quote E. F. Schumacher (1973), <q>as if people mattered</q>.

"At each level of analysis—individual, organization, or nation-state, for example—what are the conditions that make it more or less likely that a path will exist between two nodes, that the nodes will have the same attributes, that they will be reciprocally or mutually related to one another, and that triads will be balanced? The answers lie in social theory.

<text>
Topics that have been studied by network analysts: occupational mobility, decision making, group problem solving, consensus and social influence, social perception, social support, community formation, exchange and power, social roles, coalition formation, company interlocking, markets, the world economic system, difussion and adoption of innovations...
</text>


Social scientists have investigated three kinds of networks: ego-centric, sociocentric, and open-system networks. 

- Ego-centric networks are those networks that are connected with a single node or individual,

- Socio-centric networks are networks in a “box.” Connections between children in a classroom or between executives or workers in an organization are closed system networks and the ones most often studied in terms of the fine points of network structure. 
- Open system networks are networks in which the boundaries are not necessarily clear, for example, the elite of the United States, connections between corporations, the chain of influencers of a particular decision, or the adopters of new practices. In some ways, these are the most interesting networks. 


<text>
Ego-centered networks (a.k.a. personal or local networks) consist of a focal actor, called ego, a set of alters who have ties to ego, and measurements on the ties among the alters, e.g. Facebook friends or people in your Google+ circles [difference between dichotomous links @Facebook vs. valued links @Google+, e.g. trusty friend, well-known, acquaintance, name associated to face, unknown]. Applications: study of the social envionment surrounding a given individual (you!) and what social scientists call social support, i.e. how social relationships can affect the emotional and physical well-being of a given individual.
</text>

<text>
Two students of Leslie White, a renowned anthropologists, offer complementary views on the forces behind cooperation [of people within societies].
<cite>Wright 2000</cite>. Whereas Robert Carneiro's focus was on pushing people together as the rational response against external threats, Elman Service thought that it was clear in some cases and probable in many others that neighboring societies were pulled together because of economic causes. Either by pushing or pulling people, opportunities for gain originate and draw people in closer cooperation, because of the benefits of participation in the total network. 
</text>

<text>
Jennifer Fewell, from Arizona State University, illustrates the importance of [insect] social networking using a professional basketball example <cite>Fewell and O'Donnell 2009</cite>. Phoenix Suns were successful, in part, because point guard Steve Nash passed the ball quickly to different teammates, making it difficult for defenders to predict their play. However, the Suns immediately started losing the first six games after Shaquille O'Neal joined the team, most likely because he destroyed his team's network dynamics: <q>Everybody there on the floor... knew where that ball was going to go - it was going to go to Shaq.</q> The network dynamics had changed and the success of the team depended on it, so they were forced to change their network dynamics again in order to improve their results with Shaquille O'Neal in the team. <q>It's a good example that the success of individuals depend on the network, and the success of the network depends on individuals. It's not just how good the individuals are... it's how good those interactions among them are as well.</q>
</text>



<text>
++ Obesity ;-) <cite>Christakis and Fowler 2007</cite>
</text>

<text>
++ Dunbar's number: http://www.technologyreview.com/blog/arxiv/26824/ 
+ http://arxiv.org/abs/1105.5170 Validation of Dunbar's Number In Twitter Conversations  @ Network structure chapter
</text>

<text>
++ Milgram's Six Degrees of separation (4.74 @ Facebook, http://arxiv.org/abs/1111.4503  http://arxiv.org/abs/1111.4570 ) @ Network structure chapter
W: Facebook's data team released two papers in November 2011 which document that amongst all facebook users at the time of research (721 million users with 69 billion friendship links) there is an average distance of 4.74. Probabilistic algorithms were applied on statistical metadata to verify the accuracy of the measurements. It was also found that 99.91% of facebook users were interconnected, forming a large connected component.
- Backstrom, Lars; Boldi, Paolo; Rosa, Marco; Ugander, Johan; Vigna, Sebastiano (2011-11-19). "Four Degrees of Separation". ArXiv. Retrieved 23 November 2011.
- Ugander, Johan; Karrer, Brian; Backstrom, Lars; Marlow, Cameron. "The Anatomy of the Facebook Social Graph". ArXiv. Retrieved 23 November 2011.
</text>


<text>
e.g. Karate club (a conflict divided the network into two communities), a small network often used to illustrate community detection algorithms

Wayne W. Zachary
An Information Flow Model for Conflict and Fission in Small Groups
Journal of Anthropological Research
Vol. 33, No. 4 (Winter, 1977), pp. 452-473
URL: http://www.jstor.org/stable/3629752

</text>

<text>
++ Cell phone network (conversations): millions of nodes and links

J. Candia, M. C. Gonzalez, P. Wang, T. Schoenharl, G. Madey, A.-L. Barabási 
Uncovering individual and collective human dynamics from mobile phone records 
Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical 41, 1-11 (2008). 

C. A. Hidalgo, C. Rodriguez-Sickert 
The dynamics of a mobile phone network 
Physica A 387:12, 3017-3024 (2008).

 J.-P. Onnela, J. Saramaki, J. Hyvonen, G. Szabo, D. Lazer, K. Kaski, J. Kertesz, A.-L. Barabási 
Structure and tie strengths in mobile communication networks 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 104 (18), 7332-7336 (2007).

J.-P. Onnela, J. Saramäki, J. Hyvönen, G. Szabó, M A. de Menezes, K. Kaski, A.-L. Barabási, J. Kertész 
Analysis of a large-scale weighted network of one-to-one human communication 
New Journal of Physics 9, 1-27 (2007).
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>content</tag>
<title>Content networks</title>

<text>
WWW: 
- nodes: web pages
- edges: hyperlinks - directed connections (references in web documents)
++ up to 60% reciprocal connections (two web pages can cite each other, something more uncommon in scientific papers)
[
Jean-Pierre Eckmann and Elisha Moses:
Curvature of co-links uncovers hidden thematic layers in the World Wide Web
PNAS April 30, 2002 vol. 99 no. 9 5825-5829
doi: 10.1073/pnas.032093399
]

= the largest network with topological information available.

@ 1 trillion unique URLs indexed by Google on July 25th, 2008, just on the Surface Web (access to the Deep Web is restricted)
i.e. unknown true size

[S. Lawrence, C. L. Giles, Nature 400, 107 (1999).]
Structure of a website [M. E. J. Newman and M. Girvan, Phys. Rev. E (2004]

L: The structure of the Internet and WWW: an emergent property of the decentralized Internet - that it had emerged without central planning into a structure consisting of a small number of extremely popular sites called hubs, and a large number of "unpopular" sites with few links (a scale-free network).


Origin: Tim Berners-Lee proposal of an hypertext system for CERN (European Laboratory for Particle Physics, Geneve, Switzerland)

In 1999, the average number of incoming and outcoming links per web page was about eight, an extremely sparse network...

1999 Kleinberg, Kumar, Raghavan, Rajagopalan, Tomkins: Formalized model of WWW as "Webgraph"
+ We call such networks Webgraphs, because they use graph theory to understand the World Wide Web (WWW).
(Kleinberg et al. 1999)
[Kleinberg, J. M., S. R. Kumar, P. Raghavan, S. Rajagopalan, and A. S. Tomkins, The Web as a
graph: Measurements, models, and methods, in T. Asano, H. Imai, D. Lee, S. Nakano, and
T. Tokuyama, eds, Proc. 5th Annual Intnatl. Conf. Computing and Combinatorics, Tokyo,
Lecture Notes in Computer Science, Vol. 1627, Springer-Verlag, Berlin, 1999.]



1999 Albert, Jeong, Barabasi: Diameter of the WWW (at least, within a small part of the Web, the nd.edu domain from the University of Notre Dame)
nd.edu with 325729 pages and 1469680 links
+ average path length estimated to be 0.35 + 0.89 ln n
+ clustering coefficient: 0.3 (ignoring the directedness of links)
[Albert, R., H. Jeong, and A.-L. Barabasi, Diameter of the World Wide Web, Nature 401:130-131 (1999).]
+ taking into account the directedness of links: very few short loops as compared to random models
[
Ginestra Bianconi, Natali Gulbahce, and Adilson E. Motter:
Local Structure of Directed Networks
Phys. Rev. Lett. 100, 118701 (2008).
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.100.118701
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevLett.100.118701
]


2000 Broder, Kumar, Maghoul, Raghavan, Rajagopalan Stata, Tomkins, Wiener: Full Webgraph map of the WWW
+ Group of computer scientists from AltaVista, IBM, and Compaq (now part of HP)
+ the first to fully map the WWW as a Webgraph and discover its structure
	- Giant weakly-connected component composed of a giant strongly-connected component (30%), a giant out-component, and a giant in-component, plus tendrils (25%)
+ Average directed path length around 16 for the 200M pages indexed by AltaVista at the time, i.e. a small world
+ Maximum separation (diameter): about 1000 !, not so small
+ Average in- and out-degree: 7.22 in May 1999, 7.85 in October 1999
+ Power law distribution with exponent 2.1 for in-degrees and 2.7 for out-degrees (range much narrower for out-degrees, obviously)
	- Doubts about the scale-free structure w.r.t. out-degrees
	- Scale-free network w.r.t. the in-degree distribution
[Broder, A., S. R. Kumar, F. Maghoul, P. Raghavan, S. Rajagopalan, R. Stata, A. Tomkins, and
J. Wiener, Graph structure in the web, Comput. Networks 33(1-6):309-320, (2000).]
[
D. Donato, L. Laura, S. Leonardi, S. Millozzi. 
Large Scale properties of the Webgraph.
European Physical Journal B, Vol. 38 (March 2004), pp. 239-243, 
doi:10.1140/epjb/e2004-00056-6
]

2000: Power law observed in the WWW
[Adamic, L. A. and B. A. Huberman, Power-law distribution of the World Wide Web, Science 287:2115 (2000).]

1999 Adamic: Distance between .edu sites shown to be small-world
[Adamic, L. A., The small world web, in Research and Advanced Technology for
Digital Libraries, Lecture Notes in Computer Science 1696, S. Abiteboul and
A.-M. Vercoustre, eds, Springer-Verlag, New York, 1999, 443-452.]


2002 Levene, Fenner, Loizou, Wheeldon: Enhanced Webgraph model concluded structure of the WWW couldn't be explained by preferential
attachment alone
[Levene, M., T. Fenner, G. Loizou, and R. Wheeldon, A stochastic model for the evolution of
the web, Comput. Networks 39:277-287 (2002).]


[Tadic, B., Growth and structure of the world-wide web: Towards realistic modeling, Comput. Phys. Commun. 147(1-2):586-589 (2002).
[Tadic, B., Temporal fractal structures: Origin of power laws in the world-wide web, Physica A 314(1-4):278-283 (2002).]

Broder, R. Kumar, F. Maghoul, P. Raghavan, S. Rajagopalan, R. Stata, A. Tomkins, J. Wiener. Graph structure in the web. 9th International World Wide Web Conference, May 2000.
J. Kleinberg, S.R. Kumar, P. Raghavan, S. Rajagopalan, A. Tomkins. The Web as a graph: Measurements, models and methods. Invited survey at the International Conference on Combinatorics and Computing, 1999.
K. Bharat and A. Broder. A technique for measuring the relative size and overlap of public Web search engines. Proc. 7th International World Wide Web Conference, 1998.
S. Dill, R. Kumar, K. McCurley, S. Rajagopalan, D. Sivakumar, A. Tomkins. Self-similarity in the Web. 27th International Conference on Very large Data Bases, 2001.

Web search, Link analysis, Spectral analysis.

J. Kleinberg. Authoritative sources in a hyperlinked environment. Proc. 9th ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms, 1998. Extended version in Journal of the ACM 46(1999). Also appears as IBM Research Report RJ 10076, May 1997.
[Taken] S. Brin and L. Page. The Anatomy of a Large-Scale Hypertextual Web Search Engine. Proc. 7th International World Wide Web Conference, 1998.
S. Chakrabarti, B. Dom, D. Gibson, J. Kleinberg, S.R. Kumar, P. Raghavan, S. Rajagopalan, A. Tomkins, Mining the link structure of the World Wide Web. IEEE Computer, August 1999.
[Taken] A. Arasu, J. Cho, H. Garcia-Molina, A. Paepcke, S. Raghavan. Searching the Web. ACM Transactions on Internet Technology 1(1): 2-43 (2001)
A. Borodin, J. S. Rosenthal, G. O. Roberts, P. Tsaparas, Finding Authorities and Hubs From Link Structures on the World Wide Web. 10th International World Wide Web Conference, May 2001.
A. Borodin, G. Roberts, J. Rosenthal, P. Tsaparas, Link Analysis Ranking: Algorithms, Theory and Experiments, ACM Transactions on Internet Technologies (TOIT), 5(1), 2005
P. Tsaparas, Using Non-Linear Dynamical Systems for Web Searching and Ranking, Principles of Database Systems (PODS), Paris, 2004
Dimitris Achlioptas, Amos Fiat, Anna Karlin, Frank McSherry, Web Search via Hub Synthesis. 42nd IEEE Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science, 2001, p.611-618.
[Taken] Davood Rafiei, Alberto Mendelzon. What is this Page Known for? Computing Web Page Reputations. Proc. WWW9 Conference, Amsterdam, May 2000
Pedro Domingos, Matt Richardson. The Intelligent Surfer: Probabilistic Combination of Link and Content Information in PageRank. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 14, 2002.
Taher H. Haveliwala. Topic-Sensitive PageRank. 11th International World Wide Web Conference, 2002.
Alon Altman and Moshe Tennenholtz. Ranking Systems: The PageRank Axioms. Proceedings of ACM EC 2005.
A. Y. Ng, A. X. Zheng, and M. I. Jordan. Link analysis, eigenvectors, and stability. International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI), 2001.
S. Chien, C. Dwork, R. Kumar, D. Simon, and D. Sivakumar, Link Evolution: Analysis and Algorithms
A. Y. Ng, A. X. Zheng, and M. I. Jordan. Stable algorithms for link analysis. 24th International Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR 2001).
L. Lovasz. Random Walks on Graphs: A Survey. Combinatorics: Paul Erdos is Eighty (vol. 2), 1996, pp. 353-398.
R. Lempel and S. Moran, Rank Stability and Rank Similarity of Link-Based Web Ranking Algorithms in Authority Connected Graphs, Information Retrieval 8 (special issue on advances in mathematics/formal methods in information retrieval), pp. 245-264, 2005.
Ziv Bar-Yossef, Alexander Berg, Steve Chien, Jittat Fakcharoenphol, and Dror Weitz. Approximating Aggregate Queries about Web Pages via Random Walks. 26th International Conference on Very Large Databases (VLDB), 2000, pages 535-544.
Soumen Chakrabarti, Mukul Joshi, Kunal Punera, and David M. Pennock. The structure of broad topics on the Web. 11th World Wide Web conference, May 2002.
Cynthia Dwork, Ravi Kumar, Moni Naor, D. Sivakumar. Rank Aggregation Methods for the Web. 10th International World Wide Web Conference, May 2001.
Weiyi Meng, Clement Yu, King-Lup Liu. Building Efficient and Effective Metasearch Engines. ACM Computing Surveys 34(2002).
T. Joachims. Optimizing Search Engines Using Clickthrough Data. Eighth International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining, KDD-2002.
Ron Fagin, Ravi Kumar and D. Sivakumar. Comparing top k lists, Extended abstract in 2003 ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA '03), pp. 28-36.
Ron Fagin, Ravi Kumar and D. Sivakumar, Efficient similarity search and classification via rank aggregation, Proc. 2003 ACM SIGMOD Conference (SIGMOD '03), pp. 301-312.
[Taken] J. Cho, S. Roy, Impact Of Search Engines On Page Popularity, WWW 2004
D. Liben-Nowell, J. Kleinberg. The Link Prediction Problem for Social Networks. Proc. 12th International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM), 2003.
Zoltán Gyöngyi, Hector Garcia-Molina. Link Spam Alliances. 31st International Conference on Very Large Data Bases (VLDB), Trondheim, Norway, 2005.
</text>

<cite>Liu 2011</cite>


<text>
++ Bibliographic <cite>Tang et al. 2008</cite>

ref. [D.J. de S. Price: "Networks of scientific papers", Science 149:150, 1965]

ref.
The architecture of complex weighted networks 
A. Barrat, M. Barthélemy, R. Pastor-Satorras, A. Vespignani
Journal-ref: Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 101 (2004) 3747.    
cond-mat/0311416


++ Semantic associations between terms
[Steyvers, M, J. B. Tenenbaum (2005). Cognitive Science 29(1): 41-78.]
Based on the University of South Florida Word Association, Rhyme and Word Fragment Norms
</text>


</document>

<document>
<tag>economic</tag>
<title>Economic networks</title>
</document>

<document>
<tag>transportation</tag>
<title>Transportation networks</title>


<text>
INTERNET as a transportation network (rather than a content network such as the WWW)

Router-level 
- nodes: routers, hosts (i.e. computers++) [billions of them]
- edges: wires/cables and wireless connections
- undirected
++ the complete structure of this network has never been analyzed (it cannot be analyzed?)

AS level (autonomous systems)
- nodes: autonomously-administered subnetworks (ISPs) [tens of thousands, including millions of routers]
- edges: gateway protocols (e.g. BGP), 2 ASs are connected by a link when two of their routers are directly connected
- undirected
++ geographical mapping is only partially possible (so it is often ignored)

1969 Original ARPANET with just 4 linked nodes @ University of California at Los Angeles, Stanford Research Institute, University of California at Santa Barbara, and the University of Utah

1988 Waxman: First graph model of the Internet
L: Waxman proposed a static graph theory model of the Internet in 1988 (Waxman, 1988). 
[Waxman, B. M., Routing of multipoint connections, IEEE J. Select. Areas Commun. 6(9):1617-1622 (1988).]

1999 Faloutsos brothers: Power law observed in Internet at the AS level
- for a small fraction of the Internet
[
Faloutsos, M., P. Faloutsos, and C. Faloutsos, 
On power-law relationships of the Internet topology, 
Proc. ACM SIGCOMM '99 Conf. Applications, Technologies, Architectures, and Protocols for Computer Communication 
in Cambridge, MA, USA, ACM Press, New York, 1999, pp. 251-262.
]
+ for a larger AS network (11000 ASs with 4.2 connections on average,October/November 1999) 
+ IR map (230000 Internet routers with 2.8 average degree, May 2001)
[
Romualdo Pastor-Satorras, Alexei Vázquez, and Alessandro Vespignani:
Dynamical and Correlation Properties of the Internet
Phys. Rev. Lett. 87, 258701 (2001)
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.87.258701
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevLett.87.258701
]
[
Alexei Vázquez, Romualdo Pastor-Satorras, and Alessandro Vespignani:
Large-scale topological and dynamical properties of the Internet
Phys. Rev. E 65, 066130 (2002)
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevE.65.066130
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevE.65.066130
]
</text>

<text>
AIRPORTS: 3880 airports and 18810 direct flight connections...

The architecture of complex weighted networks 
A. Barrat, M. Barthélemy, R. Pastor-Satorras, A. Vespignani
Journal-ref: Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 101 (2004) 3747.    
cond-mat/0311416

The role of the airline transportation network in the prediction and predictability of global epidemics 
V. Colizza, A. Barrat, M. Barthélemy, A. Vespignani
Journal-ref: Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 103 (2006) 2015. 
q-bio/0507029

Title: Vulnerability of weighted networks 
L. Dall'Asta, A. Barrat, M. Barthélemy A. Vespignani
Journal-ref: J. Stat. Mech. (2006) P04006. 
physics/0603163

The effects of spatial constraints in the evolution of weighted complex networks 
A. Barrat, M. Barthélemy, A. Vespignani
Journal-ref: J. Stat. Mech. (2005) P05003. 
physics/0504029

</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>biological</tag>
<title>Biological networks</title>

<text>
Cellular interaction networks: signal transduction, gene regulation, metabolism
</text>


<text>
2000: Jeong, Tombor, Albert, Oltvai, and Barabasi studied the networks of metabolic chemical reactions for 43 simple organisms, 
- small networks, from 200 to 800 nodes (chemical compounds)
- 43 sparse directed graphs
+ in- and out-degree distributions, approximately scale-fee with exponent 2.2
+ the lower the exponent, the wider the range of degrees and the more
[
H. Jeong, B. Tombor, R. Albert, Z. N. Oltvai, and A.-L. Barabási
The large-scale organization of metabolic networks
Nature 407, 651-654 (5 October 2000)
doi:10.1038/35036627
]

+ skewed metabolic reaction fluxes
[
E. Almaas, B. Kovacs, T. Vicsek, Z.N. Oltvai, A.-L. Barabási 
Global organization of metabolic fluxes in the bacterium Escherichia coli 
Nature 427, 839-843 (2004). 
doi:10.1038/nature02289
]

</text>

<text>
++ Life's complexity pyramid  <cite>Oltvai and Barabasi 2002</cite>

++ <cite>Barabasi and Oltvai 2004</cite> <cite>Guimera and Nunes 2005</cite> <cite>Boccaletti et al. 2009</cite>
++ <cite>Barabasi et al. 2011</cite>

+ A.-L. Barabási and Z. N. Oltvai. Network Biology: Understanding the Cell's Functional Organization. Nature Reviews Genetics 5, 101-113 (2004)
+ Kevin Bleakley, Gérard Biau and Jean-Philippe Vert. Supervised reconstruction of biological networks with local models. ISMB/ECCB 2007.


</text>

<text>
GENOME: protein-gene interactions

Regulatory networks:
- nodes: genes, proteins
- edges: translation or regulation (activating or inhibiting)

PROTEOME: protein-protein interactions


METABOLISM: Bio-chemical reactions
- Metabolism: sum of chemical processes by which energy is stored or released.
-Metabolic pathway: sequence of enzyme reactions.
- nodes: metabolites
- edges: reactions

Reaction networks
- nodes: substrates, enzymes
- edges: chemical reactions
</text>

<text>
Map of yeast protein-protein interactions, by Hawoong Jeong
[
H. Jeong, S. P. Mason, A.-L. Barabási, Z. N. Oltvai 
Lethality and centrality in protein networks 
Nature 411, 41-42 (2001).
doi:10.1038/35075138
]
+ The yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae
+ 1870 nodes (proteins) and 2240 undirected links (physical interactions between proteins)
+ Power law (exponent 2.5) with an exponential cut-off (actually, any finite network with a heavy tail must have a cut-off, i.e. an end-part of the distribution with a rapid decay)
+ General architecture similar to the Internet at the AS-level
</text>

<text>
The underlying network is not always easy to obtain...
e.g. genome 
- genes are expressed in terms of traits (features) of living organisms
- the expression of a gene is quantitatively described by its expression level
- the expression of a gene depends on other genes
- correlations between expression levels are treated as interactions between genes, revealing their potential cooperation 
++ suitable problem for weighted networks 
</text>

<text>
Food webs
- nodes: species
- edges: predator-prey relationships
- directed edges
</text>

</document>

</document>