<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
<tag>history</tag>
<title>Historical comments</title>

<text>
Before we start the study of a new discipline, it is always a good idea to learn something about its origins, the motivations that led people towards the problems that will be addressed, and hopefully solved, with the help network concepts. At the same time, we will get acquainted with the scientists whose pioneering work has shaped the field now called <term>network science</term> <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>. As we will see during the next few pages, the network hall of fame includes mathematicians, sociologists, physicists, and computer scientists.  
</text>


<text>
Graph theory is the starting point of modern network theory. In fact network theory rests on two main bodies of knowledge from a formal point of view: graph theory and game theory. Graph theory studies network structure, whereas game theory serves as the foundation for the study of network behavior, as it provides models of individual behavior in settings where outcomes depend on the behavior of others.
</text>

<!-- 18th Century: Euler -->

<document>
<tag>history-konigsberg</tag>
<title>Eulerian circuits: The Königsberg bridges</title>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-konigsberg</tag>
  <image scale="80" file="image/history/konigsberg"/>
  <title>The seven bridges of Königsberg.</title>
</figure>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-konigsberg-graph</tag>
  <image scale="30" file="image/history/konigsberg-graph"/>
  <title>The graph representing the seven bridges of Königsberg problem.</title>
</figure>

<text>
The origins of graph theory can be traced back to the work of Leonhard Euler, the famous 18th-century Swiss mathematician, on the Königsberg seven bridges problem. His paper on the solution to this problem in 1736 <cite>Euler 1736</cite> led to the development of two branches of mathematics: the already-mentioned graph theory but also topology, the study of shapes and their properties.
</text>

<text>
Königsberg is a seaport city known today as Kaliningrad, the Russian exclave between Poland and Lithuania on the Baltic Sea. The city was annexed by the Soviet Union at the end of World War II in 1945 and renamed in 1946 after the death Mikhail Kalinin, a Bolshevik who was the Chairman of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the USSR, i.e. the de jure head of state in the Soviet Union. When Euler lived, Königsberg was a Prussian city, located on the banks of the Pregel river, which also occupied two islands in the middle of the river. Four bridges connected the banks of the river to one of the islands, two bridges crossed the river to connect to the second island, and a seventh bridge connected the two islands, as shown in Figure <ref>fig-konigsberg</ref>.
</text>

<text>
At the time, nobody knew whether it was possible to take a walk from any point in the city, cross each bridge once, and return to the starting point, what is now known as an Eulerian circuit. Well, nobody was able to explain why it seemed so hard to find such a circuit until Euler proved that it was, in fact, impossible.
</text>

<text>
The banks of the Pregel river, the two islands on it, and the seven bridges in Königsberg can be modeled as a graph, a sketch of the problem that retains its key properties. The banks and the islands become the points in that sketch, i.e. the nodes in the graph. The seven bridges can now be displayed as curved lines that connect those four points, the network links in modern terms. Technically, such a sketch of the problem is a multigraph because there are multiple links between some pairs of nodes. The resulting network, therefore, contains four nodes and seven links, as depicted in Figure <ref>fig-konigsberg-graph</ref>.
</text>

<text>
As it always happens with good models, the graph representation of the Könisberg bridges problem removes unnecessary detail, such as the precise shapes of the islands and the forks of the river. This graph retains the essence of the problem and lets us focus on its connectivity properties. The number of links that arrive to a particular node is known as the node degree and a simple observation of this quantity solves the problem. Even nodes are those nodes with an even degree, whereas odd nodes are those nodes with an odd degree.
</text>

<text>
Euler went beyond the particular Königsberg bridges problem and he gave the necessary and sufficient condition for any arbitrary graph to admit a circular tour through all its nodes without going through the same link twice. It is just not possible to traverse such a network when there are more than two odd nodes.
</text>

<text>
How can be prove such a general result? Let us first consider even nodes. Every time we arrive to an even node through a particular link, we must leave that node through a different link, using up a pair of links. Obviously, we can easily traverse all the links that lead to an even node without problems. At odd nodes, however, there will always be a final single link, which we can use to return to the node. Once there, we will be stuck, since there are no remaining links that have not been traversed. Euler observed this fact to conclude that we cannot traverse a network without revisiting some links when there are more than two odd nodes. These nodes will necessarily be the starting and ending points of our tour through the network.
</text>

<text>
For the particular case of seven bridges of Königsberg, an Eulerian tour is impossible because all its four nodes have odd degrees: <q>the network cannot
be traced by one continuous stroke of a pencil without having to double back over paths that have already been traced</q> <cite>Danesi 2004</cite>.
</text>

<note>
<text>
It should also be noted that there will always be an even number of odd nodes, since links always connect pairs of nodes.
</text>
</note>

</document>

<!-- 19th Century -->

<!-- Trees -->


<document>
<tag>history-trees</tag>
<title>Trees: Electrical circuits and isomers</title>


<text>
Already in the 19th century, a particular kind of graph attracted the attention of some scientists: trees. From a formal point of view, trees are connected acyclic graphs. When there are no cycles, any pair of nodes in a network is connected by just a single path and the network becomes disconnected if a single link is removed. In this sense, trees are the smallest of the possible connected networks.
</text>

<text>
If we look at natural trees, those belonging to the plant category, and observe their branching structures, which are also without cycles, we can easily recognize why mathematicians borrowed some terms from biology to describe this kind of graphs. Apart from the tree term itself, the leaf term is often used to describe tree nodes with degree 1. Another analogy is established with forests, which are networks whose connected components are trees, i.e. sets of trees.
</text>

<text>
Trees implicitly appeared in the study of currents in electrical networks performed by Gustav Kirchhoff <cite>Kirchhoff 1847</cite>. Gustav Kirchhoff was a German physicist who, rather curiously, was born in our well-known city Königsberg, then in East Prussia. He established the foundations of circuit analysis and electrical engineering with his famous circuit laws in 1845:
</text>

<list>

<item>Kirchhoff's current law, KCL, also known as Kirchhoff's first law, Kirchhoff's point rule, Kirchhoff's junction rule, or Kirchhoff's nodal rule: At any node in an electrical circuit, the sum of currents flowing into that node is equal to the sum of currents flowing out of that node.</item>

<item>Kirchhoff's voltage law, KVL, also known as Kirchhoff's second law, Kirchhoff's loop rule, and Kirchhoff's mesh rule: The directed sum of the electrical potential differences, i.e. voltages, around any closed network is zero.</item>

</list>


<figure>
  <tag>fig-konigsberg-graph</tag>
  <image scale="50" file="image/history/tree-n-butane"/>
  <text></text>
  <image scale="41" file="image/history/tree-i-butane"/>
  <title>The two structural isomers of isobutane, <eqn>C_{4}H_{10}</eqn>: n-butane (top) and i-butane (bottom), also known as isobutane or 2-methylpropane.</title>
</figure>


<text>
Arthur Cayley, a British mathematician, introduced the term tree in 1857 without defining it formally <cite>Cayley 1857</cite>. Cayley used trees to count the number of different alkanes, chemical compounds also known as paraffins or saturated hydrocarbons. Alkanes, as all hydrocarbons, consist only of hydrogen and carbon atoms. They are bonded by single bonds, i.e. they are saturated compounds, and they do not contain cycles. Carbon atoms have 4 bonds, either C-C or C-H in hydrocarbons, i.e. their valency is 4. Hence the use of the term valency to refer to node degree in early graph theory monographs. The valency of hydrogen is 1: hydrogen atoms have a single bond to another atom, which is always an H-C bond in hydrocarbons. The resulting chemical formula for alkanes is always <eqn>C_{n}H_{2n+2}</eqn>. However, alkanes can present different structures depending on how their carbon atoms are bonded together: alkanes with more than three carbon atoms can be arranged in various different ways, forming structural isomers. Cayley studied such structures and organized them.
</text>


<text>
In graph theory, for any arbitrary connected network, we can define a spanning tree as a tree connecting all of its nodes. Kirchhoff's matrix tree theorem, which was named after Gustav Kirchhoff, shows that the number of spanning trees in a graph can be computed in polynomial time as the determinant of a matrix that is derived from the graph. In fact, it is a generalization of Cayley's formula <cite>Cayley 1889</cite>, which provides the number of different spanning trees in a complete graph. From an alternative point of view, Cayley's formula establishes that we can define <eqn>n^{n-2}</eqn> different trees on <eqn>n</eqn> labeled nodes.
</text>

</document>


<!-- Hamilton -->

<document>
<tag>history-icosian</tag>
<title>Hamiltonian circuits: The icosian game</title>

<text>
Sir William Rowan Hamilton, an Irish physicist and mathematician, is known to mathematicians for the quaternions, a number system that extends the complex numbers, and the theorem of Cayley-Hamilton in linear algebra (yes, the same Cayley we have just met when talking about trees). Hamilton was interested in the study of symmetries in the icosahedron, for which he devised the icosians, a specific set of quaternions.
</text>

<text>
A regular icosahedron is a regular polyhedron with 20 identical equilateral triangular faces, five of them meeting at each vertex. The regular icosahedron has 12 vertices and 30 edges. It is one of the five Platonic solids, which also include the tetrahedron, the cube or hexahedron, the octahedron, and the dodecahedron that eventually led to the icosian board game. A dodecahedron is, in general, any polyhedron with 12 flat faces. In particular, regular dodecahedrons are composed of 12 regular pentagonal faces, with three of them meeting at each vertex, 20 vertices and 30 edges.
</text>

<note>
<text>
You might have noticed that both icosahedrons and dodecahedrons have 30 edges. But, where the dodecahedron has 12 faces and 20 vertices, the icosahedron has 20 faces and 12 vertices. In fact, they are duals: the vertices of one correspond to the faces of the other.
</text>
</note>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-hamiltonian</tag>
  <image scale="30" file="image/history/Hamiltonian-path"/>
  <title>A Hamiltonian cycle in the dodecahedron graph. Source: Wikipedia Commons.</title>
</figure>


<text>
At the same time that Arthur Cayley introduced the term tree in his study of isomers, Hamilton devised the icosian game. The game was invented in 1857 with the name of <q>Around the World</q> and sold to a London game dealer for 25 pounds in 1859, just over 2500 current pounds if we adjust for inflation, i.e. somewhat more than 4000 current U.S. dollars. The goal of the game was finding a cycle along the edges of a dodecahedron so that every vertex is visited just once, no edge is visited twice, and the ending point is the same as the starting point. The game was commercialized as a pegboard with holes at the nodes of the dodecahedral graph, which is shown in Figure <ref>fig-hamiltonian</ref> with a solution to the game. Each node was labeled with the name of a city and players had to travel around the world following the edges of the map and visiting each city exactly once.
</text>

<text>
While we were interested in visiting all links without repeating them in Eulerian circuits, we have imposed a similar constraint on the icosian game, but defined over the nodes of the graph. Given the inventor of the icosian game, it comes as no surprise that circuits in which each node is visited just once are known as Hamiltonian circuits. Computers scientists know them well, since they are at the heart of the traveling salesman problem, an NP-hard problem in combinatorial optimization with important applications in many domains. Eulerian circuits, in contrast, can be found in linear time when they exist.
</text>

<note>
<text>
It should be noted that we can find Hamiltonian circuits in graphs that may or may not be Eulerian. The dodecahedral graph in Figure <ref>fig-hamiltonian</ref> is clearly Hamiltonian but not Eulerian, since all its nodes have an odd degree, i.e. 3.
</text>
</note>

</document>


<!-- Terminology -->

<document>
<tag>history-graphs</tag>
<title>The graph term: From linkages to graphs</title>

<text>
Historically, <term>linkage</term>s was the term sometimes employed to refer to graphs. The graph term was standardized by James Joseph Sylvester, a 19th-century British mathematician <cite>Gross and Yellen 2003</cite> <cite>Chartrand et al. 2011</cite>. 
</text>

<text>
J.J. Sylvester was known for his extraordinary ability to coin new terms and create notations for mathematical concepts. For instance, he invented terms such as discriminant, i.e. functions that give information about the roots of a polynomial. Many results in mathematics have been named after Sylvester, apart from a crater on the Moon and the Sylvester Medal. This medal, awarded by the Royal Society in London for the encouragement of mathematical research, has been received by Henri Poincaré, Georg Cantor, Alfred North Whitehead, and Bertrand Russell, among others.
</text>

<text>
Sylvester was the inaugural professor of mathematics at the new Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore, Maryland, where he founded the American Journal of Mathematics in 1878. The American Journal of Mathematics is the oldest continuously published mathematical journal in the United States. When it was created at the John Hopkins University, the only other mathematical journal in the U.S. was the Analyst, originally edited by Joel E. Hendricks and published in Des Moines, Iowa, from 1874 to 1883. The Analyst later became the Annals of Mathematics, published by the University of Virginia since 1884 and continued by the University of Harvard since 1899, until it finally settled at Princeton University in 1911. Since 1933, it is jointly published by Princeton University and the Institute for Advanced Study, also in Princeton, New Jersey, one of the most famous theoretical research centers in the world. Albert Einstein, John von Neumann, Kurt Gödel, and J. Robert Oppenheimer worked there, next to other prominent theoretical physicists, mathematicians, and economists at Princeton, such as Oskar Morgenstern, Paul Dirac, or Paul Erdös, who we will meet later in this chapter.
</text>

</document>


<!-- 20th Century -->

<document>
<tag>history-social-networks</tag>
<title>Sociometry and social network analysis</title>

<text>
Jacob L. Moreno was a Romanian-born Austrian-American psychotherapist who developed sociometry as a quantitative method for measuring social relationships in small groups. Sociometry is the precursor to social network analysis and much of social psychology.
</text>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-sociogram</tag>
  <image scale="80" file="image/history/sociogram1938"/>
  <title>A sociogram from <cite>Moreno and Jennings 1938</cite>.</title>
</figure>

<text>
While at Columbia University, Moreno devised the sociogram as a means for depicting the interpersonal structure of groups of people. In a sociogram, people are represented as points and relationships between pairs of people are represented by lines linking the corresponding points. First used at a meeting of the Medical Society of the state of New York in April 1933, sociograms were featured by The New York Times and they immediately caught on as a visual display of the effect of networks in, for example, the propagation of diseases.
</text> <!-- The New York Times, April 3, 1933, page 17 -->

<text>
The sociogram jumpstarted the study of sociometry <cite>Moreno 1934</cite>, which was further developed by Jacob Moreno and Helen Jennings <cite>Moreno and Jennings 1938</cite> <cite>Moreno and Jennings 1945</cite> with the goal of analyzing the relationship between social structures and psychological well-being, i.e. social and psychological behavior.
Pioneering work on sociometry was published in the journal Sociometry, edited and published by Moreno in 1937. The journal was transferred to the American Sociological Association in 1955. It as renamed as Social Psychology in 1978 and obtained its current name in 1979: Social Psychology Quarterly.
</text>

<text>
Sociometry focused on small group dynamics by representing positive and negative affective relations within human groups, such as linking, disliking, friendship, or enmity.
The visual display of social relations eventually led to the development of analytic techniques. Data collected to make relations explicit, a.k.a. relational data, can also be represented in matrix form. The resulting matrices are called sociomatrices by sociologists. In a sociomatrix, each cell quantifies the tie between two particular actors in the relation. When the relation is dichotomous or binary, i.e. 0/1, the sociomatrix is just the adjacency matrix of the graph depicted by the sociogram.
</text>

<text>
Leo Katz, Robert Duncan Luce, and Leon Festinger were among the first to use matrices to represent social network data:
</text>

<list>

<item>Elaine Forsyth and Leo Katz preferred the use of sociomatrices over sociograms <q>to present sociometric data more objectively, and to make possible a more detailed analysis of group structure</q> <cite>Forsyth and Katz 1946</cite>. Even though matrices are easier to manipulate from an algebraic point of view, Jacob Moreno still believed that the sociomatrix was not <q>superior and more objective in its presentation than the sociogram</q> <cite>Moreno 1946</cite>. At the time, when computers were not as available as they are today, he preferred direct visualization for making precise observations, sociograms over sociomatrices.</item> <!-- Moreno used his position as editor of Sociometry frequently to interject editor's notes into articles in his journal -->


<item>
Leo Katz, from Michigan State College, thought that the sociogram <q>had apparently reached the limits of its usefulness in the interpretation of sociometric data</q> <cite>Katz 1947</cite> and he proceeded to develop methods for quantifying relational data with the help of matrices and <q>matric operations</q> (sic). He considered some matrix operations and showed their interpretation in sociological terms. Some years later, in 1953, he would introduce a centrality measure or <q>status index</q> that computed the influence of an actor in a social network <cite>Katz 1953</cite>. This index, currently known as Katz centrality, is the forerunner of algorithms such as PageRank, the algorithm employed by Google to rank its search results <cite>Page et al. 1998</cite>.
</item>

<item>
Robert Duncan Luce, a renowned social scientist who held positions at Columbia University, the University of Pennsylvania, the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton, and the University of California at Irvine, introduced graph-theoretic methods into the social sciences. For instance, the French term <q>clique</q> refers to a complete subgraph in graph theory and, as a graduate student at MIT, Luce developed the first techniques for finding cliques in social networks by observing that cliques <q>have simple relationships to the powers of certain matrices</q> <cite>Luce and Perry 1949</cite> <cite>Luce 1950</cite>. His pioneering work set the stage for community detection algorithms, the name received by clustering algorithms when they are applied to network data.
</item>

<item>
At around the same time, Leon Festinger also applied matrix multiplication to sociomatrices and he described how the cube of the sociomatrix can determine the existence of cliques of various sizes and with various degrees of <q>cliquishness</q> <cite>Festinger 1949</cite>, a rather crude method for finding subgroups of similar actors in a network. No wonder Festinger is better known by his work on other areas of psychology, such as the Theory of Cognitive Dissonance, which suggests that an uncomfortable psychological tension appears when people are induced to behave in ways that are inconsistent with their beliefs.
</item>

</list>

<text>
A  monograph describing the application of graph theory to the social sciences was published by Frank Harary and Robert Z. Norman as early as 1953 <cite>Harary and Norman 1953</cite>.
The historical development of sociometry and other related areas that led to the social network analysis field is described, e.g., in <cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>, <cite>Kadushin 2012</cite>, and <cite>Prell 2012</cite>. 
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>history-random-graphs</tag>
<title>Random graphs</title>


<text>
L: Solomonoff and Rappaport were the first to apply the ideas of epidemics to RANDOM networks and they proposed the Gilbert model of random graphs, as it is known since it was rediscovered by E. N. Gilbert in 1959 
[Ray L. Solomonoff and Anatol Rapoport, Connectivity of random nets, Bulletin of Mathematical Biophysics 13:107-117 (1951).]
[Ray L. Solomonoff and Anatol Rapoport, An exact method for the computation of the connectivity of random nets, Bulletin of Mathematical Biophysics 14:153 (1952).]
</text>


<text>
L: 1959 Gilbert: First generative procedure for random graphs
+ first constructing a complete graph and then deleting randomly selected links until reaching the desired number of links 
[Gilbert, E. N., Random graphs, Ann. Math. Stat. 30(4):1141-1144 (1959).]
</text>

<!-- Erdos -->
<text>
L: The Hungarian mathematician Paul Erdos (1913-1996)... papers on random graphs ... today, we use the Erdos-Renyi (ER) random graph as a kind of benchmark—to compare with nonrandom graphs (ER model, 1959-1960)
+ inserting a link between randomly selected node pairs until the desired number of links is achieved.
[Erdo¨s, P. and A. Re´nyi, On the evolution of ra ndom graphs, Publ. Math. Inst. Hungar. Acad. Sci. 5:17-61 (1960).]
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>history-small-worlds</tag>
<title>Small worlds</title>


<text>
W: results in random graph theory show that even networks with no real topological structure exhibit the small-world phenomenon, which mathematically is expressed as the diameter of the network growing with the logarithm of the number of nodes (rather than proportional to the number of nodes, as in the case for a lattice).
</text>

<!-- Milgram -->
<text>
L: Stanley Milgram is credited with introducing the notion of a small-world network ...

... experiments reported in "The Small World Problem" in May 1967 (charter) issue of the popular magazine Psychology Today, with a more rigorous version of the paper appearing in Sociometry two years later <cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite>

In Milgram's experiment, volunteers in Kansas and Nebraska were asked to forward a letter to an unfamiliar target living in Cambridge and Boston, Massachusetts. Not knowing the target person, recipients forwarded the letter to an acquaintance closer to the target than themselves. Many of the letters were lost, but of the ones that eventually reached their target addresses, the number of hops along the chain of intermediaries ranged from 2 to 10, with an average of 5.2. Hence the notion of a small world and six degrees of separation was born.

... with a budget of only $680... a collection of 296 randomly chosen “starters” to try forwarding a
letter to a “target” person – a stockbroker who lived in a suburb of Boston. The starters
were each given some personal information about the target (including his address and
occupation) and were asked to forward the letter to someone they knew on a first-name
basis, with the same instructions, to eventually reach the target as quickly as possible.
Each letter thus passed through the hands of a sequence of friends in succession,
and each thereby formed a chain of people that closed in on the stockbroker outside
Boston... sixty-four chains that succeeded in reaching the target; the median length was six
... That so many letters reached their destination, and by such short paths,was a striking fact when itwas first discovered
... many letters never arrived

Actually, Milgram made two attempts: one starting from Wichita, Kansas, and the other from Omaha, Nebraska.  The one starting in Wichita, with a target person in Sharon, Massachusetts, resulting in only 3 completed chains. The second one was more successful...


K: Milgram himself mused about this in his original paper
[Stanley Milgram. The small-world problem. Psychology Today, 2:60–67, 1967.]; his observation, paraphrased slightly, was that if we think of each person as the
center of their own social “world,” then “six short steps” becomes “six worlds apart” –
a change in perspective that makes six sound like a much larger number.

K: overall conclusion has been accepted in a broad sense: social
networks tend to have very short paths between essentially arbitrary pairs of people

... invited human subjects from Kansas and Nebraska to participate
in a "communications project" to "better understand social contact in American
society." The experiment required them to send a folder across the country to a target
person defined by the experimenters.

Instructions:
1. Add your name to the roster at the bottom of this sheet, so that the next person
who receives this letter will know whom it came from.
2. Detach one postcard, fill it out, and return it to Harvard University. No stamp is
necessary. It allows us to keep track of the progress of the folder as it moves
toward the target person.
3. If you know the target person on a personal basis, mail this folder directly to
him/her. Do this only if you have previously met the target person and
know each other on a first-name basis.
4. If you do not know the target person on a personal basis, do not try to contact
him/her directly. Instead, mail this folder (postcards and all) to a personal
acquaintance who is more likely than you to know the target person. You
may send the folder on to a friend, relative, or acquaintance, but it must be
someone you know on a first-name basis.


WIKIPEDIA
Millgram's experiment developed out of a desire to learn more about the probability that two randomly selected people would know each other. This is one way of looking at the small world problem. An alternative view of the problem is to imagine the population as a social network and attempt to find the average path length between any two nodes. Milgram's experiment was designed to measure these path lengths by developing a procedure to count the number of ties between any two people.

Basic procedure
Though the experiment went through several variations, Milgram typically chose individuals in the U.S. cities of Omaha, Nebraska and Wichita, Kansas to be the starting points and Boston, Massachusetts to be the end point of a chain of correspondence. These cities were selected because they were thought to represent a great distance in the United States, both socially and geographically. <cite>Barabasi 2003</cite>
Information packets were initially sent to "randomly" selected individuals in Omaha or Wichita. They included letters, which detailed the study's purpose, and basic information about a target contact person in Boston. It additionally contained a roster on which they could write their own name, as well as business reply cards that were pre-addressed to Harvard.
Upon receiving the invitation to participate, the recipient was asked whether he or she personally knew the contact person described in the letter. If so, the person was to forward the letter directly to that person. For the purposes of this study, knowing someone "personally" was defined as knowing them on a first-name basis.
In the more likely case that the person did not personally know the target, then the person was to think of a friend or relative he knew personally who was more likely to know the target. He was then directed to sign his name on the roster and forward the packet to that person. A postcard was also mailed to the researchers at Harvard so that they could track the chain's progression toward the target.
When and if the package eventually reached the contact person in Boston, the researchers could examine the roster to count the number of times it had been forwarded from person to person. Additionally, for packages that never reached the destination, the incoming postcards helped identify the break point in the chain.

Results
Shortly after the experiments began, letters would begin arriving to the targets and the researchers would receive postcards from the respondents. Sometimes the packet would arrive to the target in as few as one or two hops, while some chains were composed of as many as nine or ten links. However, a significant problem was that often people refused to pass the letter forward, and thus the chain never reached its destination. In one case, 232 of the 296 letters never reached the destination.
However, 64 of the letters eventually did reach the target contact. Among these chains, the average path length fell around five and a half or six. Hence, the researchers concluded that people in the United States are separated by about six people on average. Although Milgram himself never used the phrase "six degrees of separation", these findings are likely to have contributed to its widespread acceptance.

In an experiment in which 160 letters were mailed out, 24 reached the target in his Sharon, Massachusetts home. Of those 24, 16 were given to the target person by the same person Milgram calls "Mr. Jacobs", a clothing merchant. Of those that reached him at his office, more than half came from two other men.
The researchers used the postcards to qualitatively examine the types of chains that are created. Generally, the package quickly reached a close geographic proximity, but would circle the target almost randomly until it found the target's inner circle of friends. This suggests that participants strongly favored geographic characteristics when choosing an appropriate next person in the chain.

Critiques

There are a number of methodological critiques of the Milgram Experiment, which suggest that the average path length might actually be smaller or larger than Milgram expected. Four such critiques are summarized here:

The "Six Degrees of Separation" Myth argues that Milgram's study suffers from selection and nonresponse bias due to the way participants were recruited and high non-completion rates. First, the "starters" were not chosen at random, as they were recruited through an advertisement that specifically sought for people who considered themselves as well-connected. Another problem has to do with the attrition rate. If one assumes a constant portion of non-response for each person in the chain, longer chains will be under-represented because it is more likely that they will encounter an unwilling participant. Hence, Milgram's experiment should under-estimate the true average path length. Several methods have been suggested to correct these estimates; one uses a variant of survival analysis in order to account for the length information of interrupted chains, and thus reduce the bias in the estimation of average degrees of separation.[Schnettler, Sebastian. 2009. "A small world on feet of clay? A comparison of empirical small-world studies against best-practice criteria." Social Networks, 31(3), pp. 179-189, doi:10.1016/j.socnet.2008.12.005]

One of the key features of Milgram's methodology is that participants are asked to choose the person they know who is most likely to know the target individual. But in many cases, the participant may be unsure which of their friends is the most likely to know the target. Thus, since the participants of the Milgram experiment do not have a topological map of the social network, they might actually be sending the package further away from the target rather than sending it along the shortest path. This may create a bias and over-estimate the average number of ties needed for two random people.

A description of heterogeneous social networks still remains an open question. Though much research was not done for a number of years, in 1998 Duncan Watts and Steven Strogatz published a breakthrough paper in the journal Nature. Mark Buchanan said, "Their paper touched off a storm of further work across many fields of science" (Nexus, p60, 2002). See Watts' book on the topic: Six Degrees: The Science of a Connected Age.
Some communities, such as the Sentinelese, are completely isolated, disrupting the otherwise global chains. Once these people are discovered, they remain more "distant" from the vast majority of the world, as they have few economic, familial, or social contacts with the world at large; before they are discovered, they are not within any degree of separation from the rest of the population. However, these populations are invariably tiny, rendering them of low statistical significance.

In addition to these methodological critiques, conceptual issues are debated. One regards the social relevance of indirect contact chains of different degrees of separation. Much formal and empirical work focuses on diffusion processes, but the literature on the small-world problem also often illustrates the relevance of the research using an example (similar to Milgram's experiment) of a targeted search in which a starting person tries to obtain some kind of resource (e.g., information) from a target person, using a number of intermediaries to reach that target person. However, there is little empirical research showing that indirect channels with a length of about six degrees of separation are actually used for such directed search, or that such search processes are more efficient compared to other means (e.g., finding information in a directory).[Schnettler, Sebastian. 2009. "A structured overview of 50 years of small-world research" Social Networks, 31(3), pp. 165-178, doi:10.1016/j.socnet.2008.12.004]


Kleinfeld's critique: Our desire to believe in a small world 
[J. Kleinfeld: "The small world problem (Could it be a big world after all? The 'six degrees of separation' myth)". Society, 39:62, 2002] 


LOL... A theoretical physicist would say that <q>it is dangerous to believe sociologists too much: (i) they have to work with poorly defined and ubjective material, (ii) they have to use poor statistics</q> <cite>Dorogotsev 2010</cite>. Sociologists will also have their own opinions on spherical elephants and other theoretical constructs often employed to simplify complex problems.

Beyond social networks, there is a branch of network theory that deals with the networks that appear associated to physical phenomena, though such networks tend to be considerably simpler than social networks. At least, they are not so messy.


FINDING: Travers and Milgram found that many of the completed chains passed through a small number of penultimate individuals (hubs)
– Mr. G, Sharon merchant: 16/64 chains (25%)
– Mr. D and Mr. P: 10 and 5 chains
Episcopalian minister for divinity school student target?

CRITICISM
- Small starting sample size.	
- Did not take into account incomplete chains when finding an average.


Conclusion:
Society is not a nonrandom network.
Instead of randomly bouncing from person to person, some folders reached their destinations and the path they followed was not planned out ahead of
time (there was no assurance that a chain of intermediaries existed between sender and receiver).


How?

USN: This corresponds to Killworth and Bernard (1978) who found in a reverse small world experiment (asking subjects how they would go about finding a particular person in a named city with a given occupation, sex, and ethnicity) that in choosing the category of the person who might help complete the chain, about half the choices were location and another half were occupation. Blau space was apparently invoked by most of the participants. The next variety of categories was less than 7%
ref. Killworth, Peter D., and H. Russell Bernard. 1978. The reverse small-world experiment. Social Networks 1:159–192


++ USN: One study, not of the whole world but an HP laboratory’s email network of 430 individuals (still relatively large), with a median number of 10 acquaintances and a mean of 12.9, showed that the communications were largely pegged to the formal hierarchical structure; focusing on individuals with high degree was not an effective connection strategy, rather, one looked to the official hierarchy (Adamic and Adar 2005)

ref. Adamic, Lada, and Eytan Adar. 2005. How to search a social network. Social Networks 27 (3): 187–203


+ Milgram's experiment inspired a 1990 Broadway play and movie by John Guare called <q>Six Degrees of Separation: A Play</q>.
K: A line uttered by one of the play’s characters: <q>I read somewhere that everybody on this planet is separated by only six other people. Six degrees of separation. Between us and everyone else on this planet.</q>
Wikipedia: Guare, in interviews, attributed his awareness of the "six degrees" to Marconi. Although this idea had been circulating in various forms for decades, it is Guare's piece that is most responsible for popularizing the phrase "six degrees of separation." Following Guare's lead, many future television and film sources would later incorporate the notion into their stories.


+ a more recent experiment using the Internet found that few of the chains were actually completed and concluded that, although in principle people were connected, the actual successes depended on their motivations and incentives (Dodds, Muhamad, and Watts 2003).
[Dodds, P. S., R. Muhamad, and D. J. Watts. 2003. An experimental study of search in global social networks. Science 301 (5634): 827–829.]

The Columbia Small Worlds Project:
– Dodds, Muhamad, Watts 2003
– web-based, email tracking
Basic methodology:
– 18 targets from 13 countries
– on-line registration of initial participants, all tracking electronic
– 99K registered, 24K initiated chains, 384 reached targets
Some findings:
– Less than  5% of messages through any penultimate individual
– large “friend degree” rarely (les than 10%) cited
– interesting analysis of navigation method vs. chain length


note (USN'2012): The number of steps was higher than the theoretical number because there were social structural barriers to network linkages. In the first experiment, Milgram reported that links between men and women were much less frequent than same-sex linkages, a finding repeated in the recent experiment. Similarly, there were barriers between social classes. Hence, personal agency or motivation became a factor in establishing linkages. Organizations, too, vary in the extent to which they actively seek to relate to other organizations and are skilled in this endeavor.

USN'2012: Milgram’s original experiment has been difficult to duplicate. In a recent attempt using email, more than 60,000 email users attempted to reach 18 target persons in 13 countries, but only 1.6% of the 24,163 chains reached their target (Dodds, Muhamad, and Watts 2003). Judgments about the number of steps and the strategies used by participants, given the tiny proportion of completed networks, are dubious in my view. The difficulty of gathering empirical data on large-scale social networks is illustrated by this study.



+ Facebook:  The best-known real-world study, in 1967, involved a few hundred people trying to send postcards to a particular Boston stockholder. Facebook's version, conducted in collaboration with researchers from the University of Milan, involved the entire social network as of May 2011, which amounted to more than 10 percent of the world's population. Analyzing the 69 billion friend connections among those 721 million people showed that the world is smaller than we thought: four intermediary friends are usually enough to introduce anyone to a random stranger. "When considering another person in the world, a friend of your friend knows a friend of their friend, on average," the technical paper pithily concluded

- Facebook's data scientist Lars Backstrom was able to work with a much bigger data sample. His social network had 721 million members at the time of the experiment - representing around 10% of the global population - with a total of 69 billion friendships between them. Despite the vast quantity of data, Mr Backstrom and four researchers from the University of Milan were able to crunch the data using a 24-core computer with a 1 terabyte hard disk
- Facebook limits users to having 5,000 friends, but the median figure was far lower at just 100 contacts, or 0.000014% of Facebook's total membership.
- Despite this relatively small number, the results showed 99.6% of all pairs of users were connected by five degrees of separation, and 92% were connected by four degrees.
- On average, the distance between any two members was 3.74 degrees.
- That was shorter than the average 4.28 degrees of separation registered by Facebook's 2008 membership, when the network was smaller.

J. Ugander, B. Karrer, L. Backstrom, C. Marlow.
The Anatomy of the Facebook Social Graph,
http://arxiv.org/abs/1111.4503
 
L. Backstrom, P. Boldi, M. Rosa, J. Ugander, S. Vigna.
Four Degrees of Separation,
http://arxiv.org/abs/1111.4570





+ Kevin Bacon game: created in early 1994 by four Albright College students, Craig Fass, Christian Gardner, Brian Turtle, and Mike Ginelli.
NOTE: On April 7, 1994, a lengthy newsgroup thread headed "Kevin Bacon is the Center of the Universe"
+ http://oracleofbacon.org/ - The Oracle of Bacon, created by Brett Tjaden of the University of Virginia originally conceived and implemented in 1996
NOTE: average Bacon number, for most actors in the IMDb, is approximately 2.9,
NOTE: In fact, Bacon does not even make the top 100 list of average personality number...


+ a mathematician’s Erdös number is the distance from him or her to Erdös in a graph connecting pairs
of mathematicians who have jointly authored a paper.
NOTE: Paul Erdös, well-known for his Diogenes-like austerity and his battered suitcases, published 1,500 papers during his career, with 507 coauthors. 
Erdös has Erdös number 0, his coauthors have Erdös number 1, his coauthors' coauthors have Erdös number 2, and so on.
The average distance from a mathematician to Erdös is around 5


[Kearns]
– large-scale social networks reliably have high-degree vertices
– large-scale social networks have small diameter
– furthermore, people can find or navigate the short paths from only local, distributed knowledge
– these properties are true of other types of networks, too

There must be some limits to degrees
– can’t be “close friends” with too many people (150? 1000?)
- Large N, small diameter and limited degrees are in tension (not all combinations are possible)
e.g. Let N be population size, M be the maximum degree, and D be the diameter: if M=2, then D ~ N/4 ( much greatear than 6 or log(N))

</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>history-weak-ties</tag>
<title>Weak ties</title>

<text>
L: The small-world idea is related to the "weak ties" theory of Granovetter, who postulated
that social networks contain both strong (direct) and weak ties (long-distance
connections) that bind society together <cite>Granovetter 1973</cite>. In a cleverly titled paper,
"The strength of weak ties," Granovetter suggests that social networks are held
together by strong connections between friends and family members, as well as
weaker, long-distance connections among casual acquaintances. This explains why
it is possible to span a large sparse network in a small number of hops. The links
of a social network are like freeways and streets—freeways have few intersections
(nodes) and allow you to travel long distances without stopping. City streets, on
the other hand, allow you to pinpoint a single person or house within a dense neighborhood.
Freeways (weak ties) get you to a local neighborhood quickly, while streets
(strong ties) zero in on a specific person or house.

The strength proportional to the frequency (or intensity) of social interactions: 
- close friends (strong ties) vs. acquaintances (weak ties)
- dense clusters (strong ties) vs. low-density network (acquaintances)
- Information: local (received from strong ties) vs. from other parts of the network (received through weak ties)
- Lack of weak ties = disadvantaged position in the labor market
i.e. weak ties interconnect dense communities (the strength-of-weak-ties hypothesis)
i.e. weak ties provide access to remote information


K: ... the communication is balanced between staying within small organizational units and
cutting across organizational boundaries. This is an example of a much more general
principle in social networks – that strong ties, representing close and frequent social
contacts, tend to be embedded in tightly-linked regions of the network, whereas weak
ties, representing more casual and distinct social contacts, tend to cross between these
regions. Such a dichotomy suggests a way of thinking about social networks in terms
of their dense pockets of strong ties and the ways in which they interact with each
other through weaker ties. In a professional setting, it suggests a strategy for navigating
one’s way through the social landscape of a large organization by finding the structural
holes between parts of the network that interact very little with each other. At a global
scale, it suggests some of the ways in which weak ties can act as “shortcuts” that link
together distant parts of the world, resulting in the phenomenon colloquially known as
six degrees of separation.
</text>

cf. <cite>Granovetter 1983</cite>

 
USN'2012: The most authoritative statement of the idea is Granovetter’s 1982 reprise:

  
[O]ur acquaintances (“weak ties’) are less likely to be socially involved with one another than are our close friends (“strong ties”). Thus the set of people made up of any individual and his or her acquaintances will constitute a low-density network (one in which many of the possible ties are absent), whereas the set consisting of the same individual and his or her close friends will be densely knit (many of the possible lines present).

  ...Ego will have a collection of close friends, most of whom are in touch with one another—a dense “clump” of social structure. Ego will [also] have a collection of acquaintances, few of whom know one another. Each of these acquaintances, however, is likely to have close friends in his or her own right and therefore to be enmeshed in a closely knit clump of social structure, but one different from Ego’s… These clumps would not… be connected with one another at all were it not for the existence of weak ties. (Granovetter 1982, 105–106)

Interesting consequences of weak ties:

1) weak ties facilitate the flow of information from otherwise-distant parts of a network. Individuals with few weak ties will be deprived of information from distant parts of the social system and will be confined to the provincial news and views of their close friends.

2) weak ties help to integrate social systems. The macroscopic side of this communication argument is that social systems lacking in weak ties will be fragmented and incoherent. New ideas will spread slowly, scientific endeavors will be handicapped, and subgroups that are separated by race, ethnicity, geography, or other characteristics will have difficulty reaching a modus vivendi.

Complications

1) the definition of what constitutes a weak tie or relationship can be somewhat slippery. Is it the length of time one knows someone else, the frequency of interaction, the subjective “closeness” one feels, or whether the others one is connected with are defined as relatives, friends, or acquaintances? 

2) it is important to understand that the critical function of weak ties is one of bridges between network segments. As Granovetter puts it, “The importance of weak ties is asserted to be that they are disproportionately likely to be bridges as compared to strong ties, which should be underrepresented in that role. This does not preclude the possibility that most weak ties have no such function” (Granovetter 1982, 130). 

3) it must be the case that “(1) something flows through these bridges—they actually serve as conduits bearing information and influence to groups they otherwise would not get, and (2) whatever it is that flows actually plays some important role in the social life of individuals, groups, and societies” (ibid.). A flow can occur only under some circumstances. Passing along information or exercising influence should not be too costly to the weak tie that constitutes the bridge; otherwise, strong ties that are willing to bear the cost will be more effective in making the bridge. For example, if a mere acquaintance knows about a job (the original context of Granovetter’s study), and the acquaintance does not need the job himself or herself, then there is little cost in passing along the information. It would take a strong tie to pass along information that might cause a loss to the person passing it along.


[Granovetter, Mark S. 1973. The strength of weak ties. American Journal of Sociology 78:1360–1380.]
[Granovetter, Mark S. 1982. The strength of weak ties: A network theory revisited. In Social structure and network analysis, edited by P. Marsden and N. Linn. Beverly Hills, Calif.: Sage.]

</document>

<!-- Network models -->

<document>
<tag>history-models</tag>
<title>Network models</title>

<text>
L: ... scientists in other fields began to use networks as models of physical and biological phenomena... pioneering work of Duncan Watts, Steven Strogatz, and Albert-Laszlo Barabasi ...
</text>

<text>
Small worlds (sparse networks with small diameter): <cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite>

Algorithm: initially construct a graph with regular structure. Next, apply rewiring to every link with probability p, such that p*m links are randomized (redirected to a randomly selected node). Parameter p is the rewiring probability, and m is the number of links in the original regular graph.

Watts and Strogatz: small worlds as networks with relatively short distances (hops) between node pairs chosen at random, even as the size of the network grows. Specifically, the diameter of a network increases as ln(n) while its size increases by O(n), where n is number of nodes.

</text>

<text>
Scale-free networks (nonrandom networks with hubs): <cite>Barabasi and Albert 1999</cite>


L: "the probability that a site has k links obeys a power law, which drops off quickly for large k"
... A network that follows a power-law distribution means that it has a
hub, and many other nodes with many fewer links than the average. This lopsided
preference for hubs seemed counter to nature, which typically follows a normal distribution.

L: "a microrule called preferential attachment - that the probability a site will obtain a new link is directly proportional to the number of links it already has" (the <q>rich get richer</q> phenomenon).

L: scale-free networks... The name came from observing that a function f(x) scales if f(ax) = a*f(x), which is
what a power law does. Therefore, if the degree sequence distribution obeys the power law, h(x) = x ^-q, then it is clear that h(ax) = (ax)^-q = (a ^-q)h(x) = a' h(x).
</text>

<text>
A small-world network has relatively small diameter and average path length, and a scale-free network has hubs.
= Small worlds had characteristic short path length, but power-law networks had hubs—nodes with extremely high degree.
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>history-timeline</tag>
<title>Timeline</title>

<text>
TIMELINE, excerpted and extended from <cite>Lewis 2008</cite>, shown in Table <ref>table-milestones</ref>.
</text>

<dataset>
 <tag>table-milestones</tag>
 <title>Some milestones in the history of networks</title>
 <metadata>
  <field width="07">Year</field>
  <field width="50">Milestone (author: result)</field>
  <field width="23">Reference(s)</field>
 </metadata>
 <record>
  <field>1736</field>
  <field>Euler: Bridges of Königsberg</field>
  <field><cite>Euler 1736</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1955</field>
  <field>Simon: Power law observed in word analysis</field>
  <field><cite>Simon 1955</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1960</field>
  <field>Erdös, Renyi: Random graphs</field>
  <field><cite>Erdos and Renyi 1959</cite> <cite>Erdos and Renyi 1960</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1967</field>
  <field>Milgram: Small-world experiments</field>
  <field><cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1973</field>
  <field>Granovetter: <q>Weak links</q> between clusters in job seeking</field>
  <field><cite>Granovetter 1973</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1978</field>
  <field>Pool, Kochen: First theoretical examination of small worlds</field>
  <field><cite>Pool and Kochen 1978</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1998</field>
  <field>Watts, Strogatz: First generative procedure for small worlds</field>
  <field><cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite></field>
 </record>
 <record>
  <field>1999</field>
  <field>Barabasi, Albert: Scale-free network model</field>
  <field><cite>Barabasi and Albert 1999</cite></field>
 </record>
</dataset>

<text>
1951 Solomonoff, Rappaport: Spread of infection in random networks
  [Solomonoff, R. and A. Rapoport, Connectivity of random nets, Bull. Math. Biophys. 13:107-117 (1951).]

1959 Gilbert: First generative procedure for random graphs
  [Gilbert, E. N., Random graphs, Ann. Math. Stat. 30(4):1141-1144 (1959)]

1972 Bonacich: Idea of influence in social networks leading to influence diagrams
  [Bonacich, P., Factoring and weighing approaches to clique identification, J. Math. Sociol. 2:113-120 (1972).]

1989 Bristor, Ryan: "Buying networks" i.e. application of network science to model economic system
  [Bristor, J. M. and M. J. Ryan, Applying the small world phenomenon to organizational buying, in M. Kochen, ed., The Small World, Ablex, Norwood, NJ, 1989, Chapter 4, pp. 87-99.]

1995 Molloy, Reed: Generation of networks with arbitrary degree sequence distribution
  [Molloy, M. and B. Reed, A critical point for random graphs with a given degree sequence, Random Struct. Algorithms 6:161-180 (1995).]

1998 Holland: Emergence in complex adaptive systems
  [Holland, J. H., Emergence: From Chaos to Order, Addison-Wesley, Reading, MA, 1998.]
</text>

</document>

</document>
