<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
<tag>history</tag>
<title>Historical comments</title>


<text>
K: two main bodies of theory that we will be building on: graph theory and game theory. These are theories of structure and behavior, respectively.
Graph theory is the study of network structure, while game theory provides models of individual behavior in settings where outcomes depend on the behavior of others.
</text>

<!-- 18th Century: Euler -->

<document>
<tag>history-konigsberg</tag>
<title>The Königsberg bridges</title>

<text>
1736: Leonhard Euler
++ Konisberg @ 0471648167 [Marcel Danesi] The Liar Paradox and the Towers of Hanoi.pdf
 
 The Prussian city of Königsberg, founded in 1255, was annexed by the Soviet Union at the end of World War II in 1945 and later renamed Kaliningrad in 1946 after the death of Chairman of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the USSR Mikhail Kalinin, one of the original Bolsheviks. This Russian city is on the banks of the Pregel river, part of it on two islands in the middle of the river: Four bridges connected the banks of the river to the island; two bridges cross the forks of the river, and one bridge connects the island to the landmass located between the forks. Figure <ref>fig-konigsberg</ref>.

"The history of graph theory began in 1736, when Euler <cite>Euler 1736</cite> first solved the
seven bridges of K¨onigsberg problem.) . In Euler's day there were seven bridges linking the banks and
two islands, which can be modeled as a multigraph with seven edges and four vertices.
Euler sought a way to walk over each of the bridges exactly once and return home - i.e.
, an Eulerian cycle. Euler proved that such a tour is impossible, since all four of the
vertices had odd degrees."

circular walk through the town of K¨onigsberg (now Kaliningrad) in such a way as to cross over each of the seven bridges spanning the river Pregel once, and only once... the precise shapes of the island and the other three territories involved are not important; the
solvability depends only on their connection properties. Let us represent the four territories by points (called vertices), and the bridges by curves joining the respective points; then we get the graph also drawn in Figure <ref>fig-konigsberg-graph</ref>.

Euler gave a necessary and sufficient condition for an arbitrary graph to admit a circular tour of the above kind...


</text>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-history-konigsberg</tag>
  <image scale="80" file="image/history/konigsberg"/>
  <title>The seven bridges of Königsberg.</title>
</figure>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-history-konigsberg-graph</tag>
  <image scale="30" file="image/history/konigsberg-graph"/>
  <title>The graph representing the seven bridges of Königsberg problem.</title>
</figure>

</document>

<!-- 19th Century -->

<!-- Trees -->


<document>
<tag>history-trees</tag>
<title>Trees</title>

<text>
Trees (i.e. connected acyclic graphs) implicitly appeared in the study of currents in electrical networks performed by Gustav Kirchhoff, while Arthur Cailey used them in 1957 to count chemical compounds.
</text>

</document>

<!-- Hamilton -->

<document>
<tag>history-icosian</tag>
<title>The icosian game</title>

<text>
The icosian game is a mathematical game invented in 1857 by William Rowan Hamilton. The game's object is finding a Hamiltonian cycle along the edges of a dodecahedron such that every vertex is visited a single time, no edge is visited twice, and the ending point is the same as the starting point. The puzzle was distributed commercially as a pegboard with holes at the nodes of the dodecahedral graph and was subsequently marketed in Europe in many forms.

The motivation for Hamilton was the problem of symmetries of an icosahedron, for which he invented icosians—an algebraic tool to compute the symmetries. The solution of the puzzle is a cycle containing twenty (in ancient Greek icosa) edges (i.e. a Hamiltonian circuit on the icosahedron).

a Hamiltonian path (or traceable path) is a path in an undirected graph that visits each vertex exactly once. A Hamiltonian cycle (or Hamiltonian circuit) is a Hamiltonian path that is a cycle.

J: In 1857 Sir William Rowan Hamilton (1805-1865, known to every mathematician
for the quaternions and the theorem of Cayley-Hamilton) invented the
following Icosian game which he then sold to a London game dealer in 1859
for 25 pounds; it was realized physically as a pegboard with holes. The corners
of a regular dodecahedron are labelled with the names of cities; the task is
to find a circular tour along the edges of the dodecahedron visiting each city
exactly once, where sometimes the first steps of the tour might also be prescribed.
More about this game can be found in [BaCo87]. We may model the
Icosian game by looking for a cycle in the corresponding dodecahedral graph
which contains each vertex exactly once. Such a cycle is therefore called a
Hamiltonian cycle. 

All platonic solids, including the dodecahedron in Figure <ref>fig-hamiltonian</ref>.
</text>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-hamiltonian</tag>
  <image scale="30" file="image/history/Hamiltonian-path"/>
  <title>A Hamiltonian cycle in a dodecahedron. Source: Wikipedia Commons.</title>
</figure>

</document>

<!-- Terminology -->

<document>
<tag>history-graphs</tag>
<title>The graph term</title>

<text>
Historically, <term>linkage</term>s was the term sometimes employed to refer to graphs. The graph term was later standardized by James Joseph Sylvester, a 19th-century British mathematician who founded the American Journal of Mathematics, the first mathematics journal in the United States <cite>Gross and Yellen 2004</cite> <cite>Chartrand et al. 2011</cite> .

W: James Joseph Sylvester (3 September 1814 – 15 March 1897) was an English mathematician. 
+ Sylvester invented a great number of mathematical terms such as discriminant.
+ In 1877 Sylvester again crossed the Atlantic Ocean to become the inaugural professor of mathematics at the new Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore, Maryland.
+ In 1878 he founded the American Journal of Mathematics. The only other mathematical journal in the U.S. at that time was the Analyst, which eventually became the Annals of Mathematics (now published  by Princeton University and the Institute for Advanced Study, originally edited by Joel E. Hendricks and published in Des Moines, Iowa, from 1874 to 1883; continued from March 1884 as the Annals of Mathematics, edited by Ormond Stone (University of Virginia): it moved to Harvard in 1899 before reaching its current home in Princeton in 1911; until 1933, when the Institute for Advanced Study took joint editorial control)

</text>

</document>

<!-- 20th Century -->


<document>
<tag>history-social-networks</tag>
<title>Social network analysis</title>

<text>
WF: THE SOCIOGRAM: This innovation, developed by Moreno along
with Jennings, marked the beginning of sociometry (the precursor to
social network analysis and much of social psychology).

Moreno was the founder of the field of sociometry - the measurement of interpersonal
relations in small groups... Driven by an interest
in understanding human social and psychological behavior, especially
group dynamics, Moreno was led to invent a means for depicting the interpersonal
structure of groups: the sociogram.

... people (or more generally, any social units) are represented as
points in two-dimensional space, and relationships among pairs of people
are represented by lines linking the corresponding points

+ revealed to the public in Apri1 1933 at a convention
of medical scholars, and was found to be so intriguing that the story was
immediately picked up by The New York Times (April 3, 1933, page 17),
and carried in newspapers across the United States

[Moreno, J.L. (1934). Who Shall Survive?: Foundations of Sociometry, Group
Psychotherapy, and Sociodrama. Washington, D.C. : Nervous and Mental
Disease Publishing Co. Reprinted in 1953 (Second Edition) and in 1978
(Third Edition) by Beacon House, Inc" Beacon, NY.]

[Moreno, J.L., and Jennings, H.H. (1938). Statistics of social configurations.
Sociometry. 1, 342-374.]

[Moreno, J.L., and Jennings, H.H. (1945). Sociometric measurement of social
configurations, based on deviations from chance. Sociometric Monographs,
No. 3. Beacon House, NY.]

</text>

<text>

WF: Sociometry is the study of positive and negative affective relations, such
as liking/disliking and friends/enemies, among a set of people. Relational data are often presented in  matrices termed sociomatrices.
A sociomatrix for a dichotomous relation is exactly the adjacency
matrix for the graph (or sociogram) quantifying the ties between the
actors for the relation in question...


WF: Visual displays... analytic techniques: that matrices could be used to represent
social network data. Forsyth and Katz
(1946), Katz (1947), Lucc and Perry (1949), Festinger(1949) were the first to use matrices in
novel methods for the study of social networks... and Harary and Norman (1953) monograph

WF: The first sociometricians published much of
their research in the journal Sociometry, which was renamed first Social
Psychology and then Social Psychology Quarterly in the late 1970's.
Moreno was Sociometry's founding editor (in 1937). The literature in the 1940's presented a variety of methods
for analyzing and manipulating sociomatrices:

Forsyth and Katz (1946) advocated the use of
sociomatrices over sociograms to standardize the quantification of social
interactions and to represent network data "more objectively"

Moreno actually preferred the use of sociograms to sociomatrices... Moreno used his position as editor of Sociometry frequently to
interject editor's notes into articles in his journal

Katz (1947) proposed a "canonical" decomposition of a sociomatrix
to facilitate the comparison of an observed sociomatrix to a target
sociomatrix,

Festinger (1949) applied matrix multiplication to sociomatriccs and described how
products of a sociomatrix (particularly squares and cubes) can be used
to find cliques or subgroups of similar actors

Luce and Perry (1949) and Luce (1950) proposed one of the first techniques to find
cliques or subgroups of actor

[Forsyth, E., and Katz, L. (1946). A matrix approach to the analysis of
sociometric data: Preliminary report. Sociometry. 9, 340-347.]
[Moreno, J.L. (1946). Sociogram and sociomatrix: A note to the paper by
Forsyth and Katz. Sociometry, 9, 348-349.]
[Katz, L. (1947). On the matric analysis of sociometric data. Sociometry. 1 0,
233-241.]
[Luce, RD., and Perry, AD. (1949). A method of matrix analysis of group
structure. Psychometrika. 14, 95-116.]
[Luce, R.D. ( 1950). Connectivity and generalized cliques in sociometric group
structure. Psychometrika. 15, 159-190]
[Festinger, L. (1949). The analysis of sociograms using matrix algebra. Human
Relations. 2, 153-158.]

[Harary, F., and Norman, R.z. (1953). Graph Theory as a Mathematical Model in
Social Science. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press.]
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>history-random-graphs</tag>
<title>Random graphs</title>

<text>
L: 1959 Gilbert: First generative procedure for random graphs
+ first constructing a complete graph and then deleting randomly selected links until reaching the desired number of links 
[Gilbert, E. N., Random graphs, Ann. Math. Stat. 30(4):1141-1144 (1959).]
</text>

<!-- Erdos -->
<text>
L: The Hungarian mathematician Paul Erdos (1913-1996)... papers on random graphs ... today, we use the Erdos-Renyi (ER) random graph as a kind of benchmark—to compare with nonrandom graphs (ER model, 1959-1960)
+ inserting a link between randomly selected node pairs until the desired number of links is achieved.
[Erdo¨s, P. and A. Re´nyi, On the evolution of ra ndom graphs, Publ. Math. Inst. Hungar. Acad. Sci. 5:17-61 (1960).]
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>history-small-worlds</tag>
<title>Small worlds</title>


<text>
W: results in random graph theory show that even networks with no real topological structure exhibit the small-world phenomenon, which mathematically is expressed as the diameter of the network growing with the logarithm of the number of nodes (rather than proportional to the number of nodes, as in the case for a lattice).
</text>

<!-- Milgram -->
<text>
L: Stanley Milgram is credited with introducing the notion of a small-world network ...

... experiments reported in "The Small World Problem" in May 1967 (charter) issue of the popular magazine Psychology Today, with a more rigorous version of the paper appearing in Sociometry two years later <cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite>

In Milgram's experiment, volunteers in Kansas and Nebraska were asked to forward a letter to an unfamiliar target living in Cambridge and Boston, Massachusetts. Not knowing the target person, recipients forwarded the letter to an acquaintance closer to the target than themselves. Many of the letters were lost, but of the ones that eventually reached their target addresses, the number of hops along the chain of intermediaries ranged from 2 to 10, with an average of 5.2. Hence the notion of a small world and six degrees of separation was born.

... with a budget of only $680... a collection of 296 randomly chosen “starters” to try forwarding a
letter to a “target” person – a stockbroker who lived in a suburb of Boston. The starters
were each given some personal information about the target (including his address and
occupation) and were asked to forward the letter to someone they knew on a first-name
basis, with the same instructions, to eventually reach the target as quickly as possible.
Each letter thus passed through the hands of a sequence of friends in succession,
and each thereby formed a chain of people that closed in on the stockbroker outside
Boston... sixty-four chains that succeeded in reaching the target; the median length was six
... That so many letters reached their destination, and by such short paths,was a striking fact when itwas first discovered
... many letters never arrived

K: Milgram himself mused about this in his original paper
[Stanley Milgram. The small-world problem. Psychology Today, 2:60–67, 1967.]; his observation, paraphrased slightly, was that if we think of each person as the
center of their own social “world,” then “six short steps” becomes “six worlds apart” –
a change in perspective that makes six sound like a much larger number.

K: overall conclusion has been accepted in a broad sense: social
networks tend to have very short paths between essentially arbitrary pairs of people

... invited human subjects from Kansas and Nebraska to participate
in a "communications project" to "better understand social contact in American
society." The experiment required them to send a folder across the country to a target
person defined by the experimenters.

Instructions:
1. Add your name to the roster at the bottom of this sheet, so that the next person
who receives this letter will know whom it came from.
2. Detach one postcard, fill it out, and return it to Harvard University. No stamp is
necessary. It allows us to keep track of the progress of the folder as it moves
toward the target person.
3. If you know the target person on a personal basis, mail this folder directly to
him/her. Do this only if you have previously met the target person and
know each other on a first-name basis.
4. If you do not know the target person on a personal basis, do not try to contact
him/her directly. Instead, mail this folder (postcards and all) to a personal
acquaintance who is more likely than you to know the target person. You
may send the folder on to a friend, relative, or acquaintance, but it must be
someone you know on a first-name basis.


WIKIPEDIA
Millgram's experiment developed out of a desire to learn more about the probability that two randomly selected people would know each other. This is one way of looking at the small world problem. An alternative view of the problem is to imagine the population as a social network and attempt to find the average path length between any two nodes. Milgram's experiment was designed to measure these path lengths by developing a procedure to count the number of ties between any two people.

Basic procedure
Though the experiment went through several variations, Milgram typically chose individuals in the U.S. cities of Omaha, Nebraska and Wichita, Kansas to be the starting points and Boston, Massachusetts to be the end point of a chain of correspondence. These cities were selected because they were thought to represent a great distance in the United States, both socially and geographically. <cite>Barabasi 2003</cite>
Information packets were initially sent to "randomly" selected individuals in Omaha or Wichita. They included letters, which detailed the study's purpose, and basic information about a target contact person in Boston. It additionally contained a roster on which they could write their own name, as well as business reply cards that were pre-addressed to Harvard.
Upon receiving the invitation to participate, the recipient was asked whether he or she personally knew the contact person described in the letter. If so, the person was to forward the letter directly to that person. For the purposes of this study, knowing someone "personally" was defined as knowing them on a first-name basis.
In the more likely case that the person did not personally know the target, then the person was to think of a friend or relative he knew personally who was more likely to know the target. He was then directed to sign his name on the roster and forward the packet to that person. A postcard was also mailed to the researchers at Harvard so that they could track the chain's progression toward the target.
When and if the package eventually reached the contact person in Boston, the researchers could examine the roster to count the number of times it had been forwarded from person to person. Additionally, for packages that never reached the destination, the incoming postcards helped identify the break point in the chain.

Results
Shortly after the experiments began, letters would begin arriving to the targets and the researchers would receive postcards from the respondents. Sometimes the packet would arrive to the target in as few as one or two hops, while some chains were composed of as many as nine or ten links. However, a significant problem was that often people refused to pass the letter forward, and thus the chain never reached its destination. In one case, 232 of the 296 letters never reached the destination.
However, 64 of the letters eventually did reach the target contact. Among these chains, the average path length fell around five and a half or six. Hence, the researchers concluded that people in the United States are separated by about six people on average. Although Milgram himself never used the phrase "six degrees of separation", these findings are likely to have contributed to its widespread acceptance.

In an experiment in which 160 letters were mailed out, 24 reached the target in his Sharon, Massachusetts home. Of those 24, 16 were given to the target person by the same person Milgram calls "Mr. Jacobs", a clothing merchant. Of those that reached him at his office, more than half came from two other men.
The researchers used the postcards to qualitatively examine the types of chains that are created. Generally, the package quickly reached a close geographic proximity, but would circle the target almost randomly until it found the target's inner circle of friends. This suggests that participants strongly favored geographic characteristics when choosing an appropriate next person in the chain.

Critiques

There are a number of methodological critiques of the Milgram Experiment, which suggest that the average path length might actually be smaller or larger than Milgram expected. Four such critiques are summarized here:

The "Six Degrees of Separation" Myth argues that Milgram's study suffers from selection and nonresponse bias due to the way participants were recruited and high non-completion rates. First, the "starters" were not chosen at random, as they were recruited through an advertisement that specifically sought for people who considered themselves as well-connected. Another problem has to do with the attrition rate. If one assumes a constant portion of non-response for each person in the chain, longer chains will be under-represented because it is more likely that they will encounter an unwilling participant. Hence, Milgram's experiment should under-estimate the true average path length. Several methods have been suggested to correct these estimates; one uses a variant of survival analysis in order to account for the length information of interrupted chains, and thus reduce the bias in the estimation of average degrees of separation.[Schnettler, Sebastian. 2009. "A small world on feet of clay? A comparison of empirical small-world studies against best-practice criteria." Social Networks, 31(3), pp. 179-189, doi:10.1016/j.socnet.2008.12.005]

One of the key features of Milgram's methodology is that participants are asked to choose the person they know who is most likely to know the target individual. But in many cases, the participant may be unsure which of their friends is the most likely to know the target. Thus, since the participants of the Milgram experiment do not have a topological map of the social network, they might actually be sending the package further away from the target rather than sending it along the shortest path. This may create a bias and over-estimate the average number of ties needed for two random people.

A description of heterogeneous social networks still remains an open question. Though much research was not done for a number of years, in 1998 Duncan Watts and Steven Strogatz published a breakthrough paper in the journal Nature. Mark Buchanan said, "Their paper touched off a storm of further work across many fields of science" (Nexus, p60, 2002). See Watts' book on the topic: Six Degrees: The Science of a Connected Age.
Some communities, such as the Sentinelese, are completely isolated, disrupting the otherwise global chains. Once these people are discovered, they remain more "distant" from the vast majority of the world, as they have few economic, familial, or social contacts with the world at large; before they are discovered, they are not within any degree of separation from the rest of the population. However, these populations are invariably tiny, rendering them of low statistical significance.

In addition to these methodological critiques, conceptual issues are debated. One regards the social relevance of indirect contact chains of different degrees of separation. Much formal and empirical work focuses on diffusion processes, but the literature on the small-world problem also often illustrates the relevance of the research using an example (similar to Milgram's experiment) of a targeted search in which a starting person tries to obtain some kind of resource (e.g., information) from a target person, using a number of intermediaries to reach that target person. However, there is little empirical research showing that indirect channels with a length of about six degrees of separation are actually used for such directed search, or that such search processes are more efficient compared to other means (e.g., finding information in a directory).[Schnettler, Sebastian. 2009. "A structured overview of 50 years of small-world research" Social Networks, 31(3), pp. 165-178, doi:10.1016/j.socnet.2008.12.004]


Conclusion:
Society is not a nonrandom network.
Instead of randomly bouncing from person to person, some folders reached their destinations and the path they followed was not planned out ahead of
time (there was no assurance that a chain of intermediaries existed between sender and receiver).

+ Milgram's experiment inspired a 1990 Broadway play and movie by John Guare called <q>Six Degrees of Separation: A Play</q>.
K: A line uttered by one of the play’s characters: <q>I read somewhere that everybody on this planet is separated by only six other people. Six degrees of separation. Between us and everyone else on this planet.</q>
Wikipedia: Guare, in interviews, attributed his awareness of the "six degrees" to Marconi. Although this idea had been circulating in various forms for decades, it is Guare's piece that is most responsible for popularizing the phrase "six degrees of separation." Following Guare's lead, many future television and film sources would later incorporate the notion into their stories.

+ Kevin Bacon game: created in early 1994 by four Albright College students, Craig Fass, Christian Gardner, Brian Turtle, and Mike Ginelli.
NOTE: On April 7, 1994, a lengthy newsgroup thread headed "Kevin Bacon is the Center of the Universe"
+ http://oracleofbacon.org/ - The Oracle of Bacon, created by Brett Tjaden of the University of Virginia originally conceived and implemented in 1996
NOTE: average Bacon number, for most actors in the IMDb, is approximately 2.9,
NOTE: In fact, Bacon does not even make the top 100 list of average personality number...


+ a mathematician’s Erdös number is the distance from him or her to Erdös in a graph connecting pairs
of mathematicians who have jointly authored a paper.
NOTE: Paul Erdös published 1,500 papers during his career, most mathematicians have Erd¨os numbers of at most 4 or 5

</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>history-weak-ties</tag>
<title>Weak ties</title>

<text>
L: The small-world idea is related to the "weak ties" theory of Granovetter, who postulated
that social networks contain both strong (direct) and weak ties (long-distance
connections) that bind society together <cite>Granovetter 1973</cite>. In a cleverly titled paper,
"The strength of weak ties," Granovetter suggests that social networks are held
together by strong connections between friends and family members, as well as
weaker, long-distance connections among casual acquaintances. This explains why
it is possible to span a large sparse network in a small number of hops. The links
of a social network are like freeways and streets—freeways have few intersections
(nodes) and allow you to travel long distances without stopping. City streets, on
the other hand, allow you to pinpoint a single person or house within a dense neighborhood.
Freeways (weak ties) get you to a local neighborhood quickly, while streets
(strong ties) zero in on a specific person or house.


K: ... the communication is balanced between staying within small organizational units and
cutting across organizational boundaries. This is an example of a much more general
principle in social networks – that strong ties, representing close and frequent social
contacts, tend to be embedded in tightly-linked regions of the network, whereas weak
ties, representing more casual and distinct social contacts, tend to cross between these
regions. Such a dichotomy suggests a way of thinking about social networks in terms
of their dense pockets of strong ties and the ways in which they interact with each
other through weaker ties. In a professional setting, it suggests a strategy for navigating
one’s way through the social landscape of a large organization by finding the structural
holes between parts of the network that interact very little with each other. At a global
scale, it suggests some of the ways in which weak ties can act as “shortcuts” that link
together distant parts of the world, resulting in the phenomenon colloquially known as
six degrees of separation.
</text>

</document>

<!-- Network models -->

<document>
<tag>history-models</tag>
<title>Network models</title>

<text>
L: ... scientists in other fields began to use networks as models of physical and biological phenomena... pioneering work of Duncan Watts, Steven Strogatz, and Albert-Laszlo Barabasi ...
</text>

<text>
Small worlds (sparse networks with small diameter): <cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite>

Algorithm: initially construct a graph with regular structure. Next, apply rewiring to every link with probability p, such that p*m links are randomized (redirected to a randomly selected node). Parameter p is the rewiring probability, and m is the number of links in the original regular graph.

Watts and Strogatz: small worlds as networks with relatively short distances (hops) between node pairs chosen at random, even as the size of the network grows. Specifically, the diameter of a network increases as ln(n) while its size increases by O(n), where n is number of nodes.

</text>

<text>
Scale-free networks (nonrandom networks with hubs): <cite>Barabasi and Albert 1999</cite>


L: "the probability that a site has k links obeys a power law, which drops off quickly for large k"
... A network that follows a power-law distribution means that it has a
hub, and many other nodes with many fewer links than the average. This lopsided
preference for hubs seemed counter to nature, which typically follows a normal distribution.

L: "a microrule called preferential attachment - that the probability a site will obtain a new link is directly proportional to the number of links it already has" (the <q>rich get richer</q> phenomenon).

L: scale-free networks... The name came from observing that a function f(x) scales if f(ax) = a*f(x), which is
what a power law does. Therefore, if the degree sequence distribution obeys the power law, h(x) = x ^-q, then it is clear that h(ax) = (ax)^-q = (a ^-q)h(x) = a' h(x).
</text>

<text>
A small-world network has relatively small diameter and average path length, and a scale-free network has hubs.
= Small worlds had characteristic short path length, but power-law networks had hubs—nodes with extremely high degree.
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>history-timeline</tag>
<title>Timeline</title>

<text>
TIMELINE, excerpted from <cite>Lewis 2008</cite>:

1736 Euler: Bridges of Königsberg <cite>Euler 1736</cite>

1951 Solomonoff, Rappaport: Spread of infection in random networks
  [Solomonoff, R. and A. Rapoport, Connectivity of random nets, Bull. Math. Biophys. 13:107-117 (1951).]

1955 Simon: Power law observed in word analysis <cite>Simon 1955</cite>

1959 Gilbert: First generative procedure for random graphs
  [Gilbert, E. N., Random graphs, Ann. Math. Stat. 30(4):1141-1144 (1959)]

1960 Erdos, Renyi: Random graphs <cite>Erdos and Renyi 1959</cite> <cite>Erdos and Renyi 1960</cite>

1967 Milgram: Small-world experiments <cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite>

1972 Bonacich: Idea of influence in social networks leading to influence diagrams
  [Bonacich, P., Factoring and weighing approaches to clique identification, J. Math. Sociol. 2:113-120 (1972).]

1973 Granovetter: Job-seeking networks formed clusters with "weak links" between them <cite>Granovetter 1973</cite>

1978 Pool, Kochen: First theoretical examination of small worlds <cite>Pool and Kochen 1978</cite>

1989 Bristor, Ryan: "Buying networks" i.e. application of network science to model economic system
  [Bristor, J. M. and M. J. Ryan, Applying the small world phenomenon to organizational buying, in M. Kochen, ed., The Small World, Ablex, Norwood, NJ, 1989, Chapter 4, pp. 87-99.]

1995 Molloy, Reed: Generation of networks with arbitrary degree sequence distribution
  [Molloy, M. and B. Reed, A critical point for random graphs with a given degree sequence, Random Struct. Algorithms 6:161-180 (1995).]

1998 Holland: Emergence in complex adaptive systems
  [Holland, J. H., Emergence: From Chaos to Order, Addison-Wesley, Reading, MA, 1998.]

1998 Watts, Strogatz: Frst generative procedure for small worlds <cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite>

1999 Barabasi, Albert: Scale-free network model <cite>Barabasi and Albert 1999</cite>
</text>

</document>

</document>
