<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<title>Mining Network Data</title>


<text>
A network is described <q>by its structure (e.g., nodes and links), and its behavior (what the network 'does' as a result of the interactions among the nodes and links).</q> In other words, networks are graphs that represent something real, <q>a representation or model of observable reality.</q> (National Research Council, Committee on Network Science for Future Army Applications: Network Science, Board of Army Science and Technology, National Academies Press, www.nap.edu, 2005).
</text>

<text>
Two key ingredients of networks <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>:
(1) the study of the structure of a collection of nodes and links that represent something real,
(2) the study of the dynamic behavior of the aggregation of nodes and links.
</text>

<text>
The study of networks encompasses theories, models, and applications expressed in terms of <q>relational concepts</q> <cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>. In other words, the relationships defined by the existing links among the elements of a complex system are the fundamental ingredient of networks, where
</text>

<list>

<item>Elements (also known as actors in social network analysis and nodes or vertices in graph theoretical terms) are autonomous but interdependent.</item>

<item>Links between elements (also known as connections, ties, relations, or even <q>relational contents</q>) represent the only channels through which resources can flow, let them be material or immaterial.</item>

</list>

<text>
L: A network forms by the autonomous and spontaneous action of independent nodes that "volunteer" to come together (link), rather than through central control or central planning
</text>

<text>
Connections in a network provide opportunities for and impose constraints on the elements of the network. Ties among elements are primary and attributes of elements are secondary (and they can often be understood in terms of the role they play within the network structure). 

+ results seem to correlate form with function and structure with behavior <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>.
</text>

<text>
Connections in a social network may represent kinship, friendship, liking, romantic involvement, supervisor-employee relationships, interactions, transactions, resource flows, group co-membership and other kinds of social ties... even several of these at the same time. In other kinds of networks, links might represent chemical bonds, contagions, synapses, wires, Internet links, bibliographical citations, roads,.
</text>

<text>
Nodes in a social network might be people from a given group, departments within a corporation, whole corporations, public agencies, and even nation-states... In other kinds of networks, they might be atoms, molecules, genes, transistors, routers, transformers (in power grids),Web pages, research publications, cities.
</text>

<text>
Most applications focus on networks of elements of the same type (one-mode networks), albeit you could also have networks conformed by elements of different types (multimode networks)...
</text>

<text>
++ Modes = distinct sets of entities on which the structural variables are measured. Single set (uni-mode networks), two sets (two-mode networks) or even more (multi-mode networks). 

The mode of the network = the number of sets of entities on which structural variables are measured.

- Dyadic two-mode networks (two sets of actors: relations are dyads with the first actor in one set and the second actor in a different set).

- Non-dyadic two-mode networks or affiliation networks (one set of actors and one set of events or activities, which define subsets of actors).
</text>

<text>
++ Attributes: structural variables (measured on pairs of actors, i.e. links) and actor variables (a.k.a. composition variables, defined at the level of individual actors [i.e. <q>of the standard social and behavioral science variety</q> <cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>, those measured in non-network studies]).
</text>

<text>
Modeling units (level at which network data are studied): actor, dyad (pair of actors), triad (triple of actors), subset of actors, the network as a whole.
</text>

<text>
++ the need to understand the interconnectivity of our relationship with customers and the groups they interact with, whom, how and why.
</text>

<text>
Need for new data mining techniques ++ Today's data, however, doesn't take the familiar form of the database. <q>The information's not coming at you in a clean tabular form, it's coming at you in a network form.</q> [Chid Apte, director of analytics research at IBM and chair of the KDD'2011 conference]. It arrives in a graph, that records not only the complex connections between nodes but also other types of information in a diversity of formats (e.g. the videos, images, and comments that people post on social networks). Social media may have started the trend toward analyzing such graphs, Apte says, but network data comes from other sources as well-for example, from complex engineering systems such as the electric power grid, water distribution systems, and traffic management systems. <cite>Naone 2011</cite>
</text>






<text>
++ <cite>Amaral and Ottino 2004</cite> <cite>Kim and Wilhelm 2008</cite>
</text>


<text>
L: Selection of topics about what some have called <term>network science</term> <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>: <q>one has to include the work of pioneers such as Adamic, Albert, Barabasi, Barrat, Bollobas, Erdos, Granovetter, Kephart, Lin, Liu, Mihail, Milgram, Molloy, Moore, Newman, Pastor-Satorras, Renyi, Strogatz, Tadic, Wang, Watts, Weigt, White, Zhang, and Zhu.</q>
</text>


<document>
<tag>history</tag>
<title>Historical comments</title>

<!-- 18th Century: Euler -->

<text>
1736: Leonhard Euler
++ Konisberg @ 0471648167 [Marcel Danesi] The Liar Paradox and the Towers of Hanoi.pdf
 
 The German city of Königsberg, founded in 1255, was annexed by the Soviet Union at the end of World War II in 1945 and later renamed Kaliningrad in 1946 after the death of Chairman of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the USSR Mikhail Kalinin, one of the original Bolsheviks. This Russian city is on the banks of the Pregel river, part of it on two islands in the middle of the river: Four bridges connected the banks of the river to the island; two bridges cross the forks of the river, and one bridge connects the island to the landmass located between the forks. Figure <ref>fig-konigsberg</ref>.

"The history of graph theory began in 1736, when Euler [Eul36] first solved the
seven bridges of K¨onigsberg problem.) . In Euler's day there were seven bridges linking the banks and
two islands, which can be modeled as a multigraph with seven edges and four vertices.
Euler sought a way to walk over each of the bridges exactly once and return home - i.e.
, an Eulerian cycle. Euler proved that such a tour is impossible, since all four of the
vertices had odd degrees."

circular walk through the town of K¨onigsberg (now Kaliningrad) in such a way as to cross over each of the seven bridges spanning the river Pregel once, and only once... the precise shapes of the island and the other three territories involved are not important; the
solvability depends only on their connection properties. Let us represent the four territories by points (called vertices), and the bridges by curves joining the respective points; then we get the graph also drawn in Figure <ref>fig-konigsberg-graph</ref>.

Euler gave a necessary and sufficient condition for an arbitrary graph to admit a circular tour of the above kind...


</text>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-konigsberg</tag>
  <image scale="80" file="image/history/konigsberg"/>
  <title>The seven bridges of Königsberg.</title>
</figure>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-konigsberg-graph</tag>
  <image scale="30" file="image/history/konigsberg-graph"/>
  <title>The graph representing the seven bridges of Königsberg problem.</title>
</figure>

<!-- 19th Century -->

<!-- Trees -->

<text>
Trees (i.e. connected acyclic graphs) implicitly appeared in the study of currents in electrical networks performed by Gustav Kirchhoff, while Arthur Cailey used them in 1957 to count chemical compounds.
</text>

<!-- Hamilton -->

<text>
The icosian game is a mathematical game invented in 1857 by William Rowan Hamilton. The game's object is finding a Hamiltonian cycle along the edges of a dodecahedron such that every vertex is visited a single time, no edge is visited twice, and the ending point is the same as the starting point. The puzzle was distributed commercially as a pegboard with holes at the nodes of the dodecahedral graph and was subsequently marketed in Europe in many forms.

The motivation for Hamilton was the problem of symmetries of an icosahedron, for which he invented icosians—an algebraic tool to compute the symmetries. The solution of the puzzle is a cycle containing twenty (in ancient Greek icosa) edges (i.e. a Hamiltonian circuit on the icosahedron).

a Hamiltonian path (or traceable path) is a path in an undirected graph that visits each vertex exactly once. A Hamiltonian cycle (or Hamiltonian circuit) is a Hamiltonian path that is a cycle.

J: In 1857 Sir William Rowan Hamilton (1805-1865, known to every mathematician
for the quaternions and the theorem of Cayley-Hamilton) invented the
following Icosian game which he then sold to a London game dealer in 1859
for 25 pounds; it was realized physically as a pegboard with holes. The corners
of a regular dodecahedron are labelled with the names of cities; the task is
to find a circular tour along the edges of the dodecahedron visiting each city
exactly once, where sometimes the first steps of the tour might also be prescribed.
More about this game can be found in [BaCo87]. We may model the
Icosian game by looking for a cycle in the corresponding dodecahedral graph
which contains each vertex exactly once. Such a cycle is therefore called a
Hamiltonian cycle. In Figure 1.7 we give a solution for Hamilton's original
problem.

All platonic solids, including the dodecahedron in Figure <ref>fig-hamiltonian</ref>.
</text>

<figure>
  <tag>fig-hamiltonian</tag>
  <image scale="30" file="image/history/Hamiltonian-path"/>
  <title>A Hamiltonian cycle in a dodecahedron. Source: Wikipedia Commons.</title>
</figure>

<!-- Terminology -->

<text>
Historically, <i>linkages</i> was the term sometimes employed to refer to graphs. The graph term was later standardized by James Joseph Sylvester, a 19th-century British mathematician who founded the American Journal of Mathematics, the first mathematics journal in the United States <cite>Chartrand et al. 2011</cite>.
</text>

<!-- 20th Century -->

<text>
RANDOM GRAPHS
</text>

<text>
L: 1959 Gilbert: First generative procedure for random graphs
+ first constructing a complete graph and then deleting randomly selected links until reaching the desired number of links 
[Gilbert, E. N., Random graphs, Ann. Math. Stat. 30(4):1141-1144 (1959).]
</text>

<!-- Erdos -->
<text>
L: The Hungarian mathematician Paul Erdos (1913-1996)... papers on random graphs ... today, we use the Erdos-Renyi (ER) random graph as a kind of benchmark—to compare with nonrandom graphs (ER model, 1959-1960)
+ inserting a link between randomly selected node pairs until the desired number of links is achieved.
[Erdo¨s, P. and A. Re´nyi, On the evolution of ra ndom graphs, Publ. Math. Inst. Hungar. Acad. Sci. 5:17-61 (1960).]
</text>

<text>
SMALL WORLDS
</text>

<!-- Milgram -->
<text>
L: Stanley Milgram is credited with introducing the notion of a small-world network <cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite>... In Milgram's experiment, volunteers in Kansas and Nebraska were asked to forward a letter to an unfamiliar target living in Cambridge and Boston, Massachusetts. Not knowing the target person, recipients forwarded the letter to an acquaintance closer to the target than themselves. Many of the letters were lost, but of the ones that eventually reached their target addresses, the number of hops along the chain of intermediaries ranged from 2 to 10, with an average of 5.2. Hence the notion of a small world and six degrees of separation was born.

... invited human subjects from Kansas and Nebraska to participate
in a "communications project" to "better understand social contact in American
society." The experiment required them to send a folder across the country to a target
person defined by the experimenters.

Instructions:
1. Add your name to the roster at the bottom of this sheet, so that the next person
who receives this letter will know whom it came from.
2. Detach one postcard, fill it out, and return it to Harvard University. No stamp is
necessary. It allows us to keep track of the progress of the folder as it moves
toward the target person.
3. If you know the target person on a personal basis, mail this folder directly to
him/her. Do this only if you have previously met the target person and
know each other on a first-name basis.
4. If you do not know the target person on a personal basis, do not try to contact
him/her directly. Instead, mail this folder (postcards and all) to a personal
acquaintance who is more likely than you to know the target person. You
may send the folder on to a friend, relative, or acquaintance, but it must be
someone you know on a first-name basis.

Conclusion:
Society is not a nonrandom network.
Instead of randomly bouncing from person to person, some folders reached their destinations and the path they followed was not planned out ahead of
time (there was no assurance that a chain of intermediaries existed between sender and receiver).

+ Milgram's experiment inspired a 1990 Broadway play and movie by John Guare called <q>Six Degrees of Separation: A Play</q>.

+ The "Kevin Bacon game" created by Brett Tjaden of the University of Virginia: 
</text>

<text>
WEAK TIES
</text>

<text>
L: The small-world idea is related to the "weak ties" theory of Granovetter, who postulated
that social networks contain both strong (direct) and weak ties (long-distance
connections) that bind society together <cite>Granovetter 1973</cite>. In a cleverly titled paper,
"The strength of weak ties," Granovetter suggests that social networks are held
together by strong connections between friends and family members, as well as
weaker, long-distance connections among casual acquaintances. This explains why
it is possible to span a large sparse network in a small number of hops. The links
of a social network are like freeways and streets—freeways have few intersections
(nodes) and allow you to travel long distances without stopping. City streets, on
the other hand, allow you to pinpoint a single person or house within a dense neighborhood.
Freeways (weak ties) get you to a local neighborhood quickly, while streets
(strong ties) zero in on a specific person or house.
</text>


<!-- Network models -->

<text>
NETWORK MODELS
</text>

<text>
L: ... scientists in other fields began to use networks as models of physical and biological phenomena... pioneering work of Duncan Watts, Steven Strogatz, and Albert-Laszlo Barabasi ...
</text>

<text>
Small worlds (sparse networks with small diameter): <cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite>

Algorithm: initially construct a graph with regular structure. Next, apply rewiring to every link with probability p, such that p*m links are randomized (redirected to a randomly selected node). Parameter p is the rewiring probability, and m is the number of links in the original regular graph.

Watts and Strogatz: small worlds as networks with relatively short distances (hops) between node pairs chosen at random, even as the size of the network grows. Specifically, the diameter of a network increases as ln(n) while its size increases by O(n), where n is number of nodes.

</text>

<text>
Scale-free networks (nonrandom networks with hubs): <cite>Barabasi and Albert 1999</cite>


L: "the probability that a site has k links obeys a power law, which drops off quickly for large k"
... A network that follows a power-law distribution means that it has a
hub, and many other nodes with many fewer links than the average. This lopsided
preference for hubs seemed counter to nature, which typically follows a normal distribution.

L: "a microrule called preferential attachment - that the probability a site will obtain a new link is directly proportional to the number of links it already has" (the <q>rich get richer</q> phenomenon).

L: scale-free networks... The name came from observing that a function f(x) scales if f(ax) = a*f(x), which is
what a power law does. Therefore, if the degree sequence distribution obeys the power law, h(x) = x ^-q, then it is clear that h(ax) = (ax)^-q = (a ^-q)h(x) = a' h(x).
</text>

<text>
A small-world network has relatively small diameter and average path length, and a scale-free network has hubs.
= Small worlds had characteristic short path length, but power-law networks had hubs—nodes with extremely high degree.
</text>



<text>
TIMELINE, excerpted from <cite>Lewis 2008</cite>:

1736 Euler: Bridges of Königsberg <cite>Euler 1736</cite>

1951 Solomonoff, Rappaport: Spread of infection in random networks
  [Solomonoff, R. and A. Rapoport, Connectivity of random nets, Bull. Math. Biophys. 13:107-117 (1951).]

1955 Simon: Power law observed in word analysis <cite>Simon 1955</cite>

1959 Gilbert: First generative procedure for random graphs
  [Gilbert, E. N., Random graphs, Ann. Math. Stat. 30(4):1141-1144 (1959)]

1960 Erdos, Renyi: Random graphs <cite>Erdos and Renyi 1959</cite> <cite>Erdos and Renyi 1960</cite>

1967 Milgram: Small-world experiments <cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite>

1972 Bonacich: Idea of influence in social networks leading to influence diagrams
  [Bonacich, P., Factoring and weighing approaches to clique identification, J. Math. Sociol. 2:113-120 (1972).]

1973 Granovetter: Job-seeking networks formed clusters with "weak links" between them <cite>Granovetter 1973</cite>

1978 Pool, Kochen: First theoretical examination of small worlds <cite>Pool and Kochen 1978</cite>

1989 Bristor, Ryan: "Buying networks" i.e. application of network science to model economic system
  [Bristor, J. M. and M. J. Ryan, Applying the small world phenomenon to organizational buying, in M. Kochen, ed., The Small World, Ablex, Norwood, NJ, 1989, Chapter 4, pp. 87-99.]

1995 Molloy, Reed: Generation of networks with arbitrary degree sequence distribution
  [Molloy, M. and B. Reed, A critical point for random graphs with a given degree sequence, Random Struct. Algorithms 6:161-180 (1995).]

1998 Holland: Emergence in complex adaptive systems
  [Holland, J. H., Emergence: From Chaos to Order, Addison-Wesley, Reading, MA, 1998.]

1998 Watts, Strogatz: Frst generative procedure for small worlds <cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite>

1999 Barabasi, Albert: Scale-free network model <cite>Barabasi and Albert 1999</cite>
</text>

</document>



<document>
<tag>kinds</tag>
<title>Kinds of networks</title>

<text>
++ Application domains with different terminology:
- Communication engineers think of networks as systems of routers and switches; 
- sociologists think of networks as influence diagrams representing the social interactions among humans;
- marketing business people think of networks as populations of buyers; 
- physicist thinks of networks as models of phase transition, magnetism...
- Biologists use the network metaphor to understand epidemics, genetics, and metabolic systems within cells
- Power engineers think of electrical power grids.
</text>

<document>
<tag>social</tag>
<title>Social networks</title>


<text>
The first use of the <q>social network</q> term is often attributed to John Arundel Barnes <cite>Barnes 1954</cite>, an anthropologist who conducted a field study to analyze the social structure and decision-making processes in Bremnes, a small island in western Norway. Since then, social networks denote patterns of ties that encompass many concepts used by the social sciences, including bounded groups (e.g., tribes or families) and social categories (e.g., gender or ethnicity).
</text>

<text>
Sociometry can be considered to be the precursor of social network analysis (and much of social psychology), as it was founded to measure interpersonal relations in small groups of people. Jacob Levy Moreno, the founder of sociometry, also pioneered the use of <q>sociograms</q> in the 1930's, e.g. <cite>Moreno and Jennings 1938</cite>. Sociograms are standard graph drawings used to depict the social links that determine the interpersonal structure of groups.
</text>

<text>
Widely used in the social and behavioral sciences, social network analysis focuses on the relationships among social entities <cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>. Depending on the particular context, these social entities can be individuals belonging to groups, corporations making economic transactions with other corporations, or nations signing treaties and trade agreements. The key ingredient in social network analysis is its focus on relationships, in contrast to reductionist approaches that limit their attention to the attributes of individual social entities.
</text>

<text>
Kinds of relations in a social network: 
- John Barnes (1972): attitudes, roles, and transactions.
- Knoke/Kuklinski (1982): individual evaluations (sentiments: friendship, liking, respect...), kinship (family ties: marriage and descent relationships), transactions or transfers of material resources (lending/borrowing, buying/selling, exchange of gifts), transfer of non-material resources (communication, i.e. sending/receiving information, let it be e-mail messages, advice, or mere gossip), interactions (e.g. attending the same event, hitting...), movement (physical, between locations, or social, between occupations), formal roles (boss/employee, teacher/student, doctor/patient...)...
</text>


<text>
Topics that have been studied by network analysts: occupational mobility, decision making, group problem solving, consensus and social influence, social perception, social support, community formation, exchange and power, social roles, coalition formation, company interlocking, markets, the world economic system, difussion and adoption of innovations...
</text>

<text>
Ego-centered networks (a.k.a. personal or local networks) consist of a focal actor, called ego, a set of alters who have ties to ego, and measurements on the ties among the alters, e.g. Facebook friends or people in your Google+ circles [difference between dichotomous links @Facebook vs. valued links @Google+, e.g. trusty friend, well-known, acquaintance, name associated to face, unknown]. Applications: study of the social envionment surrounding a given individual (you!) and what social scientists call social support, i.e. how social relationships can affect the emotional and physical well-being of a given individual.
</text>

<text>
Two students of Leslie White, a renowned anthropologists, offer complementary views on the forces behind cooperation [of people within societies].
<cite>Wright 2000</cite>. Whereas Robert Carneiro's focus was on pushing people together as the rational response against external threats, Elman Service thought that it was clear in some cases and probable in many others that neighboring societies were pulled together because of economic causes. Either by pushing or pulling people, opportunities for gain originate and draw people in closer cooperation, because of the benefits of participation in the total network. 
</text>

<text>
Jennifer Fewell, from Arizona State University, illustrates the importance of [insect] social networking using a professional basketball example <cite>Fewell and O'Donnell 2009</cite>. Phoenix Suns were successful, in part, because point guard Steve Nash passed the ball quickly to different teammates, making it difficult for defenders to predict their play. However, the Suns immediately started losing the first six games after Shaquille O'Neal joined the team, most likely because he destroyed his team's network dynamics: <q>Everybody there on the floor... knew where that ball was going to go - it was going to go to Shaq.</q> The network dynamics had changed and the success of the team depended on it, so they were forced to change their network dynamics again in order to improve their results with Shaquille O'Neal in the team. <q>It's a good example that the success of individuals depend on the network, and the success of the network depends on individuals. It's not just how good the individuals are... it's how good those interactions among them are as well.</q>
</text>


<text>
++ Obesity ;-) <cite>Christakis and Fowler 2007</cite>
</text>

<text>
++ Dunbar's number: http://www.technologyreview.com/blog/arxiv/26824/ 
+ http://arxiv.org/abs/1105.5170 Validation of Dunbar's Number In Twitter Conversations  @ Network structure chapter
</text>

<text>
++ Milgram's Six Degrees of separation (4.74 @ Facebook, http://arxiv.org/abs/1111.4503  http://arxiv.org/abs/1111.4570 ) @ Network structure chapter
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>content</tag>
<title>Content networks</title>

<text>
WWW: 

L: The structure of the Internet and WWW: an emergent property of the decentralized Internet - that it had emerged without central planning into a structure consisting of a small number of extremely popular sites called hubs, and a large number of "unpopular" sites with few links (a scale-free network).

1999 Kleinberg, Kumar, Raghavan, Rajagopalan, Tomkins: Formalized model of WWW as "Webgraph"
+ We call such networks Webgraphs, because they use graph theory to understand the World Wide Web (WWW).
(Kleinberg et al. 1999)
[Kleinberg, J. M., S. R. Kumar, P. Raghavan, S. Rajagopalan, and A. S. Tomkins, The Web as a
graph: Measurements, models, and methods, in T. Asano, H. Imai, D. Lee, S. Nakano, and
T. Tokuyama, eds, Proc. 5th Annual Intnatl. Conf. Computing and Combinatorics, Tokyo,
Lecture Notes in Computer Science, Vol. 1627, Springer-Verlag, Berlin, 1999.]

2000 Broder, Kumar, Maghoul, Raghavan, Rajagopalan Stata, Tomkins, Wiener: Full Webgraph map of the WWW
+ Broder, Kumar, Maghoul, Raghavan, Rajagopalan, Stata, Tomkins, and Wiener were the first to fully map the WWW as a Webgraph and discover its structure
[Broder, A., S. R. Kumar, F. Maghoul, P. Raghavan, S. Rajagopalan, R. Stata, A. Tomkins, and
J. Wiener, Graph structure in the web, Comput. Networks 33(1-6):309-320, (2000).]


1999 Albert, Jeong, Barabasi: Power law observed in WWW
[Albert, R., H. Jeong, and A.-L. Barabasi, Diameter of the World Wide Web, Nature 401:130-131 (1999).]
[Adamic, L. A. and B. A. Huberman, Power-law distribution of the World Wide Web, Science 287:2115 (2000).]

1999 Adamic: Distance between .edu sites shown to be small-world
[Adamic, L. A., The small world web, in Research and Advanced Technology for
Digital Libraries, Lecture Notes in Computer Science 1696, S. Abiteboul and
A.-M. Vercoustre, eds, Springer-Verlag, New York, 1999, 443-452.]


2002 Levene, Fenner, Loizou, Wheeldon: Enhanced Webgraph model concluded structure of the WWW couldn't be explained by preferential
attachment alone
[Levene, M., T. Fenner, G. Loizou, and R. Wheeldon, A stochastic model for the evolution of
the web, Comput. Networks 39:277-287 (2002).]


[Tadic, B., Growth and structure of the world-wide web: Towards realistic modeling, Comput. Phys. Commun. 147(1-2):586-589 (2002).
[Tadic, B., Temporal fractal structures: Origin of power laws in the world-wide web, Physica A 314(1-4):278-283 (2002).]

</text>

<cite>Liu 2011</cite>


<text>
++ Bibliographic <cite>Tang et al. 2008</cite>
</text>


</document>

<document>
<tag>economic</tag>
<title>Economic networks</title>
</document>

<document>
<tag>transportation</tag>
<title>Transportation networks</title>


<text>
INTERNET: 

L: The structure of the Internet and WWW: an emergent property of the decentralized Internet - that it had emerged without central planning into a structure consisting of a small number of extremely popular sites called hubs, and a large number of "unpopular" sites with few links (a scale-free network).

1988 Waxman: First graph model of the Internet
L: Waxman proposed a static graph theory model of the Internet in 1988 (Waxman, 1988). 
[Waxman, B. M., Routing of multipoint connections, IEEE J. Select. Areas Commun. 6(9):1617-1622 (1988).]

1999 Faloutsos brothers: Power law observed in Internet
[Faloutsos, M., P. Faloutsos, and C. Faloutsos, On power-law relationships of the Internet
topology, Proc. ACM SIGCOMM '99 Conf. Applications, Technologies, Architectures, and
Protocols for Computer Communication in Cambridge, MA, USA, ACM Press, New York,
1999, pp. 251-262.]
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>biological</tag>
<title>Biological networks</title>

<text>
++ <cite>Oltvai and Barabasi 2002</cite> <cite>Barabasi and Oltvai 2004</cite> <cite>Guimera and Nunes 2005</cite> <cite>Boccaletti et al. 2009</cite>
<cite>Barabasi et al. 2011</cite>
</text>

</document>

</document>


<document>
<tag>properties</tag>
<title>Network properties</title>

<text>
++ Scale, evolution, distribution &amp; interaction through connections...
</text>

</document>



<document>
<tag>datasets</tag>
<title>Network data sets</title>

<text>
Large network datasets...
</text>

<list>

<item>
The Stanford Large Network Dataset Collection, <url>http://snap.stanford.edu/data/</url>, maintained by Jure Leskovec (University of Stanford, California) as part of the Stanford Network Analysis Platform (SNAP).
</item>

<item>
The Koblenz Network Collection, <url>http://konect.uni-koblenz.de/</url>, maintained by Jérôme Kunegis (University of Koblenz-Landau, Germany).
</item>

<item>
The UCI Network Data Repository, <url>http://networkdata.ics.uci.edu/</url>, a NSF-funded project from the University of California at Irvine led by Christopher L. DuBois.
</item>

<item>
CASOS datasets, <url>http://www.casos.cs.cmu.edu/computational_tools/datasets/</url>, from the Center for Computational Analysis of Social and Organizational Systems at Carnegie Mellon University (Pittsburhg, Pennsylvania).
</item>

<item>
NWB datasets, <url>https://nwb.slis.indiana.edu/community/?n=Datasets.HomePage</url>, from the wiki of the Network Workbench Project (Indiana University at Bloomington).
</item>

<item>
The University of Florida Sparse Matrix Collection, <url>http://www.cise.ufl.edu/research/sparse/matrices/</url>.
</item>

<item>
Pajek datasets, <url>http://vlado.fmf.uni-lj.si/pub/networks/data/</url>, by Vladimir Batagelj and Andrej Mrvar. 
</item>

<item>
Links to network data sets collected by Mark E.J. Newman (University of Michigan): <url>http://www-personal.umich.edu/~mejn/netdata/</url>.
</item>

<item>
The Stanford GraphBase, by Donald E. Knuth, http://www-cs-staff.stanford.edu/~knuth/sgb.html, includes some example graphs as well as a collection of programs to generate and manipulate graphs and networks (written in CWEB, which is a mix of the C programming language and Knuth's TEX typesetting language, to illustrate the use of literate programming). Such generators can be used to create test data for performing experiments and comparing algorithms.
</item>

<item>
The Nauty graph isomorphism testing program, http://cs.anu.edu.au/~bdm/nauty/, also includes graph generators for graphs, directed graphs, bipartitue graphs, and multigraphs.
</item>

<item>
Brendan McKay, the author of the Nauty program, also maintains collectins of various kinds of graphs at http://cs.anu.edu.au/~bdm/data/ and he recommends Gordon's Royce collection, http://mapleta.maths.uwa.edu.au/~gordon/data.html
</item>

</list>


<text>
+ Several data mining competitions @ major conferences and sites such as Kaggle (a 2010 startup created by an Australian economist, Anthony Goldbloom, for hosting predictive modeling competitions, inspired by the Netflix competition Netflix, held from 2006 to 2009, where Netflix offered $1 million to the team that could improve the accuracy of its movie-recommendation software by 10 percent).
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>introduction-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>

<text>
2005 NRC Definition of network science: Committee on Network Science for Future Army Applications, commissioned by the Board on Army Science and Technology in cooperation with the National Research Council of the National Academies:
<q>organized knowledge of networks based on their study using the scientific method</q> (National Research Council, Committee on Network Science for Future Army Applications: Network Science, Board of Army Science and Technology, National Academies Press, www.nap.edu, 2005).
</text>

<text>
<cite>Lewis 2009</cite>: <q>Network science, or the science of networks, is the study of the theoretical foundations of network structure/dynamic behavior and the application of networks to many subfields. Currently known subfields include social network analysis (SNA), collaboration networks (bibliographic citations, product marketing, online social networks), synthetic emergent systems (power grids, the Internet), physical science systems (phase transition, percolation theory, Ising theory), and life science systems (epidemics, metabolic processes, genetics).</q>
</text>

<text>
Related fields: networks incorporates ideas from complex adaptive systems (emergence), chaos theory (synchronization), and mean-field theory (physics)

+ L: Holland defines emergence in general terms as <q>much coming from little</q> (Holland, 1998): A series of microlevel changes accumulate over time, until a macrolevel change in the network is realized. Emergence means that a major change in global properties comes from many small changes at the local level.  [Holland, J. H., Emergence: From Chaos to Order, Addison-Wesley, Reading, MA, 1998.]

+ L: Networks evolve...  have dynamic properties such as fixed points when they sync. Starting at some initial state, a dynamic network may transition
to a second, third, fourth, and higher state until either cycling back or reaching a final state—its fixed point... networks that reach a fixed point are different from networks that oscillate, forever.
</text>


<document>
<title>Survey papers</title>

<text>
++ <cite>Strogatz 2001</cite> <cite>Albert and Barabasi 2002</cite> <cite>Newman 2003</cite> <cite>Watts 2004b</cite> <cite>Boccaletti et al. 2006</cite> <cite>Borner et al. 2007</cite> <cite>Costa et al. 2007</cite> <cite>Costa et al. 2011</cite>
</text>

<text>
++ Collection of classic papers <cite>Newman et al. 2006</cite>
</text>

<text>
++ Network science: 2003 Virtanen Complete survey of network science results up to 2003
[Virtanen, S., Properties of Non-uniform Random Graph Models, Helsinki Univ. Technology, Laboratory for Theoretical Computer Science, Report FIN-02015 HUT, lab@tcs.hut, 2003]

++ Voon Joe Yung gives a nonmathematical introduction and includes a copy of the Milgram experiment folder (Yung, 2001).
[Yung, V. J. An exploration in the small world networks, available as Condensed Matter/ 0004214 (2000/2001).]

++ The numerous papers by Mark Newman and Duncan Watts provide compact tutorials on the fundamentals of small worlds (Watts, 1999a; Newman, 2000b).
[Watts, D., Networks, dynamics, and the small-world phenomenon, Am. J. Sociol. 105:2 493-527 (Sept 1999).]
[Newman, M. E. J., Models of the small world: A review, J. Stat. Phys. 101:819-841 (2000).]
[Newman, M. E. J., Small worlds, the structure of social networks, J. Stat. Phys. 101(3/4) (2000).]
</text>

</document>


<document>
<title>Recommended books</title>


<text>
++ Networks <cite>Easley and Kleinberg 2010</cite> <cite>Newman 2010</cite> <cite>Jackson 2009</cite> <cite>Lewis 2009</cite> <cite>Cohen and Havlin 2010</cite> <cite>van Steen 2010</cite> <cite>Dogorotsev 2010</cite>
</text>

<text>
++ Social network analysis <cite>Scott 2000</cite> <cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite> <cite>Freeman 2004</cite> <cite>Thompson et al. 1991</cite> <cite>Hanneman and Riddle 2005</cite>
</text>

<text>
++ Tool-oriented titles: Pajek <cite>de Nooy et al. 2005</cite>, NodeXL <cite>Hansen et al. 2010</cite>
</text>

<text>
++ Monographs <cite>Bornholdt and Schuster 2003</cite> <cite>Cook and Holder 2007</cite> <cite>Yu et al. 2010</cite> <cite>Aggarwal and Wang 2010</cite> <cite>Aggarwal 2011</cite> Lecture Notes in Social Networks series from Springer <cite>Memon and Alhajj 2010</cite>
</text>

<text>
++ Divulgative books <cite>Barabasi 2003</cite> <cite>Watts 2004</cite>...  <cite>Barabasi 2010</cite> <cite>Watts 2011</cite>
</text>

<text>
++ <cite>Sterman 2000</cite> <cite>Goyal 2007</cite> <cite>Mitchell 2009</cite>, <cite>Sporns 2011</cite>...
</text>

</document>

</document>


</document>
