<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ 
  <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> 
  <!ENTITY history      SYSTEM "00-introduction-1-history.xml"> 
  <!ENTITY networks     SYSTEM "00-introduction-2-networks.xml"> 
  <!ENTITY properties   SYSTEM "00-introduction-3-properties.xml"> 
  <!ENTITY data         SYSTEM "00-introduction-4-data.xml"> 
  <!ENTITY tools        SYSTEM "00-introduction-5-tools.xml"> 
  <!ENTITY notes        SYSTEM "00-introduction-6-notes.xml"> 
]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<title>Mining Network Data</title>


<text>
Reka Albert: It is increasingly recognized that complex systems cannot be described in a reductionist view.
- Understanding the behavior of such systems starts with understanding the topology of the corresponding network.
- Topological information is fundamental in constructing realistic models for the function of the network.
</text>

<text>
K: A network perspective... involves formulating and reasoning about mathematicalmodels and also reasoning qualitatively about these models and searching for their broader implications... a powerful way of looking at complex systems in general - a way of thinking about social dynamics, economic interaction, online information, designed technology, and natural processes, and approaching such systems with an eye toward their patterns of
internal structure and the rich feedback effects that result.
</text>

<text>
A network is described <q>by its structure (e.g., nodes and links), and its behavior (what the network 'does' as a result of the interactions among the nodes and links).</q> In other words, networks are graphs that represent something real, <q>a representation or model of observable reality.</q> (National Research Council, Committee on Network Science for Future Army Applications: Network Science, Board of Army Science and Technology, National Academies Press, www.nap.edu, 2005).
</text>

<text>
Two key ingredients of networks <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>:
(1) the study of the structure of a collection of nodes and links that represent something real,
(2) the study of the dynamic behavior of the aggregation of nodes and links.
</text>

<text>
The study of networks encompasses theories, models, and applications expressed in terms of <q>relational concepts</q> <cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>. In other words, the relationships defined by the existing links among the elements of a complex system are the fundamental ingredient of networks, where
</text>

<list>

<item>Elements (also known as actors in social network analysis and nodes or vertices in graph theoretical terms) are autonomous but interdependent.</item>

<item>Links between elements (also known as connections, ties, relations, or even <q>relational contents</q>) represent the only channels through which resources can flow, let them be material or immaterial.</item>

</list>

<text>
L: A network forms by the autonomous and spontaneous action of independent nodes that "volunteer" to come together (link), rather than through central control or central planning
</text>

<text>
Connections in a network provide opportunities for and impose constraints on the elements of the network. Ties among elements are primary and attributes of elements are secondary (and they can often be understood in terms of the role they play within the network structure). 

+ results seem to correlate form with function and structure with behavior <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>.
</text>

<text>
Connections in a social network may represent kinship, friendship, liking, romantic involvement, supervisor-employee relationships, interactions, transactions, resource flows, group co-membership and other kinds of social ties... even several of these at the same time. In other kinds of networks, links might represent chemical bonds, contagions, synapses, wires, Internet links, bibliographical citations, roads,.
</text>

<text>
Nodes in a social network might be people from a given group, departments within a corporation, whole corporations, public agencies, and even nation-states... In other kinds of networks, they might be atoms, molecules, genes, transistors, routers, transformers (in power grids),Web pages, research publications, cities.
</text>

<text>
Most applications focus on networks of elements of the same type (one-mode networks), albeit you could also have networks conformed by elements of different types (multimode networks)...
</text>

<text>
++ Modes = distinct sets of entities on which the structural variables are measured. Single set (uni-mode networks), two sets (two-mode networks) or even more (multi-mode networks). 

The mode of the network = the number of sets of entities on which structural variables are measured.

- Dyadic two-mode networks (two sets of actors: relations are dyads with the first actor in one set and the second actor in a different set).

- Non-dyadic two-mode networks or affiliation networks (one set of actors and one set of events or activities, which define subsets of actors).
</text>

<text>
++ Attributes: structural variables (measured on pairs of actors, i.e. links) and actor variables (a.k.a. composition variables, defined at the level of individual actors [i.e. <q>of the standard social and behavioral science variety</q> <cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>, those measured in non-network studies]).
</text>

<text>
Modeling units (level at which network data are studied): actor, dyad (pair of actors), triad (triple of actors), subset of actors, the network as a whole.
</text>

<text>
++ the need to understand the interconnectivity of our relationship with customers and the groups they interact with, whom, how and why.
</text>

<text>
Need for new data mining techniques ++ Today's data, however, doesn't take the familiar form of the database. <q>The information's not coming at you in a clean tabular form, it's coming at you in a network form.</q> [Chid Apte, director of analytics research at IBM and chair of the KDD'2011 conference]. It arrives in a graph, that records not only the complex connections between nodes but also other types of information in a diversity of formats (e.g. the videos, images, and comments that people post on social networks). Social media may have started the trend toward analyzing such graphs, Apte says, but network data comes from other sources as well-for example, from complex engineering systems such as the electric power grid, water distribution systems, and traffic management systems. <cite>Naone 2011</cite>
</text>






<text>
++ <cite>Amaral and Ottino 2004</cite> <cite>Kim and Wilhelm 2008</cite>
</text>


<text>
L: Selection of topics about what some have called <term>network science</term> <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>: <q>one has to include the work of pioneers such as Adamic, Albert, Barabasi, Barrat, Bollobas, Erdos, Granovetter, Kephart, Lin, Liu, Mihail, Milgram, Molloy, Moore, Newman, Pastor-Satorras, Renyi, Strogatz, Tadic, Wang, Watts, Weigt, White, Zhang, and Zhu.</q>
</text>


<!-- Sections -->
&history;
&networks;
&properties;
&data;
&tools;
&notes;

</document>
