<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>

<!-- Subgraphs -->

<document>
<tag>graph-theory-subgraphs</tag>
<title>Subgraphs</title>


<text>
Let <eqn>G=(V,E)</eqn> be a graph and <eqn>V'</eqn> be a subset of <eqn>V</eqn>. Using the notation in <cite>Jungnickel 2007</cite>, by <eqn>E|V'</eqn> we denote the set of all edges <eqn>e \in E(G)</eqn> that have both vertices in <eqn>V'</eqn>. The resulting graph <eqn>G'=(V',E|V')</eqn> is the induced subgraph of <eqn>G</eqn> on <eqn>V'</eqn> and it will be denoted as <eqn>G|V'</eqn>.
</text>

<!--
For a subset T of the vertex set V of a graph G we denote by G\ T the induced subgraph on V \ T. This graph arises from G by omitting all vertices in T and all edges incident with these vertices. For a one-element set T = {v} we write G \ v instead of G \ {v}. 
--> 

<text>
Each graph of the form <eqn>G'=(V',E')</eqn> where <eqn>V' \subset V</eqn> and <eqn>E' \subseteq E|V'</eqn> is said to be a subgraph of <eqn>G</eqn>.
</text>

<text>
A subgraph of the same order of the original graph, i.e. when <eqn>V'=V</eqn>, is a spanning subgraph. 
</text>

<text>
A k-factor is a k-regular spanning subgraph. When the edge set of a graph is divided into k-factors, such a decomposition is called a k-factorization of the graph. A 1-factorization, or factorization for short, can exist only if <eqn>G</eqn> has an even number of vertices and it is also called a resolution. Factorizations of <eqn>K_{2n}</eqn> can be interpreted as schedules for tournaments of <eqn>2n</eqn> teams and always exist <cite>Jungnickel 2007</cite>.
</text>

<text>
DYAD: A subgraph with 2 nodes
+ Undirected graphs: 2 dyadic states
+ Directed graphs: 3 isomorphic classes (null dyad, asymmetric dyad, and mutual/reciprocal dyad

TRIAD: A subgraph with 3 nodes
+ Undirected graphs: 4 triadic states (0-3 links)
e.g. forbidden triad (2 links), unlikely with strong ties <cite>Granovetter 1973</cite>
</text>

<!-- Isomorphism -->

<note>
<tag>graph-theory-isomorphism</tag>
<title>Graph isomorphism</title>

<text>
When are two graphs considered different? Basically, when they do not have the same structure, which leads as to the concept of graph isomorphism.
</text>

<text>
Two graphs <eqn>G = (V(G),E(G))</eqn> and <eqn>H = (V(H),E(H))</eqn> are called isomorphic if there is a bijective function <eqn>\phi: V(G) \rightarrow V(H)</eqn> such that <eqn>(u, v) \in E(G)</eqn> if and only if <eqn>(\phi(u), \phi(v)) \in E(H)</eqn> for all <eqn>u, v \in V(G)</eqn>.
</text>

<text>
The isomorphisms of a graph G to itself are called automorphisms.
</text>

<text>
When two graphs G and H are isomorphic, they have the same number of nodes (i.e. the same order), the same number of links (i.e. the same size), and the degrees of the vertices of G are the same as the degrees of the vertices of H.
</text>
</note>

</document>
