<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
<tag>graph-theory-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>

<text>
Origin of graph theory: Euler founded the field he called <q>geometria situs</q> (geometry of position), what is now known as graph theory.
</text>

<text>
Euler 1736 @ Könisberg Bridges == Eulerian circuits and Eulerian trails.
</text>

<text>
<q>In addition to that branch of geometry which is concerned with magnitudes, and
which has always received the greatest attention, there is another branch, pre-
viously almost unknown, which Leibniz first mentioned, calling it the geometry
of position. This branch is concerned only with the determination of position
and its properties; it does not involve measurements, nor calculations made
with them. It has not yet been satisfactorily determined what kind of problems
are relevant to this geometry of position, or what methods should be used in
solving them. Hence, when a problem was recently mentioned, which seemed
geometrical but was so constructed that it did not require the measurement of
distances, nor did calculation help at all, I had no doubt that it was concerned
with the geometry of position - especially as its solution involved only position,
and no calculation was of any use...</q> translated from <q>Solution of a problem relating to the geometry of position</q> <cite>Euler 1736</cite>
</text>

<text>
[Wikipedia] In 1736 Euler solved, or rather proved unsolvable, a problem known as the seven bridges of Königsberg. The city of Königsberg, Kingdom of Prussia (now Kaliningrad, Russia) is set on the Pregel River, and included two large islands which were connected to each other and the mainland by seven bridges. The question is whether it is possible to walk with a route that crosses each bridge exactly once, and return to the starting point. Euler's solution of the Königsberg bridge problem is considered to be the first theorem of graph theory. In addition, his recognition that the key information was the number of bridges and the list of their endpoints (rather than their exact positions) presaged the development of topology <cite>Alexanderson 2006</cite>.
This stamp of the former German Democratic Republic honoring Euler displaying his formula relating the number of faces, edges and vertices of a convex polyhedron. Euler also made contributions to the understanding of planar graphs. He introduced a formula governing the relationship between the number of edges, vertices, and faces of a convex polyhedron. Given such a polyhedron, the alternating sum of vertices, edges and faces equals a constant: V-E+F=2.
</text>


<text>
++ William Rowan Hamilton's Icosian Game @ 1856: Hamiltonian circuits. 

"Hamiltonian cycles apparently first arose in Euler's study of the knight's tour problem, although they were popularized by Hamilton's “Around the World” game in 1839."
</text>

<text>
Two 19th Century examples: Kirchhoff 1847 work on electrical networks (the foundation of circuit theory in electrical engineering) and Cayley 1857 use of trees to count alkanes (chemical compounds) = enumerating chemical isomers, molecules that contain the same number of atoms bonded in different ways.
</text>

<text>
The term graph was not used in its current sense until 1878, when J.J. Sylvester used it instead of <q>linkage</q>, which was the term used to refer to graphs at that time <cite>Gross and Yellen 2003</cite>.
</text>

<text>
First two books on graph theory: <cite>Konig 1936</cite> in German (English translation: <cite>Konig 1990</cite>) and <cite>Berge 1958</cite> in French (English translation: <cite>Berge 2001</cite>).
</text>

<text>
The first major book on graph theory written in English: <cite>Ore 1962</cite>.
</text>

<text>
The only other major book on graph theory published in English before 1970: <cite>Harary 1969</cite>
</text>

<text>
A retrospective from one of the key players in the development of graph theory: <cite>Tutte 1998</cite>
</text>


<text>
++ Modern textbooks, e.g. <cite>Chartrand et al. 2011</cite> <cite>Jungnickel 2007</cite> <cite>Diestel 2005</cite> <cite>Gross and Yellen 2005</cite> <cite>Gross and Yellen 2003</cite> <cite>Bollobas 2002</cite>. 
</text>

<text>
++ Other textbooks: <cite>Bondy and Murty 1976</cite> 

WF: We recommend the following texts...
<cite>Harary 1969</cite> and <cite>Bondy and Murty 1976</cite> . 

The excellent text by Frank (1971) is more
mathematically advanced and focuses on social networks. 
[Frank, O. (1971). Statistical Inference in Graphs. Stockholm: FOA Repro]

Similarly, the
classic text by Harary, Norman, and Cartwright (1965) is also focused
on directed graphs, and is quite accessible to beginners. 
[Harary, E, Norman, R.Z., and Cartwright, D. (1 965). Structural Models: An
Introduction to the Theory of Directed Graphs. New York: John Wiley and Sons]

Roberts (1976, 1978) and Hage and Harary (1983) provide very readable, elementary
introductions to graph theory, with many concepts illustrated on anthropological
network data. 
[Hage, P., and Harary, F. (1983). Structural Models in Anthropology. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.]
[Roberts, ES. (1976). Discrete Mathematical Models. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall.]
[Roberts, ES. (1978). Graph Theory and Its Applications to Problems of SOCiety. Philadelphia: Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics.]

In their introduction to network analysis, Knoke
and Kuklinski (1982) also describe some elementary ideas in graph theory.
[Knoke, D., and Kuklinski, J.H. (1982). Network AlUllysis. Newbury Park : Sage.]

Ford and Fulkerson (1962), Lawler (1976) give mathematical treatments of more advanced topics in graph theory,
such as theories of matroids and optimization of network configurations.
[Ford, L.R., and Fulkerson, D.R. (1 962). Flows in Networks. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press]
[Lawler, E.L. (1976). Combinatorial Optimization : Networks and Matroids. New York: Holt, Rinehart, and Winston]


The topic of tournaments is treated in the context of paired comparisons
by David (1988). A more mathematical discussion of tournaments can
be found in Moon (1968). 
[Moon, J.W. (1968). Topics on Tournaments. New York : Holt, Rinehart, and Winston.]
[David, H. A. (1988). The Merhod oj Paired Comparisons. Second Edition. Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press.]
++ Skiena ??

Berge (1989) discusses hypergraphs in detail.
[Berge, C. (1973). Graphs and Hypergraphs. Amsterdam : North-Holland.]
[Berge, C. (1989). Hypergraphs: Combinatorics of Finite Sets. Amsterdam: North-Holland.]
</text>


<text>
[note] Pure mathematics, not always with practical applications.
</text>

<text>
++ Introductory divulgative books, e.g. <cite>Chartrand 1984</cite>
</text>


</document>
