<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<!-- Node degree -->

<document>
<tag>graph-theory-degree</tag>
<title>Node degree and degree sequences</title>

<text>
The set of neighbors of a vertex <eqn>v</eqn> is the neighborhood of <eqn>v</eqn> and is denoted by <eqn>N_G(v)</eqn>. Technically, this is the open neighborhood of the vertex (the closed neighborhood would also include the vertex <eqn>v</eqn> itself). 
</text>

<text>
The degree of a vertex <eqn>v</eqn> in a graph <eqn>G</eqn> is the number of vertices in <eqn>G</eqn> that are adjacent to <eqn>v</eqn>, i.e. the size of its neighborhood: <eqn>deg_G(v) = |N_G(v)|</eqn>.
</text>

<text>
Since every edge is counted twice (once for each one of its incident vertices), the sum of all vertex degrees is twice the size of the graph, i.e. <eqn>\sum deg_G(v) = 2|E(G)| = 2m</eqn>, a basic result known as the First Theorem of Graph Theory and also referred to as the Handshaking Lemma <cite>Chartrand et al. 2011</cite>. Since the sum of all vertex degrees is even, the number of vertices of odd degree must also be even. Moreover, the average degree of a graph <eqn>G</eqn> of order <eqn>n</eqn> and size <eqn>m</eqn> can be easily computed, since it is always <eqn>2m/n</eqn>.
</text>

<text>
The minimum degree among the vertices of G is denoted by <eqn>\delta(G)</eqn>, while the maximum degree in G is denoted by <eqn>\Delta(G)</eqn>. Hence, <eqn>0 \le \delta(G) \le deg_G(v) \le \Delta(G) \le n-1</eqn> for simple graphs.
</text>

<text>
When the nodes with the largest degrees in a given network are much more connected that other nodes in the network, they are typically called hubs.
</text>

<text>
Variance of the degrees (0 for regular graphs)...
</text>

<equation>
\sigma_d^2(G) = \frac{1}{n} \sum ( d_i - \langle d \rangle )^2
</equation>

<text>
Density (useful for measuring the cohesiveness of subgraphs), a.k.a. connectance, in the [0,1] interval:
</text>

<equation>
\rho(G) = \frac{2m}{n(n-1)} = \frac{\langle d \rangle}{n-1}
</equation>

<text>
N: A network for which the density \rho tends to a constant as n \rightarrow \infinity is said to be dense. In such a network the fraction of non-zero elements in the adjacency matrix remains constant as the network becomes large. A network in which \rho \rightarrow 0 as n \rightarrow \infinity is said to be sparse. In particular, a network is sparse if the average degree tends to a constant as n becomes large. (theoretical definition)

N: In some cases real-world networks do change their sizes and by making measurements for different sizes we can make a guess as to whether they are best regarded as sparse or dense. The Internet and the World Wide Web are two examples of networks whose growth over time allows us to say with some conviction that they are best regarded as sparse. In other cases there may be independent reasons for regarding a network to be sparse or dense. In a friendship network, for instance, it seems unlikely that the number of a person’s friends will double solely because the population of the world doubles. How many friends a person has is more a function of how much time they have to devote to the maintenance of friendships than it is a function of how many people are being born. Friendship networks therefore are usually regarded as sparse.
In fact, almost of all of the networks we consider in this book are considered to be sparse networks, which will be important for the design of network algorithms... One possible exception to the pattern is food webs. Studies comparing ecosystems of different sizes seem to show that the density of food webs is roughly constant, regardless of their size, indicating that food webs may be dense networks 
[Dunne, J. A., Williams, R. J., and Martinez, N. D., Food-web structure and network theory: The role of connectance and size, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 99:12917-12922 (2002)]
[Martinez, N. D., Constant connectance in community food webs, Am. Nat. 139:1208-1218 (1992)]
</text>

<document>
<tag>graph-theory-degree-sequence</tag>
<title>Degree sequences</title>

<text>
An integer partition p = (p_1, ..., p_n) where p_i is the degree of the ith highest-degree node in the graph.

p is an integer partition of 2m, i.e. sum p_i = 2m, in undirected graphs, since each edge contributes to the degree of two nodes.

Not all integer partitions correspond to actual graphs. Those that do correspond to actual graphs are called graphical.

It should be noted that different graphs can share the same degree sequence. Therefore there is not a one-to-one mapping between graphs and degree sequences. We could view a degree sequence as a rough description of the graph topology.

An algorithm to build a graph given a degree sequence: the highest-degree node is connected to the following node; the degree sequence is updated by decrementing p_1 and p_2 (and reorder the partition), resulting in a smaller partition; the process is repeated until the degree sequence is full of zeroes (or a negative value appears, which means the graph was not realizable).

The algorithm above is deterministic. If we want a random graphs with the given degree sequence, we can generate them by flipping edges: from (x,y) and (w,z) we create (x,w) and (y,z), which yields a different graph with the same degree sequence (albeit it should be noted that the resulting graph is not necessarily connected).
</text>


<text>
We can compress a degree sequence by obtaining a <term>degree distribution</term>, which is just the histogram of the relative frequencies corresponding to the different node degrees, which vary from 1 to <eqn>\Delta(G)</eqn>.

As in any probability distribution, the sum of the values in the degree sequence distribution must add up to 1. 
</text>

<text>
Different kinds of networks exhibit different degree sequence distributions:
e.g. 
- A random network has a degree sequence distribution that obeys a binomial distribution, 
- and a scale-free network’s degree sequence obeys a power law.
</text>

<text>
We can also employ the degree distribution to measure the randomness in the graph. From Information Theory, we know that <term>entropy</term> communicates the amount of information provided by a message and is measured in bits. We can obtain the entropy of a degree distribution by computing
</text>

<equation>
H(G) = - \sum_i P(deg_G(v)=i) \log_2 P(deg_G(v)=i)
</equation>

<text>
where <eqn>P(deg_G(v)=i)</eqn> is the probability of a node having degree i.
</text>

<text>
This entropy measures the randomness in the graph degree distribution, or the diversity in node degrees, which is minimum when all the nodes have the same degree (i.e. for regular graphs). For regular networks, where <eqn>P(deg_G(v)=r)=1</eqn> for a single degree <eqn>r</eqn>, we obtain <eqn>H(G_{regular}) = - 1 \log_2 1 = 0</eqn>. The more random the graph, the higher the entropy: at one extreme, regular graphs have no entropy; at the other end of the spectrum, random graphs have very little regularity (and high entropy).
</text>


</document>


<document>
<tag>graph-theory-degree-directed</tag>
<title>Directed graphs: In-degree and out-degree</title>

<text>
In a directed graph, links are directed and we distinguish between

- The out-neighborhood <eqn>N^+(v)</eqn> of a vertex <eqn>v</eqn> (the set of vertices adjacent to v)

- The in-neighborhood <eqn>N^-(v)</eqn> of a vertex <eqn>v</eqn> (the set of vertices adjacent from v)
</text>

<text>
The out-degree <eqn>deg_{out}(v)</eqn> of a vertex v is the number of edges with tail v, i.e. <eqn>deg_{out}(v) = | N^+(v) |</eqn>

The in-degree <eqn>deg_{in}(v)</eqn> of a vertex v is the number of edges with head v, i.e. <eqn>deg_{in}(v) = | N^-(v) |</eqn>

The full degree of a vertex is defined by <eqn>deg(v) = deg_{out}(v) + deg_{in}(v)</eqn>
</text>

<text>
The First Theorem of Digraph Theory can be stated as
</text>

<equation>
\sum deg_{out}(v) = \sum deg_{in}(v) = |E(G)| = m
</equation>


<text>
AVERAGE DEGREE
Undirected graphs: <eqn>\langle d \rangle = 2m/n</eqn> 
Directed graphs: <eqn>\langle d_{in} \rangle = \langle d_{out} \rangle = m/n</eqn>
</text>

<text>
VARIANCE
Note: Even though <eqn>\langle d_{in} \rangle = \langle d_{out} \rangle = m/n</eqn> in directed graphs, <eqn>\sigma_{d_{in}}^2</eqn> might differ from <eqn>\sigma_{d_{out}}^2</eqn>.
</text>

<note>
<text>
According to their in- and out-degrees, nodes in a directed graph can be classified as: isolates (d=0), sources or transmitters (din=0), sinks or receivers (dout=0), carriers (din=dout=1), and ordinary nodes.
</text>
</note>

</document>


<document>
<tag>graph-theory-degree-weighted</tag>
<title>Weighted graphs: Node strength</title>

<text>
++ Weighted graphs: Node strength instead of node degree = Sum of all the edge weights of a node.
</text>

</document>

</document>

