<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>

<document>
<tag>graph-algorithms-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>


<text>
Many textbooks describe at least part of the material mentioned in this chapter.

<cite>Skiena 2008</cite>, <cite>Kleinberg and Tardos 2005</cite>
<cite>Even 2011</cite> discusses many basic graph algorithms known before 1979.
<cite>Tarjan 1983</cite> book provides a survey of both algorithms and data structures.
<cite>Gibbons 1985</cite>
<cite>Sedgewick 1990</cite> in C, <cite>Sedgewick 2002</cite> and <cite>Sedgewick 2003</cite> in Java (2nd volume devoted to graph algorithms)

</text>


<text>
<cite>Grama et al. 2003</cite> includes a chapter on parallel graph algorithms.

+ <cite>Lynch 1997</cite> textbook on distributed algorithms.
</text>



<text>
Network flow:

- monographs: reference <cite>Ahuja et al. 1993</cite>, original work <cite>Ford and Fulkerson 1962</cite>;
- surveys <cite>Goldberg et al. 1990</cite> <cite>Schrijver 2002</cite>;
- original algorithms <cite>Ford and Fulkerson 1956</cite> <cite>Edmonds and Karp 1972</cite>;
- 114-page chapter <cite>Kleinberg and Tardos 2005</cite>, including an extensive list of exercises

++ [Thomas H. Cormen, Charles E. Leiserson, Ronald L. Rivest, and Clifford Stein. Introduction to Algorithms, Second Edition. MIT Press and McGraw-Hill, 2001. ISBN 0-262-03293-7. ... Section 26.4: Push-relabel algorithms, and section 26.5: The relabel-to-front-algorithm.]

+ books on combinatorial optimization <cite>Cook et al. 1998</cite>
[W.J. Cook, W.H. Cunningham, W.R. Pulleyblank, and A. Schrijver: Combinatorial Optimization, Wiley, 1998]

[Schrijver, Alexander, "On the history of the transportation and maximum flow problems", Mathematical Programming 91 (2002) 437-445]
@ <url>http://homepages.cwi.nl/~lex/files/histtrpclean.pdf</url>

++ [Ford, L.R., Jr.; Fulkerson, D.R., "Maximal Flow through a Network", Canadian Journal of Mathematics (1956), pp.399-404.]
</text>

<text>
Matching:  The concept of a matching in a graph is very fundamental and forms
the cornerstone of combinatorial optimization, with an entire book devoted
to it <cite>Lovasz and Plummer 1986</cite>
</text>


<text>

Many graph problems (such as shortest paths, bipartite matching, or network flows) can also be solved as special cases of linear programming.

The books by <cite>Papadimitriou and Steiglitz 1982</cite> and <cite>Ahuja et al. 1993</cite> provide a
comprehensive coverage of combinatorial optimization problems. 

Hochbaum's edited collection <cite>Hochbaum 1996</cite> provides an extensive coverage of work on approximation
algorithms for graph problems. 

Software tools: <type>lp_solve</type> (<url>http://lpsolve.sourceforge.net/</url>), CLP (<url>http://www.coin-or.org</url>), NEOS = Network-Enabled Optimization System @ Argonne National Laboratory, Illinois (submit your own optimization jobs at <url>http://neos.mcs.anl.gov/</url>)

</text>

<text>
NP problems:
- 1972: Landmark paper, "Reducibility Among Combinatorial Problems"  <cite>Karp 1972</cite>, 21 combinatorial and graph theoretical NP-complete problems
- 1979: Catalog containing hundreds of NP problems<cite>Garey and Johnson 1979</cite>, 65 graph theoretical problems and 51 network design problems.

- A compendium of NP optimization problems edited by Pierluigi Crescenzi and Viggo Kann
<url>http://www.nada.kth.se/~viggo/problemlist/</url>

- Wikipedia: More than 3000 known NP-complete problems,
<url>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_NP-complete_problems</url>

</text>

<text>
Approximation algorithms:

- Crescenzi and Kann [ACG+03]
[ACG+03] G. Ausiello, P. Crescenzi, G. Gambosi, V. Kann, S. Marchetti-Spaccamela,
and M. Protasi. Complexity and Approximation: Combinatorial Optimization
Problems and Their Approximability Properties. Springer, 2003.

- Vazirani [Vaz04]
[Vaz04] V. Vazirani. Approximation Algorithms. Springer, 2004.

- Hochbaum [Hoc96]
[Hoc96] D. Hochbaum, editor. Approximation Algorithms for NP-hard Problems. PWS Publishing, Boston, 1996.

- Gonzalez [Gon07]
[Gon07] T. Gonzalez. Handbook of Approximation Algorithms and Metaheuristics. Chapman-Hall / CRC, 2007.
</text>


<text>
Conferences: Many international conferences carry articles on recent advances in graph
algorithms. Some of them are the IEEE Symposium on Foundations of Computer
Science (FOCS), the ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC), the ACM-SIAM
Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA), and the International Colloquium on
Automata, Languages and Programming (ICALP).
</text>

</document>
