<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<!-- Visualization tools -->

<document>
<tag>graph-visualization-tools</tag>
<title>Graph visualization tools</title>


<text>
TOOLS: 
- Design patterns <cite>Heer and Agrawala 2006</cite>
- JSNVA network drawing framework <cite>Ye et al. 2008</cite>
- VisNetMiner <cite>Shi et al. 2009</cite>
</text>

<text>
Systems described in <cite>Jünger and Mutzel 2003</cite>...
</text>


<text>
Graphviz, http://www.graphviz.org, graph-drawing program developed by Stephen North of Bell Laboratories: represents edges as splines and can construct useful drawings of quite large and complicated graphs. <cite>Gansner et al. 1988</cite> <cite>Ellson et al. 2001</cite> <cite>Ellson et al. 2003</cite>
</text>


<list>

<item>
"hierarchical" or layered drawings of directed graphs (<type>dot</type>).
</item>

<item>
"spring model" layouts:

<type>neato</type> attempts to minimize a global energy function, which is equivalent to statistical multi-dimensional scaling <cite>Kamada and Kawai 1989</cite>; 

<type>fdp</type> reduces forces rather than working with energy <cite>Fruchterman and Reingold 1991</cite>; <type>sfdpmultiscale</type> is a multi-scale version of <type>fdp</type> for the layout of large graphs.

</item>

<item>
Radial layouts: <type>twopi</type> <cite>Wills 1997</cite>
1997
</item>

<item>
Circular layout: <type>circo</type> <cite>Six and Tollis 1999a</cite> <cite>Six and Tollis 1999b</cite> <cite>Kaufmann and Wiese 2002</cite>
</item>

</list>



<text>
The DOT language syntax: 
- Grafos no dirigidos (graph --)
- Grafos dirigidos (digraph ->)
</text>



<text>
Libraries:
++ JGraph, <url>http://www.jgraph.com/</url>, open source network visualisation library using standard Java Swing. 
++ JGraphT, <url>http://jgrapht.sourceforge.net/</url>: Java graph libraries suitable for interactive applications.
++ JGraphEd (http://www.jharris.ca/JGraphEd/): a Java graph-drawing framework that includes several planarity testing/embedding algorithms, including both the Booth-Lueker PQ-tree algorithm and the modern straight-line grid embedding
</text>

<text>
Social network analysis tools: 
- Pajek <cite>de Nooy et al. 2005</cite>,  output in several formats including SVG and postscript


- NodeXL <cite>Hansen et al. 2010</cite>... include implementations of force-directed methods for visualizing social networks.
  + Fruchterman-Reingold
  + Harel-Koren Fast Multiscale
  + Circle/spiral/sine wave/grid/polar
  + Sugiyama
  + Random

- UCINET Software for Social Network Analysis, http://www.analytictech.com/ucinet/,  
Commercial but cheap. Can read and write many types of simple text file, can deal with excel files and can export data for Mage and Pajek. Includes NetDraw for drawing diagrams. Also it contains many standard data sets from social science, such as the Karate Club, which can easily be exported to a text format. These may be available with the trial version. 
[Borgatti, S.P., 2002. NetDraw Software for Network Visualization. Analytic Technologies: Lexington, KY]

</text>

<text>
++ GUESS - The Graph Exploration System, http://graphexploration.cond.org/index.html
GUESS is an exploratory data analysis and visualisation tool for graphs and networks. Free, containing an embedded language called Gython (an extension of Python, or more specifically Jython). Contains "limited, but fairly functional GraphML and pajek" file readers. Contained within Network Workbench.

++ Gephi, interactive visualization and exploration platform for all kinds of networks and complex systems, dynamic and hierarchical graphs, http://gephi.org/ ...  using java Netbeans technology.

++ Cytoscape: An Open Source Platform for Complex Network Analysis and Visualization, ++ http://www.cytoscape.org/
 Visualisations can be hand edited and may be exported in all the useful formats PDF, EPS, SVG, PNG, JPEG, and BMP. 

++ yFiles, from yworks http://www.yworks.com/, a commercial java library of algorithms and components for the visualisation and analysis of networks. Used by both visone and yed,
- http://visone.info/ A software tool intended for research and teaching in social network analysis.
- yED, free multiplatform graph editor, from yWorks
</text>

</document>

