<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>

<document>
<tag>graph-visualization-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>

<text>
ALGORITHMS
</text>


<text>
Primary sources: Chapters at
- <cite>Didimo and Liotta 2007</cite> in <cite>Cook and Holder 2007</cite> (succinct survey)
- <cite>Skiena 2008</cite> (sections for arbitrary graphs, trees, and planar graphs)
</text>

<text>
Force-directed drawing: 

CH: Most force-directed algorithms described in the literature adopt the
physical model by Eades <cite>Eades 1984</cite> and propose variants of the forces definition
- Kamada <cite>Kamada and Kawai 1989</cite> <cite>Kamada and Kawai 1991</cite>
- FR <cite>Fruchterman and Reingold 1991</cite>
- Magnetic spring model <cite>Sugiyama and Misue 1995</cite>
- Adaptive model <cite>Frick et al. 1995</cite>
- Simulated annealing <cite>Davidson and Harel 1996</cite>

CH: An experimental comparison of graph drawing algorithms based on force-directed methods is described in <cite>Brandenburg et al. 1996</cite>.
</text>

<text>
Hierarchical drawing <cite>Bastert and Matuszewski 2001</cite> <cite>Di Battista et al. 1998</cite>
- <cite>Sugiyama et al. 1981</cite>
- <cite>Gansner et al. 1993</cite>
- <cite>Buchheim et al. 2000</cite>
</text>

<text>
Metrics: 
- <cite>Tamassia 1985</cite> <cite>Batini et al. 1986</cite> <cite>Tamassia 1987</cite>: Embedded planar graph with vertices having at most four incident edges
- Kandisky drawings <cite>Fossmeier and Kaugmann 1997</cite>: graphs of any vertex degree
</text>



<text>
TOOLS: 
- Design patterns <cite>Heer and Agrawala 2006</cite>
- JSNVA network drawing framework <cite>Ye et al. 2008</cite>
- VisNetMiner <cite>Shi et al. 2009</cite>

+ Force-directed: Pajek <cite>de Nooy et al. 2005</cite>, NodeXL <cite>Hansen et al. 2010</cite>...
+ Hierarchical drawing: The methodology of <cite>Sugiyama et al. 1981</cite> is used by
Graphviz <cite>Ellson et al. 2003</cite>, Ptolomaeus <cite>Di Battista et al. 1998</cite>...

</text>



<text>
Monographs <cite>Di Battista et al. 1999</cite>
- Recent survey of visualization techniques <cite>Aigner et al. 2011</cite>
- Focus on software: the development and evaluation of methods for graphically representing different aspects of software, including its structure, its execution, and its evolution <cite>Sugiyama 2002</cite>; <cite>Diehl 2007</cite>
- Focus on biology: <cite>Guimera and Nunes 2005</cite>
- General literature on visualization, what makes visualization aesthetically pleasing <cite>Cleveland 1985</cite> <cite>Tufte 2001</cite> <cite>Steele and Iliinsy 2010</cite>

- Planar graphs <cite>Nishizeki and Rahman 2004</cite>

</text>

<text>
Annual conference on graph drawing GD (proceedings published by Springer-Verlag's Lecture Notes in Computer Science series), since 1992:
<url>http://graphdrawing.org/</url>
</text>

++ <cite>Kaufmann and Wagner 2001</cite>


<cite>Jünger and Mutzel 2003</cite> is organized around systems instead of algorithms, but provides technical details about the drawing
methods each system employs. 

++ Alternative: Koren <cite>Koren et al. 2003</cite> <cite>Koren 2005</cite>

<!-- Alternative -->

<cite>Koren et al. 2003</cite>
Y. Koren, L. Carmel and D. Harel, Drawing Huge Graphs by Algebraic Multigrid
Optimization, Multiscale Modeling and Simulation, Volume 1, no. 4, pp.
645-673, SIAM, 2003

<cite>Koren 2005</cite>
Y. Koren: "Drawing graphs by eigenvectors: Theory and practice"
Computers and Mathematics with Applications, Volume 49 Issue 11-12, June, 2005, 
Pergamon Press, Inc. Tarrytown, NY, USA, doi>10.1016/j.camwa.2004.08.015


<!-- placing labels -->


<cite>Been et al. 2006</cite>
K. Been, E. Daiches, and C. Yap. Dynamic map labeling. IEEE Trans. Visualization and Computer Graphics, 12:773-780, 2006.

<cite>Wagner and Wolff 1995</cite>
F. Wagner and A. Wolff. Map labeling heuristics: provably good and practically useful. In Proc. 11th ACM Symp. Computational Geometry, pages 109-118, 1995.

<!-- force-directed algorithms -->


<cite>Eades 1984</cite>
P. Eades. A heuristic for graph drawing. Congr. Numer., 42:149-160, 1984.

<cite>Davidson and Harel 1996</cite>
R. Davidson and D. Harel. Drawing graphs nicely using simulated annealing. ACM
Transactions on Graphics, 15(4):301-331, 1996.

<cite>Frick et al. 1995</cite>
A. Frick, A. Ludwig, and H. Mehldau. A fast adaptive layout algorithm for undirected
graphs. In R. Tamassia and I. G. Tollis, eds. Graph Drawing (Proc. GD '94), Vol. 894
of Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pp. 388-403. Springer, Berlin, 1995.

<cite>Sugiyama and Misue 1995</cite>
K. Sugiyama and K. Misue. Graph drawing by the magnetic spring model. Journal of
Visual Languages and Computing, 6(3):217-231, 1995.

<cite>Brandenburg et al. 1996</cite>
F. J. Brandenburg, M. Himsolt, and C. Rohrer. An experimental comparison of forcedirected
and randomized graph drawing algorithms. In F. J. Brandenburg, ed. Graph
Drawing (Proc. GD '95), Vol. 1027 of Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pp. 76-87.
Springer, Berlin, 1996


<!-- hierarchical drawing -->

<cite>Sugiyama et al. 1981</cite>
Sugiyama, Kozo; Tagawa, Shôjirô; Toda, Mitsuhiko (1981), "Methods for visual understanding of hierarchical system structures", IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics SMC-11 (2): 109-125, doi:10.1109/TSMC.1981.4308636, MR0611436.

<cite>Di Battista et al. 1998</cite>
Di Battista, Giuseppe; Eades, Peter; Tamassia, Roberto; Tollis, Ioannis G. (1998), "Layered Drawings of Digraphs", Graph Drawing: Algorithms for the Visualization of Graphs, Prentice Hall, pp. 265-302, ISBN 9780133016154.

<cite>Bastert and Matuszewski 2001</cite>
Bastert, Oliver; Matuszewski, Christian (2001), "Layered drawings of digraphs", in Kaufmann, Michael; Wagner, Dorothea, Drawing Graphs: Methods and Models, Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 2025, Springer-Verlag, pp. 87-120, doi:10.1007/3-540-44969-8_5.

<!-- 1. Feedback arcs -->

<cite>Eades et al. 1993</cite>
P. Eades, X. Lin, and W. F. Smyth. A fast and effective heuristic for the feedback arc
set problem. Information Processing Letters, 47:319-323, 1993.

<cite>Jünger et al. 1995</cite>
M. Jünger, G. Reinelt, and S. Thienel. Practical problem solving with cutting plane
algorithms in combinatorial optimization. In P. Seymour W. Cook, L. Lov´asz, ed.
DIMACS Series in Discrete Mathematics and Theoretical Computer Science, pp.
111-152, Piscataway, New Jersey, 1995.

<!-- 2. Layer assignment -->

<cite>Coffman and Graham 1972</cite>
E. G. Coffman and R. L. Graham. Optimal scheduling for two processor systems. Acta Informatica, 1:200-213, 1972.

<cite>Gansner et al. 1993</cite>
E. R. Gansner, E. Koutsofios, S. C. North, and K. P. Vo. A technique for drawing
directed graphs. IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering, SE-19(3):214-230, 1993.


<!-- 3. Crossing reduction -->

<cite>Garey and Johnson 1983</cite>
M. R. Garey and D. S. Johnson. Crossing number is NP-complete. SIAM Journal of Algebraic Discrete Methods, 4(3):312-316, 1983.

<cite>Eades and Wormwald 1994</cite>
P. Eades and N. C. Wormald. Edge crossings in drawings of bipartite graphs. Algorithmica, 11(4):379-403, 1994.

<cite>Junger and Mutzel 1997</cite>
M. Jünger and P. Mutzel. 2-layer straightline crossing minimization: Performance
of exact and heuristic algorithms. Journal of Graph Algorithms and Applications,
1(1):1-25, 1997

<cite>Mutzel 2001a</cite>
P. Mutzel. An alternative method to crossing minimization on hierarchical graphs.
SIAM Journal of Optimization, 11(4):1065-1080, 2001.

<cite>Mutzel 2001b</cite>
P. Mutzel. Optimization in leveled graphs. In P. M. Pardalos and C. A. Floudas, eds.
Encyclopedia of Optimization, pp. 189-196. Berlin, Kluwer Academic, 2001.

<cite>Suderman and Whitesides 2005</cite>
M. Suderman and S. H. Whitesides. Experiments with the fixed-parameter approach
for two-layer planarization. Journal of Graph Algorithms and Applications, Vol. 9(1).
pp. 149-163, 2005.

<!-- 4. Coordinate assignment -->

<cite>Buchheim et al. 2000</cite>
C. Buchheim, M. Jünger, and S. Leipert. A fast layout algorithm for k-level graphs. In
Joe Marks, ed. 8th International Symposium on Graph Drawing, GD 2000, Vol. 1984
of Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pp. 229-240, Springer, Berlin, 2000.

<cite>Brandes and Köpf 2002</cite>
U. Brandes and B. Köpf. Fast and simple horizontal coordinate assignment. In
S. Leipert M. Jünger, and P. Mutzel, eds. 9th International Symposium on Graph Drawing,
GD 2001, Vol. 2265 of Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pp. 31-44, Springer,
Berlin, 2002.


<!-- Metrics-based methods -->


<cite>Batini et al. 1986</cite>
C. Batini, E. Nardelli, and R. Tamassia. A layout algorithm for data flow diagrams.
IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering, SE-12(4):538-546, 1986.

<cite>Tamassia 1987</cite>
R. Tamassia. On embedding a graph in the grid with the minimum number of bends.
SIAM Journal on Computing, 16(3):421-444, 1987.

<cite>Tamassia 1985</cite>
R. Tamassia. New layout techniques for entity-relationship diagrams. In Proceedings
of 4th International Conference on Entity-Relationship Approach, pp. 304-311, IEEE
Comp. Society, New York, 1985.

<cite>Garg and Tamassia 2001</cite>
A. Garg and R. Tamassia. On the computational complexity of upward and rectilinear
planarity testing. SIAM Journal on Computing, 31(2):601-625, 2001

<cite>Di Battista et al. 1998</cite>
G. Di Battista, G. Liotta, and F. Vargiu. Spirality and optimal orthogonal drawings.
SIAM Journal on Computing, 27(6):1764-1811, 1998.

<cite>Bertolazzi et al. 2000</cite>
P. Bertolazzi, G. Di Battista, and W. Didimo. Computing orthogonal drawings with
the minimum number of bends. IEEE Transactions on Computers, 49(8), 2000

<cite>Mutzel and Weiskircher 2002</cite>
P. Mutzel and R. Weiskircher. Bend minimization in orthogonal drawings using integer
programming. In Proceedings of COCOON 2002, pp. 484-493, Singapore, 15-17
August, 2002.

<cite>Patrignani 2001</cite>
M. Patrignani. On the complexity of orthogonal compaction. Computational Geometry:
Theory and Applications, 19(1):47-67, 2001.

<cite>Bridgeman et al. 2000</cite>
S. S. Bridgeman, G. Di Battista, W. Didimo, G. Liotta, R. Tamassia, and L. Vismara.
Turn-regularity and optimal area drawings of orthogonal representations. Computational
Geometry: Theory and Applications, 16(1):53-93, 2000.

<cite>Fossmeier and Kaugmann 1997</cite>
U. Fößmeier and M. Kaufmann. Algorithms and area bounds for non-planar orthogonal
drawings. In G. Di Battista, ed. 5th International Symposium on Graph Drawing (GD
1997), Vol. 1353 of Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pp. 134-145, Springer, Berlin,
1997.

<cite>Di Battista et al. 1999b</cite>
G. Di Battista, W. Didimo, M. Patrignani, and M. Pizzonia. Orthogonal and quasiupward
drawings with vertices of prescribed sizes. In Jan Kratochvil, ed. Graph
Drawing (Proc. GD '99), Vol. 1731 of Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pp. 297-310.
Springer, Berlin, 1999.

<cite>Binucci et al. 2005</cite>
C. Binucci, W. Didimo, G. Liotta, and M. Nonato. Computing orthogonal drawings of
graphs with vertex and edge labels. Computational Geometry: Theory and Applications.
Vol 32(2), pp. 71-114, 2005.

<cite>Binucci et al. 2002</cite>
9. C. Binucci, W. Didimo, G. Liotta, and M. Nonato. Computing labeled orthogonal drawings.
In 10th International Symposium on Graph Drawing, GD 2002, Vol. 2528 of
Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pp. 66-73, Springer, Berlin, 2002.


<!-- Evaluation -->



<cite>Tamassia et al. 1988</cite>
R. Tamassia, G. Di Battista, and C. Batini. Automatic graph drawing and readability of diagrams. IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics, SMC-18(1):61-79, 1988.

<cite>Vismara et al. 2000</cite>
L. Vismara, G. Di Battista, A. Garg, G. Liotta, R. Tamassia, and F. Vargiu. Experimental
studies on graph drawing algorithms. Software—Practice and Experience, 30(11):1235-1284, 2000.

<cite>Purchase et al. 2002</cite>
H. C. Purchase, D. Carrington, and J-A. Allder. Graph layout aesthetics in UML diagrams: User preferences. Journal of Graph Algorithms and Applications, 6(3):131-147, 2002.

<cite>Purchase et al. 2004</cite>
H. C. Purchase, D. Carrington, and J-A. Allder. Evaluating graph drawing aesthetics: Defining and exploring a new empirical research area. In J. Di Marco, ed. Computer Graphics and Multimedia: Applications, Problems and Solutions, pp. 145-178. Hershey, PA, USA, Idea Group Publishing, 2004.

<!-- Planar graphs -->


<cite>Hopcroft and Tarjan 1974</cite>
J. Hopcroft and R. E. Tarjan. Efficient planarity testing. Journal of the ACM, 21(4):
549-568, 1974.

<cite>Booth and Lueker 1976</cite>
K. Booth and G. Lueker. Testing for the consecutive ones property, interval
graphs, and planarity using PQ-tree algorithms. J. Computer System Sciences, 13:335-379, 1976.

<cite>Kuratowski 1930</cite>
K. Kuratowski. Sur le problème des courbes gauches en topologie. Fund. Math., 15:217-283, 1930.

<cite>Fary 1948</cite>
I. Fáry. On straight line representation of planar graphs. Acta. Sci. Math. Szeged, 11:229-233, 1948.


<cite>Chiba et al. 1985</cite>
N. Chiba, T. Nishizeki, S. Abe, and T. Ozawa. A linear algorithm for embedding planar
graphs using PQ-trees. Journal of Computer and System Sciences, 30(1):54-76, 1985.

<cite>Mehlhorn and Mutzel 1996</cite>
K. Mehlhorn and P. Mutzel. On the embedding phase of the Hopcroft and Tarjan planarity testing algorithm. Algorithmica, 16:233-242, 1996.


<cite>Boyer et al. 2004</cite>
J. Boyer, P. Cortese, M. Patrignani, and G. Di Battista. Stop minding your
p's and q's: Implementing a fast and simple DFS-based planarity testing
and embedding algorithm. In Proc. Graph Drawing (GD '03), volume 2912
LNCS, pages 25-36, 2004.

<cite>Shih and Hsu 1999</cite>
W. Shih and W. Hsu. A new planarity test. Theoretical Computer Science, 223(1-2):179-191, 1999.


<cite>de Fraysseix et al. 1990</cite>
H. de Fraysseix, J. Pach, and R. Pollack. How to draw a planar graph on a grid. Combinatorica, 10:41-51, 1990.


<cite>Liebers 2001</cite>
A. Liebers. Planarizing graphs—a survey and annotated bibliography. Journal of Graph
Algorithms and Applications, 5(1):1-74, 2001.

<cite>Nishizeki and Rahman 2004</cite>
T. Nishizeki and S. Rahman. Planar Graph Drawing. World Scientific, 2004.

<!-- Trees --> 

<cite>Reingold and Tilford 1981</cite> 
E. Reingold and J. Tilford. Tidier drawings of trees. IEEE Trans. Software Engineering, 7:223-228, 1981.

<cite>Moen 1990</cite>
S. Moen. Drawing dynamic trees. IEEE Software, 7-4:21-28, 1990.

<cite>Buchheim, et al. 2006</cite>
C. Buchheim, M. Jünger, and S. Leipert. Drawing rooted trees in linear time. Software: Practice and Experience, 36:651-665, 2006.

<cite>Supowit and Reingold 1983</cite>
K. Supowit and E. Reingold. The complexity of drawing trees nicely. Acta Informatica, 18:377-392, 1983.


<!-- Local neighborhood -->


<cite>Wills 1997</cite>
Graham J. Wills: 
NicheWorks - Interactive Visualization of Very Large Graphs. 
Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 1997, Volume 1353/1997, 403-414, 
DOI: 10.1007/3-540-63938-1_85
Giuseppe Di Battista (Ed.): Graph Drawing, 5th International Symposium, GD '97, 
Rome, Italy, September 18-20, 1997, Proceedings. Lecture Notes in Computer Science 1353 Springer 1997, ISBN 3-540-63938-1

<cite>Six and Tollis 1999a</cite>
Janet M. Six, Ioannis G. Tollis: 
A Framework for Circular Drawings of Networks.
Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 1999, Volume 1731/1999, 107-116, 
DOI: 10.1007/3-540-46648-7_11
Jan Kratochvíl (Ed.): Graph Drawing, 7th International Symposium, GD'99, Stirín Castle, Czech Republic, September 1999, Proceedings. Lecture Notes in Computer Science 1731 Springer 1999, ISBN 3-540-66904-3

<cite>Six and Tollis 1999b</cite>
Janet M. Six, Ioannis G. Tollis: 
Circular Drawings of Biconnected Graphs. 57-73
ALGORITHM ENGINEERING AND EXPERIMENTATION
Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 1999, Volume 1619/1999, 662, 
DOI: 10.1007/3-540-48518-X_4
Michael T. Goodrich, Catherine C. McGeoch (Eds.): Algorithm Engineering and Experimentation, International Workshop ALENEX '99, Baltimore, MD, USA, January 15-16, 1999, Selected Papers. Lecture Notes in Computer Science 1619 Springer 1999, ISBN 3-540-66227-8

<cite>Kaufmann and Wiese 2002</cite> @ GD'02
Michael Kaufmann, Roland Wiese: 
Maintaining the Mental Map for Circular Drawings.
GRAPH DRAWING
Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 2002, Volume 2528/2002, 235-255, DOI: 10.1007/3-540-36151-0_2
Stephen G. Kobourov, Michael T. Goodrich (Eds.): Graph Drawing, 10th International Symposium, GD 2002, Irvine, CA, USA, August 26-28, 2002, Revised Papers. Lecture Notes in Computer Science 2528 Springer 2002, ISBN 3-540-00158-1 


<!-- Monographs and application-specific systems -->

<cite>Kaufmann and Wagner 2001</cite>
M. Kaufmann and D. Wagner. Drawing Graphs: Methods and Models. Springer-Verlag, 2001.

<cite>Jünger and Mutzel 2003</cite>
M. Jünger and P. Mutzel. Graph Drawing Software. Springer-Verlag, 2003.



Graphviz 

<cite>Ellson et al. 2003</cite>
  J. Ellson, E. R. Gansner, E. Koutsofios, G. Woodhull, and S. C. North. G
  raphviz and Dynagraph—static and dynamic graph drawing tools. 
  In M. Jünger and P. Mutzel, eds. Graph Drawing Software, pp. 127-148. Springer, Berlin, 2003.

<cite>Ellson et al. 2001</cite>
John Ellson, Emden R. Gansner, Eleftherios Koutsofios, Stephen C. North and Gordon Woodhull
Graphviz - Open Source Graph Drawing Tools. 
Graph Drawing 2001: 483-484
Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 2002, Volume 2265/2002, 594-597, DOI: 10.1007/3-540-45848-4_57
Petra Mutzel, Michael Jünger, Sebastian Leipert (Eds.): Graph Drawing, 9th International Symposium, GD 2001 Vienna, Austria, September 23-26, 2001, Revised Papers. Lecture Notes in Computer Science 2265 Springer 2002, ISBN 3-540-43309-0

<cite>Gansner et al. 1988</cite>
ORIGIN OF dot :
Emden R. Gansner, Stephen C. North, K. P. Vo, 
"DAG - A Program to Draw Directed Graphs", 
Software - Practice and Experience 17(1), 1988, pp. 1047-1062.



Hermes: Internet topology

<cite>Carmignani et al. 2002</cite>
A. Carmignani, G. Di Battista, F. Matera, W. Didimo, and M. Pizzonia. Visualization
of the high level structure of the internet with Hermes. Journal of Graph Algorithms
and Applications, 6(3):281-311, 2002.


Ptolomaeus system to draw maps of Web navigations

<cite>Di Battista et al. 1998</cite>
  G. Di Battista, R. Lillo, and F. Vernacotola. Ptolomaeus: The web cartographer. In 6th International Symposium on Graph Drawing, GD 1998, Vol. 1547 of Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pp. 444-445, Springer, Berlin, 1998.


Social sciences

<cite>Brandes et al. 2003</cite>
U. Brandes, P. Kenis, and D. Wagner. Communicating centrality in policy network drawings. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, 9(2):241-253, 2003.

<cite>Brandes and Cornelsen 2003</cite>
U. Brandes and S. Cornelsen, Visual Rank of Link Structures, Journal of Graph Algorithms and Applications, vol. 7, no. 2, pp. 181-201, 2003.


WilmaScope: Computational biology

T. Dwyer, H. Rolletschek, and F. Schreiber. Representing experimental biological data
in metabolic networks. In 2nd Asia-Pacific Bioinformatics Conference (APBC'04),
Vol. 29 of CRPIT, pp. 13-20, ACS, Sydney, 2004.

F. Schreiber, T. Dwyer, and H. Rolletschek. Representing experimental biological data
in metabolic networks. In Second Asia-Pacific Bioinformatics Conference (APBC
2004), pp. 13-20, Vol. 29 of CRPIT, ACS, Sydney, 2004.


</document>
