<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<title>Network Motifs</title>


<text>
Large networks can be decomposed into smaller <q>building blocks</q> or <q>networks-within-networks</q>, commonly referred to as <b>motifs</b>.
</text>

<text>
Every network can be uniquely decomposed into a set of motifs, and the number and distribution of individual motifs can reflect some functional characteristics of the network <cite>Sporns 2011</cite>.
</text>

<document>
<tag>motifs-dyads</tag>
<title>Dyads</title>

<text>
= Two actors and their ties
</text>

<text>
At the most basic level, a link establishes a relationship between two nodes. The link is a property of the pair, not of any single node...
</text>

<text>
Dyadic analysis focuses on the properties of pairwise relationships, e.g. reciprocity.
</text>

<text>
<cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>: chapters 13, 15 &amp; 16...
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>motifs-triads</tag>
<title>Triads</title>

<text>
= Three actors and their ties
</text>

<text>
++ Transitivity (if A likes B and B likes C, then A will like C)
</text>

<text>
++ Balance (if A and B like each other, they will have a similar opinion of C; if they dislike each other, they will not agree on C)
</text>


<text>
<cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>: chapters 6 and 14...
</text>
</document>


<document>
<tag>motifs-cliques</tag>
<title>Cliques, plexes &amp; cores</title>
</document>

<document>
<tag>motifs-components</tag>
<title>Components &amp; k-components</title>
</document>


<document>
<tag>motifs-structural-balance</tag>
<title>Appendix: Structural balance</title>


<text>
Stuctural balance, postulated by Fritz Heider in the 1940's <cite>Heider 1946</cite> and Theodore M. Newcomb in the 1950's <cite>Newcomb 1953</cite>, led to research on triples of individuals, since balanced relations are common in empirical work...
</text>

<text>
<cite>Cartwright and Harary 1956</cite> were among the first to quantify structural balance...
</text>

<text>
Balance theory influenced the development of other structural theories, such as transitivity...
</text>

</document>



<document>
<tag>motifs-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>

<text>
Motif analysis extended to weighted networks <cite>Onnela et al. 2005</cite>.
</text>

<text>
Motif composition => profile of local processing capacity <cite>Sporns and Kotter 2004</cite>, <cite>Sporns et al. 2007</cite>.
</text>

<text>
<cite>Milo et al. 2002</cite>
<cite>Milo et al. 2004a</cite>
<cite>Milo et al. 2004b</cite>
</text>

</document>

</document>
