<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<title>Models of Network Formation</title>


<document>
<tag>growing-random-networks</tag>
<title>Growing random networks</title>


<document>
<tag>formation-watts-strogatz</tag>
<title>Watts-Strogatz model (small-world networks)</title>


<text>
<cite>Pool and Kochen 1978</cite> @ inaugual issue of the Social Networks journal (a draft widely circulated two decades before its publication): the world of social relationships is much smaller than expected given the size of the social network.
</text>

<text>
<cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite> famous experiments...
</text>

<text>
<cite>Kleinberg 2000</cite>, not only surprisingly short paths, but also the remarkable ability of individuals to identify links that lead to those short paths...
</text>

<text>
++
<cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite> created a simple model that originates small worlds + discovered that these patterns are present in a broad range of networks. 

L: Very sparse networks with small diameter (small worlds) at diverse phenomena such as phase transitions in materials, functionality of biological organisms, and behavior of electrical power grids.

<cite>Uzzi et al. 2007</cite>
</text>

<text>
Networks are considered to be small worlds when they have a high clustering coefficient but exhibit a similar path length when compared to random networks with the same number of nodes and links.
</text>

<text>
Small-world-ness measure <cite>Humphries and Gurney 2008</cite>: The small-world index = ratio of the clustering coefficient to the path length after normalizing by the corresponding values for random networks.
</text>


<text>
A different class of small-world networks <cite>Sporns 2006</cite>: modular small-world networks (generated from isolated modules by gradually redistributing connections from within modules to between modules).
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>formation-barabasi-albert</tag>
<title>Barabasi-Albert model (scale-free networks)</title>


<text>
Anthropologists such as Elman Service, when studying cultural evolution, envision chiefdoms being formed when several villages were bound by commerce. The village located at the nexus would naturally become the richest and would gradually grow dominant <cite>Wright 2000</cite>. This <q>rich get richer</q> effect is pervasive in networks...
</text>

<text>
A wide range of real-world networks have been found to exhibit power-law degree distributions: the World Wide Web, citation networks, cellular metabolism networks...
</text>

<text>
A power law implies that the probability of finding a node with a degree that is twice as large as a given number decreases by a constant factor, rather than following an exponential falloff. ++ exponent of the power law distribution.
</text>

<text>
IDEA: The fluctuations in degree are unbounded, i.e., the standard deviation is bounded only by the finite size of the graph.
</text>

<text>
<cite>Clauset et al. 2009</cite> examine how power laws are best detected in practice: regression analysis of linear relationships in log-log scale (the standard method) results in many false positives (e.g. networks that might be better approximated by exponential or log-normal distributions). Sampling might also introduce false negatives <cite>Stumpf et al. 2005</cite>.
</text> 

<text>
The <q>scale-free</q> term refers to the fact that nodes in a scale-free network do not have a characteristic scale. You can zoom in on any segment of the distribution and it does not change its shape.
</text>

<text>
++
<cite>Barabasi and Albert 1999</cite> demonstrated that power-law degree distributions can be generated by a <q>preferential attachment</q> growth process. This process is a well-known example of how local processes can determine the global properties of complex networks. 
</text>

<text>
++ Linear preferential attachment yields scale-free networks with an exponent of 3. Refined attachment rules that vary node attractiveness yield scale-free networks with exponents between 2 and 3.
</text>

<text>
++ When new links involve a cost, i.e. they cost energy or occupy space, the degree distribution becomes truncated for high degrees <cite>Amaral et al. 2000</cite>. Networks that exhibit a scale-free behavior only through a range of node degrees are called broad-scale networks.
</text>

<text>
Alternative formation model: <cite>Alava and Dogorotsev 2005</cite>
</text>

<text>
<cite>Caldarelli 2007</cite>
<cite>Cohen and Havlin 2003</cite>
<cite>Barabasi and Bonabeau 2003</cite>
</text>



</document>

<document>
<tag>formation-exponential</tag>
<title>Exponential random graphs</title>
</document>

</document>


<document>
<tag>strategic-network-formation</tag>
<title>Strategic network formation</title>
</document>




<document>
<tag>formation-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>

<text>
<cite>Sole and Valverde 2004</cite> arrange network classes in a qualitative space by considering three dimensions: randomness, heterogeneity, and modularity. The first introduces the amount of randomness involved in the process of network’s building. The second measures how diverse is the link distribution and the third would measure how modular is the architecture. The position of different examples are only a visual guide. The domain
of highly heterogeneous, random hierarchical networks appears much more occupied than others. Scale-free like networks belong to this domain.

Each class results from a different formation process and exhibits different patterns of behavior. 

Not all niches in this space are occupied by real-world networks (empty regions might correspond to unrealistic growth strategies or unstable network configurations).
</text>

<text>
++
<cite>Jackson 2009</cite>
<cite>Lewis 2009</cite>
</text>

<text>
Hierarchical models can combine scale-free degree distributions and high clustering coefficients <cite>Ravasz and Barabasi 2003</cite>
</text>


</document>



</document>
