<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<title>Other Network Models</title>

<cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite>
<cite>Barabasi and Albert 1999</cite>

<cite>Lewis 2009</cite>, chapter 7... how to produce networks with almost any desired level of clustering, path length, and entropy. With
this ability, we can produce <q>designer networks</q> with arbitrary properties.

<document>
<tag>affiliation-networks</tag>
<title>Affiliation networks</title>

<text>
Affiliation networks (a.k.a. membership networks) are a special kind of two-mode network: bipartite graph, actors + events the actor is associated to (e.g. organizations, clubs, meetings, groups...). Events, therefore define subsets of actors, whose belonging to the group can be described by means of a binary affiliation variable (for each relevant subset).
</text>

<text>
e.g. Club membership, voluntary organizations, attendance to social events, sitting on a board of directors, countries belonging to treaty organiztions...
</text>

<text>
++ Projection
</text>

<text>
e.g. interlocking boards of directors
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>modular-networks</tag>
<title>Hierarchical/modular networks</title>
</document>

<document>
<tag>influence-networks</tag>
<title>Influence networks</title>

<text>
L: Chapter 10 @ <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>, <q>Influence Networks,</q> is mostly new material and
suggests what conditions must be met in order for a social network to come to consensus.
As it turns out, it is not easy for groups to agree! 
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>kirchhoff-networks</tag>
<title>Kirchhoff networks</title>

<text>
++FLOW: defined as directed-flow
networks where the state of every node is the sum of the values of incoming links
minus the sum of values of outgoing links.
</text>

<text>
Applications: abstractions of electrical power grids, electromechanical feedback systems, air traffic routes...
</text>

<text> 
L: Chapter 9 @ <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>, <q>Synchrony,</q> pushes the early work of Watts to new levels—claiming that
network synchronization is merely a special case of linear system stability. Simple
eigenvalue tools can be used to determine the stability and synchrony of almost
any linear network. 
</text>

<text>
L: STABILITY it is important that they not blow up—but instead, stabilize quickly
after a disruption or sudden change in the value of one or more nodes. Curiously,
Kirchhoff networks exhibit wildly chaotic behavior followed by sudden synchronization
when the lengths of circuits within the network are relatively prime numbers.
This has important applications to the design of self-stabilizing power grids, selfcorrecting
transportations systems, and perhaps self-repairing biological systems.
</text>
</document>

<document>
<tag>netgain-networks</tag>
<title>Netgain networks</title>

<text>
L: Chapter 12 @ <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>, <q>Netgain,</q> is an exploration of business
models - relating the famous Schumpeter creative destruction process to an emergent
process, and mapping the Bass and Fisher-Pry equations onto networks. It is comforting
to verify the Bass-Fisher-Pry equations for networks, but furthermore, I
show how these classical models may be extended to multi-product markets and oligopolies.
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>models-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>

<cite>Jackson 2009</cite>
<cite>Lewis 2009</cite>

</document>



</document>
