<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
<tag>graph-visualization-orthogonal</tag>
<title>Orthogonal methods</title>


<text>
CH:The topology-shape-metrics approach is one of the most effective techniques for
computing highly readable drawings of graphs. It represents graphs in the so-called
orthogonal drawing standard, that is, each vertex of the graph is drawn as a point
or a box and each edge is drawn as a polygonal chain of horizontal and vertical
segments. The topology-shape-metrics approach <cite>Batini et al. 1986</cite> <cite>Tamassia 1987</cite> takes as input a graph G with
vertices of degree at most 4 and produces as output an orthogonal drawing of G
where each vertex is drawn as a point. It consists of three steps:

1) Planarization If G is planar, then a planar embedding of G is computed. A
planar embedding of G specifies the set of faces of a planar drawing of G. If
G is not planar, a set of dummy vertices is added to replace edge crossings.

2) Orthogonalization During this step, an orthogonal shape H of G is computed
within the previously defined embedding. An orthogonal shape specifies the
sequence of left and right turns along each edge, and the angles formed by
consecutive edges incident around a vertex.

3) Compaction In this step a final geometry for H is computed by assigning
coordinates and dimensions to vertices and edge bends.

As described above, the topology-shape-metrics approach deals with the topology,
shape, and geometry of the drawing separately; in each step of the approach,
one or more optimization goals are considered, which are related to well-known
drawing aesthetic criteria. Namely, during planarization, since each dummy
vertex represents an edge crossing, the goal is the minimization of the number
of inserted dummy vertices. During orthogonalization the objective is typically to
determine a shape with the minimum number of edge bends. Finally, in the compaction
step, the goal can be either the minimization of the area of the drawing or
the minimization of the total edge length.

The distinct phases of the topology-shape-metrics approach have been extensively
studied in the literature. 

If G is planar, which can be tested in linear time <cite>Hopcroft and Tarjan 1974</cite>, a planar embedding of G is also computable in linear time <cite>Chiba et al. 1985</cite> <cite>Mehlhorn and Mutzel 1996</cite>. 

If G is not planar, the minimum number of edge crossings required by the drawing may be <eqn>\Omega(n^4)</eqn>, although in practice this number is much smaller. Since, minimizing the number of crossings is an NP-hard problem <cite>Garey and Johnson 1983</cite>, several heuristic planarization
techniques have been proposed in the literature <cite>Liebers 2001</cite>.

A popular and very elegant algorithm for constructing an orthogonal shape
of an embedded planar graph with vertices having at most four incident edges
was presented by <cite>Tamassia 1985</cite>. This algorithm uses a flow network approach
to compute an orthogonal shape that has the minimum number of edge bends,
while preserving the given embedding. <cite>Garg and Tamassia 2001</cite> proved that the
problem of computing an orthogonal shape with the minimum number of bends
in a variable embedding setting is NP-hard. Polynomial time solutions for specific
classes of graphs are studied by <cite>Di Battista et al. 1998</cite>; exponential algorithms have
been proposed by <cite>Bertolazzi et al. 2000</cite> and by <cite>Mutzel and Weiskircher 2002</cite>.

<cite>Patrignani 2001</cite> showed that the problem of compacting an orthogonal shape
minimizing the area or the total edge length of the drawing is NP-hard, while
polynomial time solutions for particular classes of orthogonal shapes exist <cite>Bridgeman et al. 2000</cite>.
</text>


<text>
Several standards have been proposed in the literature to extend the topology-shape-metrics approach so as to work with graphs of any vertex degree. Here we recall the Kandisky drawing convention, originally described by <cite>Fossmeier and Kaugmann 1997</cite>. A Kandisky drawing is an orthogonal drawing with the following properties:

- Segments representing edges cannot cross, with the exception that two segments that are incident of the same vertex may overlap (the angle between such segments has 0º).

- All the polygons representing the faces have area strictly greater than 0.

- Vertices are drawn as boxes with equal size and overlapping segments are drawn as very near segments.

The Kandisky model has been further extended by <cite>Di Battista et al. 1999</cite> to
deal with drawings in which the size (width and height) of each single vertex is
assigned by the user. Having the possibility of customizing the size of each vertex
is important in many application contexts; for example, this makes it possible to
place a textual or graphical label in a vertex without intersecting any other element
of the drawing <cite>Binucci et al. 2002</cite> <cite>Binucci et al. 2005</cite>.
</text>

</document>

