<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<!-- Scale-free networks -->

<document>
&bibliography;
<tag>scale-free</tag>
<title>Scale-free networks</title>


<text>
N'2003: All of the models discussed so far take observed properties
of real-world networks, such as degree sequences
or transitivity, and attempt to create networks that incorporate
those properties. The models do not however
help us to understand how networks come to have those
properties in the first place. In this section we examine
a class of models whose primary goal is to explain
network properties. In these models, the networks typically
grow by the gradual addition of vertices and edges
in some manner intended to reflect growth processes that
might be taking place on the real networks, and it is these
growth processes that lead to the characteristic structural
features of the network.

In random networks, the average degree gives the characteristic scale (value) of the degree.
In scale-free networks: Large variability, the average degree not informative, no characteristic scale for the degree (hence "scale-free").
Scale-free
</text>

<text>
++ An alternative and intriguing idea, which has so far not been in-
vestigated in much depth, is that features such as power-law de-
gree distributions may arise through network optimization. See...
[Banavar, J. R., Maritan, A., and Rinaldo, A., Size and form in efficient transportation networks, Nature 399, 130{132 (1999).]
[Ferrer i Cancho, R. and Solé, R. V., Optimization in complex networks, Preprint cond-mat/0111222 (2001]
[Gaychuk, V., Lubashevsky, I., and Stosyk, A., Remarks on scaling properties inherent to the systems with hierarchically organized supplying network, Preprint nlin/0004033 (2000).]
[Valverde, S., Cancho, R. F., and Solé, R. V., Scale-free networks from optimal design, Europhys. Lett. 60, 512{517 (2002).]
[West, G. B., Brown, J. H., and Enquist, B. J., A general model for the origin of allometric scaling laws in biology, Science 276, 122{126 (1997).
[West, G. B., Brown, J. H., and Enquist, B. J., A general model for the structure, and allometry of plant vascular systems, Nature 400, 664{667 (1999)]

++ Many authors have studied models of network transitivity that make use of \triadic closure" processes. 
[Banks, D. L. and Carley, K. M., Models for network evolution, Journal of Mathematical Sociology 21, 173{196 (1996).]
[Davidsen, J., Ebel, H., , and Bornholdt, S., Emergence of a small world from local interactions: Modeling acquaintance networks, Phys. Rev. Lett. 88, 128701 (2002).]
[Holme, P. and Kim, B. J., Growing scale-free networks with tunable clustering, Phys. Rev. E 65, 026107 (2002).]
[Jin, E. M., Girvan, M., and Newman, M. E. J., The structure of growing social networks, Phys. Rev. E 64, 046132 (2001).]
[Jost, J. and Joy, M. P., Evolving networks with distance preferences, Phys. Rev. E 66, 036126 (2002).]
[Klemm, K. and Eguiluz, V. M., Highly clustered scalefree networks, Phys. Rev. E 65, 036123 (2002).]
[Vázquez, A., Growing networks with local rules: Preferential attachment, clustering hierarchy and degree correlations, Preprint cond-mat/0211528 (2002).]
[Vázquez, A., Boguña, M., Moreno, Y., Pastor-Satorras, R., and Vespignani, A., Topology and correlations in structured scale-free networks, Preprint condmat/0209183 (2002).]
[Watts, D. J., Networks, dynamics, and the small world phenomenon, Am. J. Sociol. 105, 493{592 (1999).
[Watts, D. J., Small Worlds, Princeton University Press, Princeton (1999).]

  N'2003: In these models, edges are added to the network preferentially between pairs of vertices that have another third vertex as a common neighbor. In other words, edges are added so as to complete triangles, thereby increasing the amount of transitivity in the network.
  (There is some empirical evidence from collaboration networks in support of this mechanism.)
  [Newman, M. E. J., Clustering and preferential attachment in growing networks, Phys. Rev. E 64, 025102 (2001)]
</text>

<text>
Anthropologists such as Elman Service, when studying cultural evolution, envision chiefdoms being formed when several villages were bound by commerce. The village located at the nexus would naturally become the richest and would gradually grow dominant <cite>Wright 2000</cite>. This <q>rich get richer</q> effect is pervasive in networks...
</text>

<text>
A scale-free network is a network whose degree distribution obeys a power law, p(k) \sim k^{-q}, where k is the degree and q is an exponent typically between 2 and 3. Informally, a scale-free network is one with a small but significant number of nodes with a high degree and a large majority of nodes with a low degree. The nodes with high degree are called hubs. 
...
Scale-free networks are networks with hubs, which skew the degree distribution of the network.
...
Key properties not shared by other networks: 
- hubs 

L: A scale-free network connects a large proportion of the network’s nodes to a small fraction of nodes. This simple architecture is responsible for nearly all of the distinguishing properties of the class, from average path length, fast navigation, to local clustering

L: Scale-free networks exhibit structure by shifting from random connectivity to hub-like connectivity. In return, they sacrifice clustering and entropy. Intuitively,entropy goes into hub-like topology in a scale-free network, clustering in a small-world network, and disorder in a random network. This is why the class of scale-free networks is known as the “class with hubs,” and the class of small-world networks is known as the “class with clusters.”... Intuitively, a small-world network is a scale-free network with constraints on the degree of hubs, whereas a scale-free network has no such constraints.
</text>

<text>
A wide range of real-world networks have been found to exhibit power-law degree distributions: the World Wide Web, citation networks, cellular metabolism networks... 


L: Barabasi, Albert, and Jeong (Barabasi, 1999) argued that random or small-world network classes fail to model some real-world systems because they assume that the number of nodes n is set prior to activation of the underlying microrules. Real networks are dynamic, not static and therefore should be modeled as growth phenomena... They grow from a few nodes to many millions of nodes through an evolutionary process called preferential attachment. In simple terms, preferential attachment is biased—not random—which leads to networks with hubs. These early researchers concluded that the dynamic nature of some real-world systems is better represented by networks that “unfairly” add nodes and links as they evolve into nonrandom semistructured networks
[Barabasi, A.-L., R. Albert, and H. Jeong, Emergence of scaling in random networks, Science 286:509–512 (1999).]
</text>


<text>
Preferential attachment derives its name from the fact that the probability of a new node attaching to an existing node is proportional to the degree of the existing node. The higher the degree, the more likely a new link will be attached to the node. Clearly, high-degreed nodes become more connected and low-degreed nodes become less connected as the network grows. The resulting degree distribution is skewed toward low degree, because an increasing number of nodes decrease in degree as a few nodes greatly increase in degree.

L: 1925: Yule first observed preferential attachment in evolution
- A possible explanation for the observed power-law distriution of the number of species in genera (with exponent close to 2)
- Darwinian algorithm = the frequency of appearance of new species is proiportional to the number of species in a genus
i.e. Connect the new node to an existing node with probability proportional to the number of links already connected to the existing node, i.e. its degree
[Yule, G. U., A Mathematical theory of evolution based on the conclusions of Dr. J. C. Willis, Phil. Trans. Roy. Soc. Lond. B 213:21-87 (1925).]


L: the idea of nonrandomness as a factor in behavior and the connection between preferential attachment and nonrandom distributions occurred to Simon in 1955 [Simon, H. A., On a class of skew distribution functions, Biometrika 42(3/4):425-440 (1955).]
   ++ [Bornholdt, S. and Ebel, H., World Wide Web scaling exponent from Simon's 1955 model, Phys. Rev. E 64, 035104 (2001).]

  ++ Herbert Simon, who showed that power laws arise when \the rich get richer," when the amount you get goes up with the amount you already have. In sociology this is referred to as the Matthew effect, after the biblical edict, \For to every one that hath shall be given. . . " (Matthew 25:29). Price called it cumulative advantage. Today it is usually known under the name preferential attachment, coined by Barabasi and Albert.
  [Merton, R. K., The Matthew effect in science, Science 159, 56{63 (1968).]

  e.g. D: rich attracts more wealth, attractive woman attracts more looks, and also superstitions (a failure attracts more misfortunes)

++ Yule-Simon distribution


L: the earliest definition of preferential attachment, called cumulative advantage by Derek de Solla Price (Price, 1965, 1976), explained the power-law property of scale-free networks before such networks were called scale-free. Price’s model was slightly different from the BA model. The BA procedure ignores link direction, while the Price model did not, and the BA model starts from scratch, while the Price model assumes an existing network. Nonetheless, preferential attachment and cumulative advantage are identical concepts.
i.e. for explaining the growing directed network of scientific citations
[Price, D. J. de S., Networks of scientific papers, Science 149:510–515 (1965). ]
[Price, D. J. de S., A general theory of bibliometric and other cumulative advantage processes, J. Am. Soc. Inform. Sci. 27:292–306 (1976).]

  ++ N'2003: A the physicist-turned-historian-of-science Derek de Solla Price described in 1965 probably the first example of what would now be called a scale-free network; he studied the network of citations between scientific papers and found that both in- and out-degrees (number of times a paper has been cited and number of other papers a paper cites) have power-law distributions...

  the resulting degree distribution has a power-law tail with exponent \alpha = 2 + 1/m, where m is  the mean in-degree of the network (which is also the the mean out-degree of the network)

  ++ N'2003: In fact, this is really only a half of the Matthew effect, since the same verse continues, \. . . but from him that hath not, that also which he seemeth to have shall be taken away." In the processes studied by Simon and Price nothing is taken away from anyone. The full Matthew effect, with both the giving and the taking away, corresponds more closely to the Polya urn process than to Price's cumulative advantage. Price points out this distinction in his paper.


L: In fact, preferential attachment is known as the law of increasing returns in economics, adaptive
learning in artificial intelligence, and natural selection in biology. It is often
called “the rich get richer” (or the Matthew effect).
++ L: "a microrule called preferential attachment - that the probability a site will obtain a new link is directly proportional to the number of links it already has" (the <q>rich get richer</q> phenomenon).

1) a form of positive feedback that accelerates the acquisition of a commodity on the basis of the widespread or mainstream adoption of that commodity (increasing returns means a commodity becomes more valuable as it becomes more plentiful)

2) Adaptive learning in artificial intelligence: "Each response to a stimulus is
rewarded by increasing the probability that the same response will result from the
stimulus. Repetition increases the probability, which in turn increases the repetition
of the stimulus–response pair. Learning is a form of conditioning based on the
probability distribution established by repetition and positive feedback"

3) Natural selection is a similar process. In most species, stronger genes are replicated
in subsequent generations while weaker genes fade. The so-called fitness function of
an individual is akin to a power law—the more fit an individual is, the more likely it is
to survive, reproduce, and pass its genes on to the next generation. As fitness
increases, the gene is more likely to survive, and as survivability increases, so
does fitness. This feedback mechanism repeats many times, usually in extremely
small increments. Over time, fitter individuals emerge from weaker ancestors.


L: Preferential attachment describes an emergent process—that is, a process that results in a network topology that is not apparent by examination of the local algorithm, or microrule. It is not at all obvious that the result of repeated application of preferential attachment will result in a network with a degree distribution that follows a power law. This realization would come 70 years later, when A.-L. Barabasi and R. Albert showed how to create a scale-free network by repeated application of preferential attachment.

Mechanisms for preferential attachment
1. Copying mechanism: select a node and an edge of this node + attach to the endpoint of this edge
2. Walking on a network: the new node connects to a node, then to every first, second... neighbor of this node
3. Attaching to edges: select an edge attach to both endpoints of this edge
</text>



<document>
<tag>scale-free-models</tag>
<title>Models of scale-free network formation</title>


<document>
<tag>formation-barabasi-albert</tag>
<title>Barabasi-Albert model</title>

<text>

Network model based on their observations on the World Wide Web
- Small-world models operate only on sparse graphs.
- Highly connected sites dominate the Web.
- Distribution of the coordination numbers of sites is not bimodal but follows power-law.
- Does not show clustering which is present in the Web as well.

Network creation algorithm
- Start with a random network
- Take two vertex at random and add a link if it brings the distribution of z nearer to power-law
- Continue until correct coordination numbers reached
- Still otherwise a random graph

The network could also be created by generating N vertices with lines out of them according to power-law distribution and joining lines randomly until none are left.



[Barabasi, A.-L., R. Albert, and H. Jeong, Emergence of scaling in random networks, Science 286:509–512 (1999).]
demonstrated that power-law degree distributions can be generated by a <q>preferential attachment</q> growth process... the preferential attachment rule, which states that the probability of a link connecting node pairs is proportional to the degree of the new node.

L: random networks obey a uniformly random attachment rule, whereby the probability of attachment of a link to a pair of nodes is uniformly random... 
Instead of sampling from a uniformly random distribution, the Barabasi–Albert (BA) generative procedure creates dynamic networks by sampling from the degree distribution of network G at timestep t, namely, g0(t). The probability of a high-degreed node obtaining a subsequent link continues to rise as new nodes and links are added. The probability of a low-degreed node obtaining a subsequent link declines, so that over time, “popular nodes” become more popular, and out-of-favor nodes become less popular. 
</text>


<text>
[Barabasi, A.-L., R. Albert, and H. Jeong, Emergence of scaling in random networks, Science 286:509–512 (1999).]

  (1) Growth: Starting with a small number (m_0) of vertices, at every time step we add a new vertex with m (\leq m_0) edges (that will be connected to the vertices already present in the system).

  (2) Preferential attachment: When choosing the vertices to which the new vertex connects, we assume that the probability P that a new vertex will be connected to vertex i depends on the connectivity k_i of that vertex, such that P(k_i) = k_i / \sum_j k_j

  (3) After t time steps the model leads to a random network with N = t + m_0 vertices and mt edges.
</text>

<text>
BA generative procedure begins with a “triangular network” consisting of three nodes and three links, and then attaches a new node to as many as Dm other nodes by preferential attachment. setting n_0 = m_0 = 3, and substituting m for \Delta m to avoid confusion with the total number of links in a network...
Starting with n = 3 nodes, each of the remaining (n - 3) nodes are attached to the network by adding \Delta m links to existing nodes. For sufficiently large networks and sufficiently small \Delta m, m is approximately (\Delta m)n, and the degree distribution obeys a power law of the form p(k) \sim k^{-3}.
</text>

<text>
Parameters:
\Delta m = number of links to add to each new node;
n = desired network size.


L: The BA scale-free network is generated by repeated application of a simple dynamic network construction algorithm:

  1. Starting with three nodes and three links, grow the network by adding one node at each timestep t.
  2. Link the new node to \Delta m other nodes using preferential attachment.
  3. Repeat this until all n nodes have been added to the network.

This takes an additional t = (n - 3) steps to add (n - 3) additional nodes to the initial three nodes and three links. In the early stages of formation, fewer than \Delta m links are added because network size n is too small. When n &lt; Dm, only n links are added. Thus, at the end of the growth stage, the scale-free network has
</text>

<equation>
m = (\Delta m) n - \sum_{i=1}{\Delta m} i = (\Delta m) n - \frac{ \Delta m ( \Delta m - 1)} {2}
</equation>

<text>
IMPLEMENTING PREFERENTIAL ATTACHMENT

L: Of particular interest is the method of finding a replacement node when the node
selected by preferential attachment leads to a duplicate link. When this happens, the
code rolls variable j forward, seeking a node with higher index. This is achieved by
incrementing j until it exceeds nNodes, and then starting over again with node 0.

1. select an existing head node u by sampling from the degree cumulative distribution function CDF(i) defined by

CDF(i) = \sum_{j=1}{i} \frac {d(n_j)}{total}

where total is given by the current number of nodes in the network

ii. Let r be a uniform random number from [0,1). Then u is a random variate sampled from CDF(i) as follows:
CDF(u - 1) \geq r \geq CDF(u);

iii. Connect v with u, taking care to avoid duplicate links.


NOTE: CDF is recomputed each time a new node is added because total number of links and node degrees change after each insertion.
</text>


N'2002: A naive simulation of the preferential attachment process is quite inefficient. In order to attach to a vertex in
proportion to its degree we normally need to examine the degrees of all vertices in turn, a process that takes O(n) time for each step of the algorithm. Thus the generation of a graph of size n would take O(n^2) steps overall. A much better procedure, which works in O(1) time per
step and O(n) time overall, is the following. We maintain a list, in an integer array for instance, that includes ki entries of value i for each vertex i. Thus, for example, a network of four vertices labeled 1, 2, 3, and 4 with degrees 2, 1, 1, and 3, respectively could be represented
by the array (1; 1; 2; 3; 4; 4; 4). Then in order to choose a target vertex for a new edge with the correct preferential attachment, one simply chooses a number at random from this list. Of course, the list must be updated as new vertices and edges are added, but this is simple. Notice
that there is no requirement that the items in the list be in any particular order. If we add a new vertex 5 to our network above, for example, with degree 1 and one edge that connects it to vertex 2, the list can be updated by adding new items to the end, so that it reads
(1; 1; 1; 2; 3; 4; 4; 4; 5; 2). And so forth.

An alternative method for simulating the model of
Barabasi and Albert has been described by Krapivsky
and Redner
[Krapivsky, P. L. and Redner, S., Organization of growing random networks, Phys. Rev. E 63, 066123 (2001).]

Their method uses the network structure itself in place of the list of vertices above and works as follows. The model is regarded as a directed network in which there are exactly m edges running out of each vertex, pointing to others. We first pick a vertex at random from the graph and then with some probability we either keep that vertex or we \redirect" to one of its neighbors, meaning that we pick at random one of the vertices it points to. Since each vertex has exactly m outgoing edges, the latter operation is equivalent to choosing an edge at random from the graph and following it, and hence alights on a target vertex with probability proportional to the in-degree j of that target (because there are j ways to arrive at a vertex of in-degree j). Thus the total probability of selecting any given vertex is proportional to j + c, where c is some constant. However, since the out-degree of all vertices is simply m, the total degree is k = j +m and the selection probability is therefore also proportional to k + c .. m. By choosing the probability of redirection appropriately, we can arrange for the constant c to be equal to m, and hence for the probability of selecting a vertex to be simply proportional to k. Since it does not require an extra array for the vertex list, this method of simulation is more
memory efficient than the previous method, although it is slightly more complicated to implement. 

<comment>
<title>Random resampling</title>

<text>
Alternatives for roulette wheel selection 

A) Weight normalization + cumulative weights + single random U[0,1] for each new sample
O(n) for a single sample, O(n^2) for n samples, O(nlog n) for n samples if binary search is employed

B) Wheel + multiple calls to an uniform random number generator for each new sample
O(n) for a single sample in the worst case, O(n^2) for n samples in the worst case, i.e. a extremely skewed distribution
O(k) for a single sample in the average case, O(kn) for n samples in the average case
Faster than the standard roulette wheel selection, despite higher number of calls to RNG ???
++ "B is faster when the weights are uniformly distributed, and slower when they are exponentially distributed"

++ "the resampling wheel aims to take advantage of the fact that we are going to select a large number of particles at once as opposed to "a particle at a time"."
++ "tradeoff seems to be that you want as small an interval as possible to minimize the number of particles you visit on each step but still is sufficiently random to approximate the desired distribution. If the interval was very small then all of your samples would reside on a tiny slice of the wheel. If the interval is too large then you waste time "visiting." 2 * max(w) assures that you get at least one "new" particle per iteration of the algorithm. Why not use max(w) instead? That would bias the probability of choosing the larger elements because elements close to max(w) in size are essentially guaranteed to be selected"
i.e. 2*wmax is a somewhat arbitrary value that balances keeping the tries to keep the algorithm efficient without overly biasing the results.
i.e. if the increment was less than wmax, you would be guaranteed to select the highest probability particle so the results would definitely be biased. If the increment was 10*wmax, you would be looping through alot more particles and you algorithm would be less efficient.


C) Walker's alias method, slightly faster, especially if there are many samples. 
O(n) setup time using Vose's algorithm (makes sense if you do lots of sampling) + samples in O(1).
An implementation in python can be found @ <url>http://code.activestate.com/recipes/576564/</url>, 

Walker's algorithm essentially arranges a given lot of sticks into equal-length rows: pick a row shorter than average and a row longer than average, split the longer to fill the shorter, iterate until they're all the same length.


Walker's method involves setting up \magic" tables of length nn, where nn is the smallest power of 2 that is \geq n.


ref. On the Alias Method for Generating Random Variables from a Discrete Distribution
     Richard A. Kronmal and Arthur V. Peterson, Jr.
     The American Statistician
     Vol. 33, No. 4 (Nov., 1979), pp. 214-218
     <url>http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/2683739</url>

    "A Linear Algorithm For Generating Random Numbers With a Given Distribution" by Michael Vose
    IEEE  TRANSACTIONS ON SOFTWARE  ENGINEERING,  VOL.  17, NO.  9, 972-975  SEPTEMBER  1991
    <url>http://web.eecs.utk.edu/~vose/Publications/random.pdf</url>


ref. "Darts, Dice, and Coins: Sampling from a Discrete Distribution"
     Tutorial by Keith Schwarz, lecturer in Stanford's CS department: http://www.keithschwarz.com/darts-dice-coins/

++ http://www.google.com/patents/US5247677
   "Stochastic priority-based task scheduler
   Robert V. Welland, Walter R. Smith
   US Patent (Apple Computer, Inc.)
   Patent number: 5247677
   Filing date: May 22, 1992
   Issue date: Sep 21, 1993

++  L. Devroye, Non-Uniform Random Variate Generation, 1986, p. 107 ff., http://cg.scs.carleton.ca/~luc/rnbookindex.html
    Knuth, Stanford GraphBase, 1993, p. 392, http://tex.loria.fr/sgb.html
    Seminumerical Algorithms, second edition, exercise 3.4.1-7. 
    C++ hat random container by AngleWyrm, http://home.comcast.net/~anglewyrm/hat.html

++ non-random resampling ;-) "sorting the weights largest to smallest and then calculating exactly how many particles correspond to each of those weights. Because it isn't homework, I assume it is okay to post this non-random resampling algorithm."
</text>

<text>
Evaluation (Matlab):
</text>

<code>
for i=1:N
  distribution(i) = sum(new==i)/N; % frequency of index i
endfor

error = sqrt(sum((distribution - weight).^2))/N;
</code>

<text>
Applications: Preferential attachment, selection method in genetic algorithms (a.k.a. fitness proportionate selection or roulette-wheel selection), resampling in particle filters (e.g. robot localization).
</text>

<text>
ref. ON RESAMPLING ALGORITHMS FOR PARTICLE FILTERS
<url>http://www.control.isy.liu.se/~schon/Publications/HolSG2006.pdf</url>
</text>

</comment>

<algorithm>
<title>Choosing items in proportion to their importance weights</title>
<code>
# 1) Roulette wheel: inefficient <eqn>O(n^2)</eqn> implementation

# Weight normalization

W = sum(weight)

for i in range(N): 
    weight[i] = weight[i]/W

# Resampling

for i in range(N):
    r = random.random()
    index = 0
    s = weight[0]
    while (index&lt;N) and (s&lt;r):
        index = index + 1
        s = s + weight[index]
    if (index==N):
        index = N-1
    new[i] = element[index]


# 2) Resampling wheel: starting from a (uniformly) random index, O(n) on average, but might be O(n^2)

# Initial selection

index     = int(random.random() * N)
beta      = 0.0
maxWeight = max(weight)

# Resampling: U[0,2*maxWeight]

for i in range(N):
    beta += 2.0 * maxWeight * random.random()
    while (beta &gt; weight[index]):
        beta -= weight[index]
        index = (index+1) % N
    new[i] = element[index]


# 3) Improved resampling wheel, O(n) worst case (Curt Welch)
# + Only one loop around the wheel, instead of many.
# + Wheel divided into N slices
# + Noise in w rather than calls to random() !!
# ref. "On Resampling Algorithms for Particle Filters"

    p3 = [0]*N  # minor speed up by pre-allocating list
    index = 0
    w_sum = sum(w)
    step = w_sum / N
    beta = (w_sum * w_sum) % step
    for i in range(N):
        while beta &gt; w[index]:
            beta -= w[index]
            index = (index + 1) % N
        beta += step
        p3[i] = p[index]
    p = p3
</code>
</algorithm>




<text>
++ When new links involve a cost, i.e. they cost energy or occupy space, the degree distribution becomes truncated for high degrees <cite>Amaral et al. 2000</cite>. Networks that exhibit a scale-free behavior only through a range of node degrees are called broad-scale networks.
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>formation-barabasi-albert-generalizations</tag>
<title>Generalizations of the Barabasi-Albert model</title>

<text>
++ Generalizations of the Barabasi-Albert model <cite>Newman 2003</cite>, p. 34ff
e.g. Table III in <cite>Albert and Barabasi 2002</cite>


Another variation on the basic growing network theme is to make the mean degree change over time, Dorogovtsev and Mendes
[Dorogovtsev, S. N. and Mendes, J. F. F., Effect of the accelerating growth of communications networks on their structure, Phys. Rev. E 63, 025101 (2001).]
[Dorogovtsev, S. N. and Mendes, J. F. F., Accelerated growth of networks, in S. Bornholdt and H. G. Schuster
(eds.), Handbook of Graphs and Networks, pp. 318{341, Wiley-VCH, Berlin (2003).]

Dorogovtsev and Mendes have proposed a model that adds to the standard Barabasi{Albert model an extra mechanism whereby edges appear and  disappear between pre-existing vertices with stochastically constant but possibly different rates.
[Dorogovtsev, S. N. and Mendes, J. F. F., Scaling behaviour of developing and decaying networks, Europhys. Lett. 52, 33{39 (2000).]

Krapivsky and Redner have also proposed a model that allows edges to be added after vertices are created, which we discuss in the next section. 
[Krapivsky, P. L. and Redner, S., A statistical physics perspective on Web growth, Computer Networks 39, 261{276 (2002).]

Albert and Barabasi and Tadic have studied models in which edges can move around the network after they are added. These models can show both power-law and exponential degree distributions depending on the model parameters.
[Albert, R. and Barabasi, A.-L., Topology of evolving networks: Local events and universality, Phys. Rev. Lett. 85, 5234{5237 (2000).]
[Tadic, B., Dynamics of directed graphs: The World-Wide Web, Physica A 293, 273{284 (2001).]
[Tadic, B., Temporal fractal structures: Origin of power laws in the World-Wide Web, Physica A 314, 278{283 (2002).]

Adamic and Huberman have shown that the real World Wide Web does not have the correlations between age and degree of vertices that
are found in the model of Barabasi and Albert. Adamic and Huberman suggest that this is because the degree of vertices is also a function of their intrinsic worth; some Web sites are useful to more people than others and so gain links at a higher rate. 
[Adamic, L. A. and Huberman, B. A., Power-law distribution of the world wide web, Science 287, 2115 (2000).]
Bianconi and Barabasi have proposed an extension of the Barabasi{Albert model that mimics this process.
[Bianconi, G. and Barabasi, A.-L., Bose{Einstein condensation in complex networks, Phys. Rev. Lett. 86, 5632{5635 (2001).]
[Bianconi, G. and Barabasi, A.-L., Competition and multiscaling in evolving networks, Europhys. Lett. 54, 436{442 (2001).]

+ variations on the fitness theme have been studied by Ergün and Rodgers
[Ergun, G. and Rodgers, G. J., Growing random networks with fitness, Physica A 303, 261{272 (2002).],
  + A model with vertex fitness but no preferential attachment has been studied by Caldarelli et al., and also gives power-law degree distributions under some circumstances.  [Caldarelli, G., Capocci, A., De Los Rios, P., and Mu~noz, M. A., Scale-free networks from varying vertex intrinsic fitness, Phys. Rev. Lett. 89, 258702 (2002).]
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>formation-klemm-eguiluz</tag>
<title>Klemm-Eguiluz model</title>

A model with high clustering coefficient
- Each node of the network can be either active or inactive.
- There are only m active nodes in the network at any instance.

1. Start with m active, completely connected nodes
2. At each timestep add a new node (active) that connects to m active nodes.
3. Deactivate one active node

p_d(k_i) \propto (a+k_j)^-1

\Pi k \approx a + k

p(k) \approx k_{-2-a/m}

[K. Klemm and V. Eguiluz, Phys. Rev. E 65, 036123 (2002)]


</document>

<document>
<tag>formation-aggregation</tag>
<title>Aggregation models</title>


<text>
Aggregation as an alternative formation model:  

<cite>Alava and Dorogotsev 2005</cite>
[
ABSTRACT: ... aggregation as a mechanism for the creation of complex networks. In this evolution process vertices merge together, which increases a number of highly connected hubs. We study a range of complex network architectures produced by the aggregation. Fat-tailed (in particular, scale-free) distributions of connections are obtained for both networks with a finite number of vertices and growing networks. We observe a strong variation of a network structure with growing density of connections and find the phase transition of the condensation of edges. Finally, we demonstrate the importance of structural correlations in these networks.
]
</text>

<text>
Another alternative model that yields a power law degree distribution:  
When the network evolution allows merging nodes (i.e. a pair of nodes is merged and their degrees are added).
[
B.J. Kim, A. Trusina, P. Minnhagen, and K. Sneppen
Self organized scale-free networks from merging and regeneration
Eur. Phys. J. B 43, 369-372 (2005) 
DOI: 10.1140/epjb/e2005-00065-y

ABSTRACT: ... the ubiquitous scale free nature of many real world networks may emerge from a steady state process where nodes are created and merged randomly. The merging may be viewed as an optimization of efficiency by minimizing redundancy.
]
</text>

</document>

</document>

<!-- Properties -->

<document>
<tag>scale-free-properties</tag>
<title>Structural properties of scale-free networks</title>

<text>
- The degree distribution is a decreasing function, usually a power-law
- The betweenness centrality distribution is a power law as well
* Both indicate heterogeneity and the existence of hubs.
- The distances scale logarithmically with the network size
- The clustering coefficient does not seem to depend on the network size CC \propto \langle d \rangle
</text>

<document>
<tag>scale-free-properties-degree</tag>
<title>Degree distribution</title>

<text>
L: ++ Before Barabasi-Albert model, most networks were thought to be random, with Poisson degree distributions.
</text>

<text>
<cite>Newman 2003</cite> proved that the scale-free network degree distribution, p(k) \sim k^{-3}, is a direct consequence of the change in the expected number of nodes with degree k after each new node is added.

A fraction of nodes with degree (k - 1) increase their degree to k, and another fraction of nodes increase their degree from k to (k + 1). The net change in fraction of nodes with degree k is the difference between these two.

we approximate the net change in nodes with degree k by observing that a new node is attached to the network by Dm links, which transitions
a fraction of nodes of degree (k - 1) to nodes of k degrees, and another fraction of nodes of degree k to nodes of (k + 1) degree. The difference between the distribution before adding a node and after adding a node is averaged, which leads to a closed-form equation for p(k).

The derivation given by Newman makes a number of assumptions that may not be valid for all scale-free networks. For example, the derivation assumes linearity—the probability of link attachment varies directly proportional to the degree of the destination node. Alternately, the relationship could be proportional to the square of destination node degree, square root, and so on. Nonetheless, Newman’s linear model seems to give an accurate result for the BA generative procedure. 


Strategy:


1. Let <eqn>p_t(k)</eqn> represent the degree distribution at timestep <eqn>t</eqn>, and let <eqn>\Delta m</eqn> be the number of links attached each time a new node is added to the Barabasi-Albert scale-free network. One new node and <eqn>\Delta m</eqn> links are added at each timestep; hence the number of nodes with degree <eqn>k</eqn> at time <eqn>t</eqn> is <eqn>np_t(k)</eqn>, and the number of nodes with degree <eqn>k</eqn> at timestep <eqn>(t + 1)</eqn> is <eqn>(n + 1)p_{t+1}(k)</eqn>.

2. Using the degree distribution <eqn>p_t(k)</eqn> at timestep t, construct a meanfield equation expressing the expected change in number of nodes with degree k for a typical timestep. Note that the expected number of nodes with degree k after insertion of a new node is <eqn>\Delta m p_t(k - 1)</eqn>, and the expected number of nodes that no longer have degree k is <eqn>\Delta m p_t(k)</eqn> after the new node is inserted. In other words, some nodes transition from degree <eqn>(k - 1)</eqn> to <eqn>k</eqn>, and others transition from degree <eqn>k</eqn> to degree <eqn>(k + 1)</eqn>.

3. Solve the mean-field equation for the stationary (time-invariant) case, yielding <eqn>p(k)</eqn>. Time invariance means that <eqn>p_{t-1}(k) = p_t(k) = p(k)</eqn>. This is the so-called stationary process solution, which represents the final state of the scale-free network. <eqn>p(k)</eqn> is the degree distribution function after <eqn>n</eqn> nodes have been attached.
</text>

<text>
1. linear relation between probability of attachment and degree distribution.

The degree distribution <eqn>p_t(k)</eqn> is the fraction of nodes with degree k, at timestep t. Note that <eqn>\sum_k p_t(k) = 1</eqn>, which is independent of t. Preferential attachment uses this fraction to select the node with degree k that is linked to the new node with the following probability:
</text>

<equation>
\frac{ k p_t(k) } { \sum_k p_t(k) } =  \frac{ k p_t(k) } { \lambda }
</equation>

<text>
where <eqn>\lambda</eqn> is the average degree, as usual. We also know that <eqn>\lambda = 2(m/n)</eqn> for any network, and <eqn>m \approx n \Delta m</eqn>. Thus, the fraction of nodes with degree k is <eqn>(k p_t(k)) / (2 \Delta m)</eqn>, after substituting <eqn>\lambda \approx 2 \Delta m</eqn> into the equation for <eqn>p_t(k)</eqn>.
</text>

<text>
2. Mean-field equation that relates the “before”/“after” change in number of nodes with degree k

Change in number of nodes with degree k equals the number of nodes increased from degree (k - 1) to degree k, minus the number of nodes increased from degree k to degree (k + 1).
</text>

<text>
The left-hand side of the mean-field equation is the expected number of nodes with degree k after insertion of a new node, minus the number before insertion:
</text>

<equation>
(n+1) p_{t+1}(k) - n p_t(k)
</equation>

<text>
The right-hand-side is the expected number of links connecting to nodes with degree (k - 1) minus the number of nodes that are no longer of degree k because they increased to degree (k + 1):
</text>

<equation>
\Delta m (k - 1) \frac { p_t(k-1)} { 2 \Delta m } - \Delta m \frac { k p_t(k)} { 2 \Delta m }
</equation>

<text>
which can be simplified to
</text>

<equation>
(k - 1) \frac { p_t(k-1)} { 2 } - \frac { k p_t(k)} { 2 }
</equation>

<text>
The time-varying mean-field equation for <eqn>k &gt; \Delta m</eqn> is
</text>

<equation>
(n+1) p_{t+1}(k) - n p_t(k) = \frac {k-1} { 2 } p_t(k-1) - \frac { k } { 2 } p_t(k)
</equation>

<text>
Since there are no nodes with a degree lower than <eqn>\Delta m</eqn>, we know that <eqn>p(k)=0</eqn> for <eqn>k &lt; \Delta m</eqn>. For <eqn>k = \Delta m</eqn>, we obtain the following expression given that a single node increases its degree to <eqn>\Delta m</eqn> (i.e. the new one):
</text>

<equation>
(n+1) p_{t+1}(\Delta m) - n p_t(\Delta m) = 1 - \frac { \Delta m } { 2 } p_t(\Delta m)
</equation>


<text>
3. The stationary, or time-invariant solution, obtained by setting <eqn>p_{t+1}(k) = p_t(k) = p(k)</eqn>:
</text>

<equation>
p(k) = \frac {k-1} { 2 } p(k-1) - \frac{k}{2} p(k) 
</equation>

<text>
for <eqn>k &gt; \Delta m</eqn>, and
</text>

<equation>
p(\Delta m) = 1 - \frac{\Delta m}{2} p(\Delta m)
</equation>

<text>
when <eqn>k = \Delta m</eqn>. Therefore
</text>

<equation>
p(\Delta m) = \frac{2}{\Delta m + 2}
</equation>

<text>
And, rearranging for <eqn>k &gt; \Delta m</eqn>:
</text>

<equation>
p(k) = \frac {k-1} {k-2} p(k-1)
</equation>


<text>
Expanding the recurrence, we obtain
</text>

<equation>
p(k) = \frac{(k-1)(k-2)...\Delta m}{(k+2)(k+1)...(\Delta m+3)} p(\Delta m)
</equation>

<text>
which yields the solution for the degree distribution of the Barabasi-Albert model:
</text>

<equation>
p(k) = \frac{2 \Delta m (\Delta m + 1)}{(k+2)(k+1)k}
</equation>

<text>
For large <eqn>k</eqn> and constant <eqn>\Delta m</eqn>, <eqn>p(k)</eqn> is a power law with <eqn>q = 3</eqn>, since <eqn>p(k) \sim k^{-3}</eqn>.

++ Notice how the above determines the degree distribution regardless of the network size, which has no influence in the BA model.

Barabasi et al. (Barabasi, 1999) describe another alternative to the derivation given by Newman...
[Barabasi, A.-L., R. Albert, and H. Jeong, Emergence of scaling in random networks, Science 286:509–512 (1999).]
and <cite>Newman 2003</cite> discusses other solutions, yielding different values of q, based on different assumptions.
</text>


<text>
++ This derivation yields an exponent q=3 for BA scale-free networks, but in practice, a network is considered scale-free if 2 \leq q \leq 3. 
Technically, any value of q satisfies the scale-free relation p(\alpha k) = \beta p(k).
</text>


<text>
++ Proportional preferential attachment yields scale-free networks with an exponent of 3. Refined attachment rules that vary node attractiveness yield scale-free networks with exponents between 2 and 3.

A slight change in the rule for preferential attachment is sufficient. The probability of linking to a node of degree <eqn>k</eqn> is made proportional to a preference function <eqn>f(k)</eqn>. Instead of maintaining a proportional preference, as in the Barabasi-Albert model, where <eqn>f_{BA}(k) = k</eqn>, we make it linear by incorporating an additional attrativeness to each node, so that <eqn>f_{linear}(k) = k + \alpha \Delta m</eqn>, where <eqn>\alpha &gt; -1</eqn> is a constant. This linear preference function leads to power laws with exponent <eqn>\lambda = 3 + \alpha</eqn>.

Actually, <eqn>\gamma</eqn> can take values from 2 to infinity, which would correspond to a growing random network with uniform attachment and not a scale-free network.

The preferential attachment mechanism generates power-law degree distributions only when the preference function is linear. 
Krapivsky et al. also consider another important generalization of the model, to the case where the probability of attachment to a vertex is not linear in the degree k of the vertex, but goes instead as some general power of degree k^\gamma... this model is solvable using methods similar to those above, and the authors find three general classes of behavior. 
[Krapivsky, P. L. and Redner, S., Organization of growing random networks, Phys. Rev. E 63, 066123 (2001).]
[Krapivsky, P. L., Redner, S., and Leyvraz, F., Connectivity of growing random networks, Phys. Rev. Lett. 85, 4629{4632 (2000).]
Pavel Krapivski and Sid Reiner have shown that when the preference function is <eqn>k^\gamma</eqn>:

  - For \phi = 1 exactly, we recover the normal linear preferential attachment and power-law degree sequences. 
  - For \phi &lt; 1, the degree distribution is a power law multiplied by a stretched exponential, whose exponent is a complicated function of \gamma. (i.e. the degree distribution decays slower than exponentially but faster than a power law when)
  - For \gamma &gt; 1 there is a \condensation" phenomenon, in which a single vertex gets a finite fraction of all the connections in the network
  - For \gamma &gt; 2, there is a non-zero probability that this \gel node" will be connected to every other vertex on the graph. The remainder of the vertices have an exponentially decaying degree distribution.
</text>



<text>
L: Networks whose degree distribution approximates a power law,
<eqn>p(k)=k^{-q}</eqn>, for some power <eqn>q &gt; 1</eqn>. 

L:Such graphs are called scale-free because the power-law distribution has no scale parameter; that is, the variance of a power-law is
infinite, versus the finite variance of most other distributions such as the Gaussian or normal distribution. Power laws are also sometimes called “fat tailed” because they do not decline as k increases as fast as an exponential or normal distribution.

Random graphs more or less distribute links uniformly across n nodes. But... scale-free graphs are lopsided - a vast number of nodes have only one or two links, while a rare few nodes have perhaps hundreds of links... 


scale-free graphs have less entropy than random graphs, but more than small worlds...
The entropy of a scale-free graph is generally lower than the entropy of a random
graph because scale-free networks contain some structure. Scale-free networks are closer to the random end of the "graph structure" spectrum
than to the structured extreme. At one end is the class of structured k-regular graphs
(where entropy equals zero), and the other end is the class of random networks that
have no discernable structure or topology. In between is the class of scale-free networks,
which have some structure, because the degree distribution obeys a power law.
</text>


<text>
A power law implies that the probability of finding a node with a degree that is twice as large as a given number decreases by a constant factor, rather than following an exponential falloff. 

L: Power-law distributions are not exponential distributions even though they appear
to be similar. The tail of an exponential distribution vanishes much faster. For this
reason, power-law distributions are often called “fat tail” distributions.

L: The power law  declines more slowly than the exponential distribution so commonly found to model phenomena in the physical world. 
k^-q &gt; exp(-qk)  for most values of 1 &lt; q &lt; 3. Even when the power-law function is
adjusted to match at k=1, the exponential function declines more rapidly as k increases. This is why power-law distributions are sometimes
called “long” or “fat tail” distributions.


Power laws:
- Vilfredo Pareto: Income distribution (1897)
- J.B. Estoup (1916) and George Kingsley Zipf (1932): frequency of occurrence of distinct words in a text
- F. Auerbach (1913): Distribution of city size
- Alfred James Lotka (1926): Number of papers by a scientist


The power law is related to Zipf’s, Pareto’s, and Yule–Simon’s laws, but is somewhat more general.

- Zipf’s law states that the frequency of a word w in the English language is inversely proportional to its rank in the frequency table: f(w) = c/(r(w)), where r(w) is the word’s rank and c is a constant.

- Pareto’s distribution—also known as the 80/20 rule—says that 20% of the population has 80% of the wealth. 

- The Yule–Simon distribution is asymptotic to a power law: f (k) * 1/k^{p+1}. Yule may have been the first modern scientist to identify
natural processes that follow a power law (Yule, 1925).

[Zipf, G. K., Human Behavior and the Principle of Least Effort, Addison-Wesley Press, Cambridge, MA, 1949.]
[Yule, G. U., A Mathematical theory of evolution based on the conclusions of Dr. J. C. Willis, Phil. Trans. Roy. Soc. Lond. B 213:21–87 (1925).]

++ exponent of the power law distribution.

L: "the probability that a site has k links obeys a power law, which drops off quickly for large k"
... A network that follows a power-law distribution means that it has a
hub, and many other nodes with many fewer links than the average. This lopsided
preference for hubs seemed counter to nature, which typically follows a normal distribution.
</text>


<text>
L: A scale-free graph has many nodes with very low degree, and one node with very
high degree. Hence, its degree distribution is skewed to the left—toward small degree
values. Because so many nodes are connected to the graph’s hub node, the scale-free
graph also exhibits a small graph diameter—similar to a random graph. It is nearly
one-half the diameter of the small-world graph, and 50% smaller than the diameter
of a random graph. This is a consequence of the high concentration of links attached
to the hub. The unexpectedly large hub degree is a distinguishing property of scalefree
graphs.
</text>

<text>
IDEA: The fluctuations in degree are unbounded, i.e., the standard deviation is bounded only by the finite size of the graph.
</text>


<text>
The <q>scale-free</q> term refers to the fact that nodes in a scale-free network do not have a characteristic scale. You can zoom in on any segment of the distribution and it does not change its shape.

L: scale-free networks... The name came from observing that a function f(x) scales if f(ax) = a*f(x), which is
what a power law does. Therefore, if the degree distribution obeys the power law, p(x) = x ^-q, then it is clear that p(ax) = (ax)^-q = (a ^-q)p(x) = a' p(x).

L: Any function that obeys the relation p(\alpha k) = \beta p(k), for constants \alpha and \beta, is considered scale-free because scaling the x axis (independent variable) by a constant factor \alpha, results in scaling the y axis (dependent variable) also by a constant factor \beta. 
In this case, \beta = \alpha ^q, which is a constant relative to k. The effect of scaling the independent variable by a constant factor of a is to move the powerlaw curve up or down vertically, but does not change the shape or range of the curve...

</text>

<document>
<tag>scale-free-properties-density</tag>
<title>Density</title>

<text>
The density of a canonical BA scale-free network depends on the preferential attachment parameter \Delta m, which is the number of links used to attach each new node to other nodes during construction. This parameter determines the number of links in BA scale-free networks and, therefore, their density
</text>

<equation>
m = (\Delta m) n -  \frac{ \Delta m ( \Delta m - 1)} {2}
</equation>

<equation>
\rho = \frac {2m}{n(n-1)} = (\Delta m) \frac{ 2n - ( \Delta m + 1)} {n(n-1)} \approx \frac { 2 \Delta m} {n} 
</equation>


<text>
The degree  distribution of the canonical BA scale-free network is a power law which can be expressed in terms of the network density:
</text>

<equation>
\begin{aligned}
p(k) &amp; = \frac{ 2 \Delta m ( \Delta m + 1)} { k(k+1)(k+2) } \\
     &amp; = \frac{ n \rho ( n \rho + 2)} { 2k(k+1)(k+2) } \\
     &amp; \approx \frac { n^2 \rho^2 } {2k^3} 
\end{aligned}
</equation>

<text>
++ ability to scale network density while retaining a power-law relationship in its degree distribution.
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>scale-free-properties-hub</tag>
<title>Hub degree</title>

<text>
Hubs are the predominant feature of scale-free networks...
</text>

<text>
As the number of available links increases, so does the degree of the network's largest hub. In other words, the largest hub degree is expected to increase with density. 
</text>


<text>
The maximum degree d_max of a vertex in a network will in general depend on the size of the network. In work on scale-free networks, Aiello et al.
assumed that the maximum degree was approximately the value above which there is less than one vertex of that degree in the graph on average, i.e., the point where <eqn>np_k = 1</eqn>. This means, for instance, that kmax \sim n^{1-\alpha} for the power-law degree distribution p_k \sim k^{-\alpha}. This assumption often underestimates the higher degree, as discussed by Adamic et al. 
[Aiello, W., Chung, F., and Lu, L., A random graph model for massive graphs, in Proceedings of the 32nd Annual ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing, pp. 171{180, Association of Computing Machinery, New York (2000).]
[Adamic, L. A., Lukose, R. M., Puniyani, A. R., and Huberman, B. A., Search in power-law networks, Phys. Rev. E 64, 046135 (2001).]
</text>

<text>
We can also estimate the largest hub degree by solving a differential equation that relates rate of change in hub degree to the network density <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>:
</text>

<equation>
\frac{ \delta d_{max}(t) } { \delta t } = \rho
</equation>

<equation>
\frac{ \delta d_{max}(t) } { \delta t } = \frac{2m(t)}{n(t) ( n(t)+1 )}
</equation>

<text>
Since <eqn>\Delta m \approx m(t) / n(t)</eqn> and <eqn>n(t) \approx n(t+1)</eqn> for large values of <eqn>t</eqn>, we get
</text>

<equation>
\frac{ \delta d_{max}(t) } { \delta t } = \frac{2\Delta m}{n(t)}
</equation>

<text>
Integrating from 1 to n, we obtain
</text>

<equation>
d_{max}(t) = 2 \Delta m \ln n(t)
</equation>

<text>
which means that the largest node degree is given by:
</text>

<equation>
d_{max} = 2 \Delta m \ln n \sim \ln n
</equation>

<text>
L: The largest node degree grows with the network size, as expected, for both random and scale-free networks, but the rate of increase is much greater for a scale-free network.
</text>


<text>
L: ... limitations ...  because competition among the highest-degreed nodes in a very sparse network siphons off links from preferred nodes; that is, as density decreases (corresponding to increases in size, n), preference for the hub with the highest degree is overcome by the shortage of links. Because of this shortage, links must be acquired by competition among many high-degreed nodes. At some point, there simply aren’t enough links to go around, which limits logarithmic growth of hub degree.
</text>

<text>
A better approximation for the largest hub degree is given in <cite>Newman 2003</cite> for power-law distributions where <eqn>p_k \sim k^{-\alpha}</eqn>:
</text>

<equation>
d_{max} \sim n^{1/(\alpha - 1)}
</equation>

<text>
which agrees with the intuition behind the empirical quadratic approximation made by <cite>Lewis 2009</cite> for the Barabasi-Albert model, where <eqn>\alpha = 3</eqn> and, therefore, <eqn>d_{max} \sim \sqrt{n}</eqn>.
</text>

<text>
Cohen et al. employs a simple rule of thumb that leads to the same result: the maximum degree is roughly the value of k that solves np_k = 1. However, as shown by Dorogovtsev and Samukhin, the fluctuations in the tail of the degree distribution are very large for the power-law case. Dorogovtsev et al. have also shown that the above expression holds for Barabasi-Albert scale-free networks and a detailed numerical study can be found in  Moreira et al..
</text>

[Cohen, R., Erez, K., ben-Avraham, D., and Havlin, S., Resilience of the Internet to random breakdowns, Phys. Rev. Lett. 85, 4626{4628 (2000).]
[Dorogovtsev, S. N. and Samukhin, A. N., Mesoscopics and fluctuations in networks, Preprint condmat/0211518 (2002).]
[Dorogovtsev, S. N., Mendes, J. F. F., and Samukhin, A. N., Size-dependent degree distribution of a scale-free growing network, Phys. Rev. E 63, 062101 (2001).]
[Barabasi, A.-L. and Albert, R., Emergence of scaling in random networks, Science 286, 509{512 (1999).]
[Moreira, A. A., Andrade, Jr., J. S., and Amaral, L. A. N., Extremum statistics in scale-free network models, Preprint cond-mat/0205411 (2002).]


<text>
NOTE: Power laws with exponential cut-offs (any finite network with a heavy tail necessarily includes a cut-off, i.e. an end-part of the distribution with a rapid exponential decay). The highest possible cut-off point <eqn>k_{cut}(n)</eqn> is estimated to be of the order of <eqn>n^{1/(\gamma - 1)}</eqn> <cite>Dorogotsev 2010</cite>. When such a cut-off is present, it is called a <q>natural cut-off</q>.
</text>

<text>
In scale-free networks, when parallel links and loops are not allowed, the cut-off cannot be higher than <eqn>n^{1/2}</eqn> for <eqn>\gamma &lt; 3</eqn>. When nodes with higher degrees are present, the <term>rich club phenomenon</term> appears: such nodes form a densely-connected cluster within an otherwise sparse network. This phenomenon has been observed in many real-world networks, such as the Internet at both the AS and router levels <cite>Zhou and Mondragon 2004</cite>. It should be noted, however, that this club contains only a tiny fraction of the nodes in the network, about <eqn>n^{(3-\gamma)/2}</eqn> according to <cite>Colizza et al. 2006</cite>. Despite it size, it plays an important role as the core of the giant connected component of the network: it is essential for the robustness of the network against random failures.
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>scale-free-properties-entropy</tag>
<title>Entropy</title>

<text>
Since the degree distribution of a scale-free network follows a power low, it is possible to derive a closed-form equation for its entropy:
</text>

<equation>
\begin{aligned}
H(SF) &amp; = - \int_{\Delta m}^{\infty} p(k) \log_2 p(k) dk \\
      &amp; = - \int_{\Delta m}^{\infty} 2 \Delta m (\Delta m + 1) k^{-3} \log_2 \left( 2 \Delta m (\Delta m + 1) k^{-3} \right) dk
\end{aligned}
</equation>

<text>
Setting <eqn>\alpha = 2 \Delta m (\Delta m + 1)</eqn>:
</text>

<equation>
\begin{aligned}
H(SF) &amp; = - \int_{\Delta m}^{\infty} \alpha k^{-3} \log_2 \left( \alpha k^{-3} \right) dk \\
      &amp; = \frac{-\alpha } {\ln 2} \int_{\Delta m}^{\infty} k^{-3} \ln \left( \alpha k^{-3} \right) dk \\
      &amp; = \frac{-\alpha } {\ln 2} \int_{\Delta m}^{\infty} \frac{\ln \alpha - \ln k^3}{k^3} dk \\
      &amp; = \frac{-\alpha } {\ln 2} \int_{\Delta m}^{\infty} \frac{\ln \alpha - 3 \ln k}{k^3} dk \\
      &amp; = \frac{-\alpha } {\ln 2} \left[ \int_{\Delta m}^{\infty} \frac{\ln \alpha}{k^3} dk - 3 \int_{\Delta m}^{\infty} \frac{\ln k}{k^3} dk \right]
\end{aligned}
</equation>

<text>
The first integral is easy to solve:
</text>

<equation>
\begin{aligned}
\int_{\Delta m}^{\infty} \frac{\ln \alpha}{k^3} dk &amp; = \frac{\ln \alpha}{2 \Delta m^2}
\end{aligned}
</equation>

<text>
For the second term, we resort to integration by parts, using <eqn>u=\ln k</eqn>, <eqn>dv=k^{-3} dk</eqn>, <eqn>du=(1/k) dk = k^{-1} dk</eqn>, and <eqn>v=(-1/2k^2)</eqn>:
</text>

<equation>
\begin{aligned}
\int \frac{\ln k}{k^3} dk 
  &amp; = uv - \int vdu \\
  &amp; = - \frac{\ln k}{2k^2} - \int \frac{-1}{2k^2} \frac{1}{k} dk \\
  &amp; = - \frac{\ln k}{2k^2} - \int \frac{-1}{2k^3} dk \\
  &amp; = - \frac{\ln k}{2k^2} + \frac{1}{2} \int \frac{1}{k^3} dk \\
  &amp; = - \frac{\ln k}{2k^2} + \frac{1}{2} \frac{-1}{2k^2} \\
  &amp; = - \frac{\ln k}{2k^2} - \frac{1}{4k^2} \\
  &amp; = - \frac{2\ln k + 1}{4k^2} \\
\end{aligned}
</equation>

<text>
Therefore,
</text>

<equation>
\int_{\Delta m}^{\infty} \frac{\ln k}{k^3} dk = \frac{2\ln \Delta m + 1}{4 \Delta m^2} = \frac{\ln \Delta m + 1/2}{2 \Delta m^2}
</equation>

<text>
Combining both results, we obtain:
</text>

<equation>
\begin{aligned}
H(SF) &amp; = \frac{-\alpha } {\ln 2} \left[ \int_{\Delta m}^{\infty} \frac{\ln \alpha}{k^3} dk 
                                          - 3 \int_{\Delta m}^{\infty} \frac{\ln k}{k^3} dk \right] \\
      &amp; = \frac{-\alpha } {\ln 2} \left[ \frac{\ln \alpha}{2 \Delta m^2}
                                          - 3 \frac{\ln \Delta m + 1/2}{2 \Delta m^2} \right] \\
      &amp; = \frac{-\alpha } {\ln 2} \frac{\ln \alpha - 3 (\ln \Delta m + 1/2)}{2\Delta m^2} \\
\end{aligned}
</equation>

<text>
Now we recall that <eqn>\alpha = 2 \Delta m (\Delta m + 1)</eqn>:
</text>

<equation>
\begin{aligned}
H(SF) &amp; = - \frac{2 \Delta m (\Delta m + 1)}{\ln 2} \frac{\ln (2 \Delta m (\Delta m + 1)) - 3(\ln \Delta m + 1/2)}{2 \Delta m^2} \\
      &amp; = - \frac{\Delta m + 1} {\ln 2} \frac{ \ln (2 \Delta m (\Delta m + 1)) - 3 \ln \Delta m - 3/2}{\Delta m} \\
      &amp; = - \frac{\Delta m + 1} {\Delta m} \frac{ \ln (2 \Delta m (\Delta m + 1)) - 3 \ln \Delta m - 3/2}{\ln 2} \\
      &amp; = - \frac{\Delta m + 1} {\Delta m} \frac{ \ln 2 + \ln \Delta m + \ln (\Delta m + 1) - 3 \ln \Delta m - 3/2}{\ln 2} \\
      &amp; = - \frac{\Delta m + 1} {\Delta m} \left( 1 + \log_2 \Delta m + \log_2 (\Delta m + 1) - 3 \log_2 \Delta m - \frac{3}{2\ln 2} \right) \\
      &amp; = - \frac{\Delta m + 1} {\Delta m} \left( 1 + \log_2 (\Delta m + 1) - 2 \log_2 \Delta m - \frac{3}{2\ln 2} \right) \\
      &amp; = - \frac{\Delta m + 1} {\Delta m} \left( 1 + \log_2 \frac{\Delta m + 1}{\Delta m^2} - \frac{3}{2\ln 2} \right) \\
      &amp; = - \frac{\Delta m + 1} {\Delta m} \left( \left( 1 - \frac{3}{2\ln 2} \right) + \log_2 \frac{\Delta m + 1}{\Delta m^2} \right)  \\
\end{aligned}
</equation>

<text>
If we set <eqn>C = \frac{3}{2\ln 2} - 1 \approx 1.164</eqn> and <eqn>H_0 = \frac{\Delta m + 1} {\Delta m}</eqn>, we can simplify the above expression to:
</text>

<equation>
\begin{aligned}
H(SF) &amp; = H_0 \left( C + \log_2 \frac{\Delta m}{H_0} \right)
\end{aligned}
</equation>

<text>
for <eqn>2 \leq \Delta m \leq n-1</eqn>.
</text>

<text>
This result indicates that the entropy of the degree distribution for a Barabasi-Albert scale-free network depends exclusively on <eqn>\Delta m</eqn> and is independent of the network size. This entropy logarithmically increases with <eqn>\Delta m</eqn> and, since <eqn>\Delta m</eqn> is proportional to the network density, the entropy also increases with the logarithm of the network density. Unlike Poisson random networks, which become more structured as links are added to the network, entropy increases when we increase the density of scale-free networks.
</text>


<text>
A conjecture: a scale-free graph is more random than structured; a small-world graph is more structured than random
+ a scale-free network behaves more like a small-world network than a random network with respect to entropy

</text>

</document>

</document>

<document>
<tag>scale-free-properties-path-length</tag>
<title>Average path length</title>


<text>
L: The small path length of a scale-free network is due to its hubs—very high-degreed
nodes—rather than random links, acting as shortcuts.

L: The average path length of a (sparse) BA scale-free network is lower than the average path length of a (sparse) random network.
</text>

<text>
L: Intuitively, the average path length of a sparse scale-free network should be shorter than that of a random network of equal density because there are more long-haul links in a scale-free network...  path length slowly decreases with an increase in density—just as it does in a random network. But the decline in average path length of a scale-free network is more pronounced in sparse scale-free networks than in sparse random networks. This is
due to... hub nodes... 
...
But the difference quickly vanishes with increasing density
</text>


<text>
Average path length of a scale-free network follows a logarithmic approximation rather than a power law.
</text>

<text>
(1) L: Albert and Barabasi approximated the average path length of a BA scale-free network with average degree \lambda= 4
by fitting simulation data to a logarithmic curve (Albert, 2002): L(SF) = a \log (n+b) + c
</text>

<equation>
L(SF) \sim log (n)
</equation>

<text>
(2) L: More accurate estimates by Bollobas and Riordan do not appreciably improve the simple approximation given by Albert and Barabasi for small networks, yet they report their double-logarithmicapproximation seems to be more accurate for large networks such as the Internet:
[Bollobas, B., O. Riordan, J. Spencer, and G. Tusnady, The degree sequence of a scale-free random graph process, Random Struct. Algorithms 18(3):279–290 (2001).]
[
Béla Bollobás, Oliver Riordan
The Diameter of a Scale-Free Random Graph
Combinatorica, Volume 24 Issue 1, January 2004 
doi: 10.1007/s00493-004-0002-2
]
</text>

<equation>
L(SF) \sim log (n) 
</equation>

<text>
when <eqn>\Delta m = 1</eqn>, and
</text>

<equation>
L(SF) \sim log (n) / log (log (n))
</equation>

<text>
when <eqn>\Delta m &gt; 1</eqn> (i.e. cycles make the network more compact).
</text>

<text>
DENSITY: Recall that density = \lambda/n for any network, and if n remains constant, then density decreases with increasing size n. Therefore, average path length gradually rises with increase in size, because density declines.

L: Unfortunately, these theoretical estimates do not directly relate path length to adjustments in number of links, or hub size. For example, if we hold n constant and vary density, the average path length should rise and fall inversely with the rise and fall of density; the higher the density, the lower the path length. <cite>Lewis 2009</cite> studies the influence of network density on average path length... 

L: Average path length declines with increasing density of (any) network, because there are more alternate paths—some shorter than others—through a denser network. When a network is extremely sparse, fewer alternative paths are available to connect node u to node w. The lack of alternative paths in sparse scale-free networks can partially, but not completely, be made up by high-degreed hubs. Low-degreed nodes are more likely to be connected to hubs, and hubs establish long-haul links.
</text>

<text>
HUB DEGREE: Average path length linearly declines with hub degree

L: When dealing with very sparse scale-free networks, the degree of the hub may be a better predictor of the average path length for sparse networks...

L: If this hypothesis is true, we should be able to observe a correlation between hub degree and path length in a scale-free network. Intuitively, path length declines as hub degree increases because there are more long-haul links in a scale-free network...
The correlation is not strong, but the trend is clear—path length trends downward with increasing hub degree as hypothesized
...
the higher the hub degree of a scale-free network, the shorter the average path length
</text>

<text>
L: It is possible to control the path length of a scale-free network while simultaneously controlling the hub structure by changing density.
</text>

</document>



<document>
<tag>scale-free-betweenness</tag>
<title>Betweenness</title>


<text>
The betweenness centrality (a.k.a. load by physicists) characterizes the distribution of shortest paths within a network. Even though an exact betweenness distribution for random graphs has not been found (due to the complications that arise from the presence of cycles), the observed distribution for a wide range of scale-free networks <cite>Goh et al. 2001</cite> follows a power law:
</text>

<equation>
P(B) \sim B^{-\delta}
</equation>

<text>
with exponent <eqn>\delta \approx 2.2</eqn>. This exponent has been found to be nsensitive to different values of <eqn>\gamma</eqn> in the range <eqn>2 &lt; \gamma \leq 3</eqn> for different mean degrees, and it is valid for both undirected and directed cases. In fact, <cite>Goh et al. 2001</cite> conjecture that the load exponent is a universal quantity that characterizes scale-free networks. For <eqn>\gamma &gt; 3</eqn>, however, the load exponent <eqn>\delta</eqn> increases as the degree exponent <eqn>\gamma</eqn> increases, and eventually the load distribution decays exponentially.
</text>

<text>
L: ... hubs are  the largest intermediary nodes... i.e. most paths traverse them when connecting any two nodes
...  their betweenness property is also the highest.
... The dominant hub node of a scale-free network tends to insert direct links between itself and the majority of all other nodes, which eliminates intermediaries and reduces betweenness by an amount proportional to the degree of the hub
</text>

<text>
L: The average betweenness of a scale-free network is determined by its density and the size of its largest hub:
L: a suitable model of average betweenness in scale-free networks is...
</text>

<equation>
betweenness(SF) \sim \rho \lambda^r
</equation>

<text>
where
</text>

<equation>
r = \frac { log_2 (n - d_{hub}) } { log_2 \lambda }
</equation>

<text>
A a hub tends to directly connect to the majority of other nodes, therefore it tends to remove d_{hub} nodes from consideration as potential intermediaries. 

</text>

<text>
L: ++ generalizations can be made from this model:  average betweenness smoothly increases to a peak value, and then smoothly declines beyond 50% density, as fewer nodes escape direct connections with the dominant hub;
</text>

<text>
In terms of the importance of the most connected node: scale-free (highest), small-world (medium), random (lowest).

In terms of average betweenness, network classes are ranked as follows: random (highest), small-world (medium), and scale-free (lowest).

L: ... the average betweenness of scale-free networks is much lower than that of equivalent random and small-world networks. Generally, the average betweenness of a node in a scale-free network is one-half that of nodes in the other classes of network. There are far fewer, and less powerful, intermediaries in a scale-free network, on average. In a sense, the hub is the sole intermediary, with intermediary power over nearly all other nodes.
Scale-free networks have weaker intermediaries, on average, but the hub is much stronger than the strongest intermediary possible in small-world and random networks.
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>scale-free-clustering</tag>
<title>Clustering coefficient</title>

<text>
Barabasi claims that there is no analytic approximation of cluster coefficient for the BA-generated scale-free network, but suggests that it follows a power law for networks with \lambda = 4: CC(scale-free) \sim n^{3/4}. 
</text>

<text>
For large Barabasi-Albert scale-free networks, the locally tree-like of the network makes its clustering coefficient approach zero in the limit <cite>Dorogotsev 2010</cite>:
</text>

<equation>
CC \approx (\Delta m - 1) \frac { \ln^2 n } { n }
</equation>

<text>
Note that a Barabasi-Albert scale-free network is actually a tree when <eqn>\Delta m = 1</eqn>, hence its clustering coefficient is 0 in that case.
</text>

<text>
L: The cluster coefficient of a scale-free network generally varies inversely with n, and linearly with increase in density: 

CC(scale-free) \sim density... 

...by simulation and curve fitting that cluster coefficient of scale-free networks is much like that of a random network.
</text>

<text>
L: Curve fitting determines that cluster coefficient slowly increases as a linear function of density in a scale-free network, but the increase is nonlinear and rapid in an equivalent small-world network (clustering rises quickly with slight increase in density)...

L: As density increases, a small-world network transitions into a highly clustered network while a scale-free network transitions into a high-degree
hub network. This is a direct consequence of the high cluster coefficient of the underlying k-regular network.

L: In short, scale-free networks have large hubs and small clustering. Small-world networks have large clusters and small hubs.
</text>

<text>
Because the density of a scale-free network is approximately \rho \approx 2(\Delta m/n), the clustering coefficient also increases with \Delta m:
CC(scale-free) \sim \Delta m. 


L: Local clustering around scale-free network nodes is indeed correlated with node
degree, but in a negative manner... The cluster coefficient of individual nodes is inversely proportional to the degree of individual nodes in a sparse scale-free network; hubs have low cluster coefficients, while non-hubs have high cluster coefficients. 
++ The nodes with highest connectivity appear to be the nodes with the smallest number of connected neighboring nodes.
++ There is a correlation between local cluster coefficient and node degree in scale-free networks that does not exist in random and small-world networks, e.g. CC(random) \sim (\lambda/n) = density, for random networks (Albert, 2002).


L: As density increases, the degree of hub of a scale-free network also increases. High-degreed hubs tend to lower the cluster coefficient because density increases linearly while cluster coefficient must increase as a quadratic: Degree(degree - 1)/2.


</text>

<text>
Empirical approximation <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>: 
In scale-free networks, cluster coefficient is bounded by \Delta m /(d -\Delta m) for low values of \Delta m (\Delta m &lt;&lt; n). 
</text>

<text>
Theoretical
</text>

<equation>
CC = \frac {\langle d \rangle} {n} \left( \frac {\langle d^2 \rangle - \langle d \rangle^2} {\langle d \rangle^2} \right)^2
</equation>

<text>
The second term depends on the variance of the degree distribution
</text>

<text>
When <eqn>p(k) \sim k^{-\gamma}</eqn> for <eqn>\gamma &lt; 7/3</eqn>, the clustering coefficient increases with network size:
</text>

<equation>
CC(SF) \approx n ^{- \frac{3\gamma - 7}{\gamma - 1}}
</equation>

[M. E. J. Newman, SIAM Review 45, 167 (2003)]

</document>






</document>



<document>
<tag>scale-free-examples</tag>
<title>Scale-free networks in the real world</title>


<text>
Measuring the exponent:
+ Use cumulative degree distributions to smooth fluctuations in the region of large degrees (i.e. note the inverse definition of the traditional cumulative probabilities)
</text>

<equation>
P_{cumulative}(d) = \sum_{d' \geq d} P(d')
</equation>

<text>
When <eqn>P(d) \sim d^{-\gamma}</eqn>, then <eqn>P_{cumulative} \sim d^{1-\gamma)</eqn>. Binning/partitioning could also be used...
</text>

<text>
<cite>Clauset et al. 2009</cite> examine how power laws are best detected in practice: regression analysis of linear relationships in log-log scale (the standard method) results in many false positives (e.g. networks that might be better approximated by exponential or log-normal distributions). Sampling might also introduce false negatives <cite>Stumpf et al. 2005</cite>.
</text> 

<text>
Many real-world networks have been shown to obey a power-law degree distribution rather than a binomial or Poisson distribution. 
</text>

Expectations:
- Connectedness: \gamma \leq 2, \lambda \geq \ln n
- Giant connected component \gamma \leq 3.47, \lambda \geq 1
[W. Aiello, F. Chung, L. Lu, Proc. 32th ACM Theor. Comp., 171 (2000)]
[M. E. J. Newman, S. H. Strogatz, D. J. Watts, Phys. Rev. E 64, 026118 (2001)]

There is no universal exponent characterizing all networks.
2. The origins of the preferential attachment might be systemdependent.
3. It is generally true that networks evolve.
4. Modeling real networks:
	- identify the processes that play a role
	- measure their frequency from real data
	- develop dynamical models that capture these processes


<text>
Barabasi (Barabasi, 2001, 2002a, 2002b) and others <cite>Newman 2003</cite> (Adamic, 2000) have extensively studied networks with fat-tail distributions and found many applications of their theories in physical and biological sciences.
[Barabasi, A.-L., E. Ravasz, and T. Vicsek, Deterministic scale-free networks, Physica A 299(3–4):559–564 (2001).]
[Barabasi, A.-L., Linked: The New Science of Networks, Perseus Publishing, Cambridge, MA, 2002.]
[Barabasi, A.-L., H. Jeong, Z. Neda, E. Ravasz, A. Schubert, and T. Vicsek, Evolution of the social network of scientific collaborations, Physica A 311(3–4):590–614 (2002).]
[Adamic, L. A. and B. A. Huberman, Power-law distribution of the World Wide Web, Science 287:2115 (2000).]




In their original paper on their model, Barabasi and Albert gave simulations showing the power-law distribution of degrees. 
[Barabasi, A.-L. and Albert, R., Emergence of scaling in random networks, Science 286, 509-512 (1999)]


N'2003: A number of authors have subsequently published more extensive simulation results.
 [Dorogovtsev, S. N. and Mendes, J. F. F., Evolution of networks with aging of sites, Phys. Rev. E 62, 1842-1845 (2000).]
 [Dorogovtsev, S. N. and Mendes, J. F. F., Scaling behaviour of developing and decaying networks, Europhys. Lett. 52, 33{39 (2000).]
 [Krapivsky, P. L. and Redner, S., Finiteness and fluctuations in growing networks, J. Phys. A 35, 9517{9534 (2002).]

N'2003: A crucial element of both the models of Price and of Barabasi and Albert is the assumption of linear preferential attachment. It is worth asking whether there is any empirical evidence in support of this assumption. Two studies indicate that it may be a reasonable approximation to the truth:
 - Jeong et al. looked at the time evolution of citation networks, the Internet, and actor and scientist collaboration networks, and measured the number of new edges a vertex acquires in a single year as a function of the number of previously existing edges. They found that the one quantity was roughly proportional  to the other and hence concluded that linear preferential attachment was at work in these networks. 
 [Jeong, H., Neda, Z., and Barabasi, A.-L., Measuring preferential attachment in evolving networks, Europhys. Lett. 61, 567{572 (2003).]
 - Newman performed a similar study for scientific collaboration networks, but with finer time resolution, measured by the publication of individual papers, and came to similar conclusions.
 [Newman, M. E. J., Clustering and preferential attachment in growing networks, Phys. Rev. E 64, 025102 (2001).]


EXAMPLES
distribution of number of papers published by scientists, distribution of cities by population, distribution of wealth, and
distribution of species among genera all obey a power law.
[Mitzenmacher, M., A brief history of generative models for power law and lognormal distributions, Internet Math. 1(2):226-251 (2004).] 

1999:
+ M. Faloutsos, P. Faloutsos, and C. Faloutsos observed a power law in their graph models of the Internet
+ Albert, Jeong, and Barabasi obtained similar results for the WWW
[R. Albert, H. Jeong, A.-L. Barabási, Nature 401, 130 (1999)]


Many critical infrastructure systems such as the Internet, railroads, and
gas/oil pipeline systems have been shown to be scale-free 
[Lewis, Ted G., Critical Infrastructure Protection in Homeland Security: Defending a Networked Nation, Wiley, 2006]

Scale-free networks appear to model economic constructs such as the Internet and
monopolies within industrial segments, because preferential attachment is essentially
the law of increasing returns of economics.

INTERNET, known to have hubs of extremely high degree, and exhibit the small-world effect
Scale-free nature of the Internet (Huberman, 1999; Kim, 2002; Kleinberg, 2000a, 2000b).
[Huberman, B. A. and L. A. Adamic, Growth dynamics of the worldwide web, Nature 401:131–132 (1999)]

WWW
[Adamic, L. A. and B. A. Huberman, Power-law distribution of the World Wide Web, Science 287:2115 (2000).
</text>

<text>
WWW

L: <cite>Broder et al. 2000</cite> analyzed over 200 million servers in the Internet’s Webgraph, and discovered its giant component, called the giant strongly connected component (GSCC). The Internet’s Webgraph is shaped like a “bowtie”—44 million nodes (21%) are predominantly incoming nodes that send messages such as email; another 44 million are predominantly outgoing nodes that receive messages. A larger cluster, 56 million (27%) make up the GSCC.
[A. Broder et al., Comput. Netw. 33, 309 (1999)]

L: In terms of small-world effect (short average path length), GSCC is a small-world
network. The average path length (out of 56 million nodes in the GSCC) reported by
Broder et al. is a mere 16–20 hops! According to WWW high-level measurements
made by Adamic, of which the GSCC is a component, the average path length is 35 hops.
[Adamic, L. A., The small world web, in Research and Advanced Technology for
Digital Libraries, Lecture Notes in Computer Science 1696, S. Abiteboul and
A.-M. Vercoustre, eds, Springer-Verlag, New York, 1999, 443–452.]

At the other extreme, Yook et al. estimates an average
path length equal to 9 hops when measured at the Internet’s router level 
[Yook, S. H., H. Jeong, A.-L. Barabasi, and Y. Tu, Phys. Rev. Lett. 86:5835 (2001).]

L: GSCC path length is a consequence of hub topology (scale-free), not random rewiring (small-world). 

While clustering is modest in the domain-level Webgraph, Internet clustering is higher than expected of a purely random network. Yook et al. place the cluster coefficient of the domain level Internet in the range 0.18–0.30, versus 0.001 for an equivalent random network (Albert, 2002).

WWW: 
- nodes: web pages
- edges: hyperlinks - directed connections (references in web documents)
++ up to 60% reciprocal connections (two web pages can cite each other, something more uncommon in scientific papers)
[
Jean-Pierre Eckmann and Elisha Moses:
Curvature of co-links uncovers hidden thematic layers in the World Wide Web
PNAS April 30, 2002 vol. 99 no. 9 5825-5829
doi: 10.1073/pnas.032093399
]

= the largest network with topological information available.

@ 1 trillion unique URLs indexed by Google on July 25th, 2008, just on the Surface Web (access to the Deep Web is restricted)
i.e. unknown true size

[S. Lawrence, C. L. Giles, Nature 400, 107 (1999).]
Structure of a website [M. E. J. Newman and M. Girvan, Phys. Rev. E (2004]

L: The structure of the Internet and WWW: an emergent property of the decentralized Internet - that it had emerged without central planning into a structure consisting of a small number of extremely popular sites called hubs, and a large number of "unpopular" sites with few links (a scale-free network).


Origin: Tim Berners-Lee proposal of an hypertext system for CERN (European Laboratory for Particle Physics, Geneve, Switzerland)

In 1999, the average number of incoming and outcoming links per web page was about eight, an extremely sparse network...

1999 Kleinberg, Kumar, Raghavan, Rajagopalan, Tomkins: Formalized model of WWW as "Webgraph"
+ We call such networks Webgraphs, because they use graph theory to understand the World Wide Web (WWW).
(Kleinberg et al. 1999)
[Kleinberg, J. M., S. R. Kumar, P. Raghavan, S. Rajagopalan, and A. S. Tomkins, The Web as a
graph: Measurements, models, and methods, in T. Asano, H. Imai, D. Lee, S. Nakano, and
T. Tokuyama, eds, Proc. 5th Annual Intnatl. Conf. Computing and Combinatorics, Tokyo,
Lecture Notes in Computer Science, Vol. 1627, Springer-Verlag, Berlin, 1999.]



1999 Albert, Jeong, Barabasi: Diameter of the WWW (at least, within a small part of the Web, the nd.edu domain from the University of Notre Dame)
nd.edu with 325729 pages and 1469680 links
+ average path length estimated to be 0.35 + 0.89 ln n
+ clustering coefficient: 0.3 (ignoring the directedness of links)
[Albert, R., H. Jeong, and A.-L. Barabasi, Diameter of the World Wide Web, Nature 401:130-131 (1999).]
+ taking into account the directedness of links: very few short loops as compared to random models
[
Ginestra Bianconi, Natali Gulbahce, and Adilson E. Motter:
Local Structure of Directed Networks
Phys. Rev. Lett. 100, 118701 (2008).
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.100.118701
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevLett.100.118701
]


2000 Broder, Kumar, Maghoul, Raghavan, Rajagopalan Stata, Tomkins, Wiener: Full Webgraph map of the WWW
+ Group of computer scientists from AltaVista, IBM, and Compaq (now part of HP)
+ the first to fully map the WWW as a Webgraph and discover its structure
	- Giant weakly-connected component composed of a giant strongly-connected component (30%), a giant out-component, and a giant in-component, plus tendrils (25%)
+ Average directed path length around 16 for the 200M pages indexed by AltaVista at the time, i.e. a small world
+ Maximum separation (diameter): about 1000 !, not so small
+ Average in- and out-degree: 7.22 in May 1999, 7.85 in October 1999
+ Power law distribution with exponent 2.1 for in-degrees and 2.7 for out-degrees (range much narrower for out-degrees, obviously)
	- Doubts about the scale-free structure w.r.t. out-degrees
	- Scale-free network w.r.t. the in-degree distribution
[Broder, A., S. R. Kumar, F. Maghoul, P. Raghavan, S. Rajagopalan, R. Stata, A. Tomkins, and
J. Wiener, Graph structure in the web, Comput. Networks 33(1-6):309-320, (2000).]
[
D. Donato, L. Laura, S. Leonardi, S. Millozzi. 
Large Scale properties of the Webgraph.
European Physical Journal B, Vol. 38 (March 2004), pp. 239-243, 
doi:10.1140/epjb/e2004-00056-6
]

2000: Power law observed in the WWW
[Adamic, L. A. and B. A. Huberman, Power-law distribution of the World Wide Web, Science 287:2115 (2000).]

1999 Adamic: Distance between .edu sites shown to be small-world
[Adamic, L. A., The small world web, in Research and Advanced Technology for
Digital Libraries, Lecture Notes in Computer Science 1696, S. Abiteboul and
A.-M. Vercoustre, eds, Springer-Verlag, New York, 1999, 443-452.]


2002 Levene, Fenner, Loizou, Wheeldon: Enhanced Webgraph model concluded structure of the WWW couldn't be explained by preferential
attachment alone
[Levene, M., T. Fenner, G. Loizou, and R. Wheeldon, A stochastic model for the evolution of
the web, Comput. Networks 39:277-287 (2002).]
</text>

<text>
INTERNET

1999 Faloutsos brothers: Power law observed in Internet at the AS level
- for a small fraction of the Internet
[
Faloutsos, M., P. Faloutsos, and C. Faloutsos, 
On power-law relationships of the Internet topology, 
Proc. ACM SIGCOMM '99 Conf. Applications, Technologies, Architectures, and Protocols for Computer Communication 
in Cambridge, MA, USA, ACM Press, New York, 1999, pp. 251-262.
]
+ for a larger AS network (11000 ASs with 4.2 connections on average,October/November 1999) 
+ IR map (230000 Internet routers with 2.8 average degree, May 2001)
[
Romualdo Pastor-Satorras, Alexei Vázquez, and Alessandro Vespignani:
Dynamical and Correlation Properties of the Internet
Phys. Rev. Lett. 87, 258701 (2001)
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.87.258701
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevLett.87.258701
]
[
Alexei Vázquez, Romualdo Pastor-Satorras, and Alessandro Vespignani:
Large-scale topological and dynamical properties of the Internet
Phys. Rev. E 65, 066130 (2002)
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevE.65.066130
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevE.65.066130
]
- Both of these studies concluded that degree distributions followed an imperfect power law with exponent \gamma = 2.1
- Caveat: Incomplete maps obtained by sending packet probes from just a few sources
(i.e. nodes with a small degree might not be mapped, resulting in more skewed distributions)
[
Aaron Clauset and Cristopher Moore
Accuracy and Scaling Phenomena in Internet Mapping
Phys. Rev. Lett. 94, 018701 (2005)
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.94.018701
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevLett.94.018701
]
[
T. Petermann and P. De Los Rios 
Exploration of scale-free networks: Do we measure the real exponents?
Eur. Phys. J. B 38, 201-204 (2004) 
DOI: 10.1140/epjb/e2004-00021-5
]

+ Small path lengths: 3-4 average path length @ AS, about 9 @ IR

+ High clustering: 0.3 @ AS, 0.03 @ IR
++ The clustering depends strongly on the node degree (CC decreases with degree increases)

+ Pastor-Satorras et al. also measured the average degree of the nearest neighbors of a node with k connections: d_{nn}(k)
++ d_nn independent of k in uncorrelated networks
++ d_nn dependent of k in the Internet (a correlation found in many real-world networks)

+ Evolution (denser networks?)
++ Theoretical suggestion: 
[
S.N. Dorogovtsev and J.F.F. Mendes:
Effect of the accelerated growth of communications networks on their structure, 
Phys. Rev. E 63, 025101 1-4 (2001) (R); cond-mat/0009065. 
]
++ Empirical confirmation <cite>Leskovek et al. 2007b</cite>: Networks become denser with time, as the number of links grows faster than the number of nodes. This growing average degree also increases clustering and reduces network diameter (networks grow exponentially, yet their diameter are kept constant or even decrease).

</text>

[R. Govindan, H. Tangmunarunkit, IEEE Infocom (2000)]
[A.-L. Barabási, R. Albert, Science 286, 509 (1999)]


<text>
L: the pure power law may not always model of reality. 

Laherrere and Sornette suggest that a stretched exponential distribution may be more precise in natural and economic systems (Laherrere, 1998):
[Laherrere, J. and D. Sornette, Stretched exponential distributions in nature and economy: “Fat tails with characteristic scales,” Eur. Phys. J. B 2:525–539 (1998).]
</text>

<equation>
exp_{stretched}(x) = c \left( \frac { x_{c-1} } { x_0^c } \right) e^{ - \left( \frac{x}{x_0} \right) ^ c }
</equation>

<text>
Typically, exponent c is less than one. When c = 1, the stretched exponential is simply the well-known exponential distribution. Laherrere and Sornette list a number of natural and economic systems that obey this law: distribution of the 1300 largest earthquakes, temperature variations over the past 420,000 years, radio and light emissions from galaxies, oilfield reserve sizes, US and French company sizes, United Nations country sizes, citation distribution of the most frequently cited physicists, and the distribution of biological extinction events.
</text>

</document>



<document>
<tag>scale-free-dynamics</tag>
<title>The dynamics of scale-free networks</title>

<text>
L: Albert, Jeong, and Barabasi observed that scale-free networks were extremely resilient
against random attacks, but extremely vulnerable to systematic attacks on hubs
(Albert, 2000). This makes sense—a random attack will most likely strike and destroy
a node with only a few links, because a scale-free network has many such nodes. On
the contrary, since hubs are rare, it is unlikely that a hub is attacked. But a hub has
many links, and so its demise damages a large percentage of the network. Let pc
be the fraction of damaged nodes that dismantles the network. When pc is high,
the network is resilient, because many nodes must be knocked out to dismantle the
network. When it is low, the network is vulnerable. In simulations, Albert et al.
found threshold values of pc = 28% for random networks versus nearly 99% for
scale-free networks under random attacks; that is, a random network dismantles
when an average of 28% of its nodes are damaged. But the tables are turned when
hubs are systematically attacked—only 18% of the nodes need to be attacked to dismantle
a scale-free network. Thus, a scale-freenetwork is more vulnerable than a
random network when its hubs are targeted.

2000 Albert, Jeong, Barabasi: Scale-free networks are resilient if hubs are protected (Internet's "Achilles heel")
[Albert, R., H. Jeong, and A. L. Barabasi, The Internet's Achilles' heel: Error and attack tolerance of complex networks, Nature 406:378-382 (2000).]
</text>

<text>
L: In related work, Pastor-Satorras and Vespignani observed that populations forming
a scale-free network have no minimum epidemic threshold that prevents an infectious
disease from recurring (Pastor-Satorras, 2001). Once an infection enters a network, it
rises and falls repeatedly. Persistent epidemics are real—they occur in human networks
as well as on the Internet.


2001 Pastor-Satorras, Vespignani: Claim no epidemic threshold in scale-free networks; Internet susceptible to SIS viruses
[Pastor-Satorras, R. and A. Vespignani, Epidemic spreading in scale-free networks, Phys. Rev. Lett. 86(14):3200-3203 (2001).]
</text>

<text>
L: Wang and coworkers showed the initial claim of Pastor-Satorrus to be generally
false (Wang, 2003a). Instead, persistence of an infection is determined not by the network's
degree distribution but by its spectral radius, which is defined as the largest nontrivial
eigenvalue of a network's connection matrix. Therefore, network topology
determines its susceptibility to epidemics, but not because it is scale-free. This profound
result has significant implications for fighting both kinds of viruses—Internet
and human. It also has implications for the product marketer.
</text>



<text>
NAVIGATION

L: ... messages should flow quickly from one node to another using hubs. In fact, navigating a scale-free network by hopping from hub to hub is a fast path through a scale-free network because average path length declines with density and hub degree. In particular, the relationship between hub degree and path length leads to fast navigation in scale-free networks when using the max-degree search algorithm, described next (Paxson, 1997; Adamic, 2001, 2002)...

[Paxson, V. and S. Floyd, Why we don’t know how to simulate the internet, Proc. 1997 Winter Simulation Conf., Atlanta, GA, ACM Press, New York, 1997, pp. 1037–1044]
[Adamic, L. A., R. M. Lukose, A. R., Puniyani, and B. A. Huberman, Search in power-law networks, Phys. Rev. E 64(4):046135 (2001).]
[Adamic, L. A., R. M. Lukose, and B. A. Huberman, Local Search in Unstructured Networks, Wiley-VCH, Verlag, Berlin, 2002.]

The max-degree navigation algorithm is simple. Starting at node u0, hop to the adjacent node u1 with the highest degree among all adjacent nodes. Then hop from u1 to u2, the node adjacent to u1, with the highest degree, and so on, until reaching the destination node. Of course, the algorithm must avoid cycling back to a previously visited node, and it must back up when encountering a deadend. In the worst-case scenario, a max-degree search traverses the entire network.
...
practical application in peer-to-peer network design.

[Kim, B. J., C. N. Yoon, S. K. Han, and H. Jeong, Path finding strategies in scale-free networks, Phys. Rev. E 65(2):027103, (2002).]
[Kleinberg, J. M., Navigation in a small world, Nature 406:845 (2000).]
[Kleinberg, J. M., The small-world phenomenon: An algorithm perspective, in STOC, Proc. 32nd Annual ACM Symp. Theory of Computing, Portland, OR, ACM Press, New York, 2000, pp. 163–170.]



L: ... the impact of density and hub degree on navigation speed and show that the higher the degree of a hub, the faster the navigation time...

- The average length of a path—using max-degree navigation—is O(1/density), and therefore the expected time to navigate through this network diminishes inversely with density. Compare this with the shortest-path-length average, which drops off far more slowly, since it is \sim density^{-1/3}

- we should expect navigation time to improve with increases in hub degree... Hub_degree increases logarithmically with density, so the relationship between expected navigation time and hub degree fits an exponential curve... Hub degree has a dramatic impact on navigation time

L: Scale-free networks are intrinsically more efficient to navigate than are random or small-world networks. They both have small-world effect and low clustering. In a sense, scale-free networks perform better than do small-world networks, leading to the conclusion that scalefree networks are “smaller than small worlds”!
++ greater number of long-haul links in a scale-free network compared to an equivalent small-world network. 
++ LIMIT: Star network

NOTE: Hubs are also the most powerful intermediary nodes—and because they capture more paths than do other nodes, they require greater bandwidth. Therefore, a max-betweenness search is equivalent to a max-degree search. But it is much easier to calculate the degree of a node than its betweenness value.
</text>

<text>
MORE...
</text>

<text>
1999 Dorogovtsev, Mendes, Samukhim, Krapivsky, Redner: Exact solution to scale-free network degree distribution
[Dorogovtsev, S. N., J. F. F. Mendes, and A. N. Samukhin, Structure of growing networks with preferential linking, Phys. Rev. Lett. 85(21):4633-4636 (2000).]
[Krapivsky, P. L., S. Redner, and F. A. Leyvraz, Connectivity of growing random networks, Phys. Rev. Lett. 85(21):4629-4632 (2000).]
</text>


<text>
<cite>Caldarelli 2007</cite>
<cite>Cohen and Havlin 2003</cite>
<cite>Barabasi and Bonabeau 2003</cite>
</text>


</document>


<document>
<tag>scale-free-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>

<text>
M. Faloutsos, P. Faloutsos and C. Faloutsos. On Power-Law Relatonships of the Internet Topology. ACM SIGCOMM 1999.
M. E. J. Newman, Power laws, Pareto distributions and Zipf's law, Contemporary Physics.
M. Mitzenmacher, A Brief History of Generative Models for Power Law and Lognormal Distributions, Internet Mathematics, 2004
B. Bollobas, Mathematical Results in Scale-Free random Graphs.
L. A. Adamic, R. M. Lukose, A. R. Puniyani, B. A. Huberman. Search in Power-Law Networks. Phys. Rev. E, 64 46135, 2001.
R. Albert. Scale-free networks in cell biology.
A.-L. Barabasi, Reka Albert, and Hawoong Jeong. Mean-field theory for scale-free random networks. Physica A 272 173-187 (1999).
B. Bollobas, C. Borgs, J. Chayes, and O. Riordan Directed scale-free graphs Proceedings of the 14th ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (2003), 132-139.
A. Fabrikant, E. Koutsoupias, C. Papadimitriou. Heuristically Optimized Trade-offs: A New Paradigm for Power Laws in the Internet. 29th International Colloquium on Automata, Languages, and Programming (ICALP), 2002.
Qian Chen, Hyunseok Chang. Ramesh Govindan, Sugih Jamin, Scott J. Shenker, Walter Willinger. The Origin of Power Laws in Internet Topologies Revisited. Proc. of IEEE Infocom 2002.
</text>

<text>
++
Models of weighted network formation...

e.g.
New links according to node strengths (sum of their weights) + weight increase (e.g. airport connections)

Title: Modeling the evolution of weighted networks 
A. Barrat, M. Barthélemy, A. Vespignani
Journal-ref: Phys. Rev. E 70 (2004) 066149. 
cond-mat/0406238 

Title: Weighted evolving networks: coupling topology and weights dynamics
A. Barrat, M. Barthélemy, A. Vespignani
Journal-ref: Phys. Rev. Lett. 92 (2004) 228701. 
cond-mat/0401057 

Title: Characterization and Modeling of weighted networks (pdf) 
Authors: M. Barthélemy, A. Barrat, R. Pastor-Satorras, A. Vespignani 
Ref: cond-mat/0408566; Physica A 346 (2005) 34

G. Bianconi, 
Emergence of weight-topology correlations in complex networks,
Europhys. Lett. 71, 1029 (2005).
http://www.iop.org/EJ/abstract/0295-5075/71/6/1029
(combination of Barrat et al.'s model with the BA preferential attachment model)

</text>

</document>

</document>
