<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography  SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>

<!-- Small worlds -->

<document>
&bibliography;
<tag>small-worlds</tag>
<title>Small-world networks</title>


<text>
L: The class of small-world networks lies between structured and random networks...
</text>

<text>
++ The small-world phenomenon: in a social network each pair of nodes is connected with a fairly short path.

In general, the term small-world effect refers to networks where the average path length grows slower than any positive power of the number of nodes in the network. Or, alternatively, to networks whose number of nodes grows faster than any power of its average path length.
In fact, the small-world effect is often observed as a rapid decline in average path length when a small number of random links are added to a  network, even when it is random. This result is not completely surprising, since a single link connects separate parts of a network and brings distant nodes closer.
</text>


<text>
<cite>Pool and Kochen 1978</cite> @ inaugual issue of the Social Networks journal (a draft widely circulated two decades before its publication): the world of social relationships is much smaller than expected given the size of the social network.

i.e. the earliest known theoretical analysis of small-world networks
</text>

<text>
<cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite> famous experiments...

+ White identified biases in Milgram's experiment and suggested modifications that lead to an average of seven intermediaries (White, 1970). 
[White, H. C., Search parameters for the small world problem, Soc. Forces 49:259-264 (1970).]

+ Hunter and Shotland modeled the experiment as a Markov process to determine average distances between groups (Hunter, 1974).
[Hunter, J. and R. L. Shotland, Treating data collected by the small world method as a Markov process, Social Forces 52:321-332 (1974).]

Two decades later (Kleinfeld, 2002).
[Kleinfeld, J., Six degrees of separation: Urban myth? Psychol. Today (2002)]
2002 Kleinfeld, Claims Milgram experiments not well founded: small-world social network is an "urban myth"

</text>



<document>
<tag>small-worlds-formation</tag>
<title>Models of small-world network formation</title>

<document>
<tag>formation-watts-strogatz</tag>
<title>Original Watts-Strogatz model (WS)</title>

<text>
++
<cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite> created a simple model that originates small worlds + discovered that these patterns are present in a broad range of networks. 

IDEA: Balance between the clustering property of a regular lattice and small-world properties of a random graph

Begin with a low-dimensional regular lattice (which includes lots of triangles and, unlike a random network, will allow for hig clustering coefficients). For that to happen, the lattice must include triangles in its unit cells. Even when they do not have them, the resulting network is still a small-world (the clustering coefficient is a secondary effect of the original Watts-Strogatz model).

Randomly rewire some of the links with a probability p, so that small-world features are included (i.e. long-range shortcuts that make the original lattice more compact)

For small p a mostly regular graph is produced
Small-world properties are obtained through the randomly wired links

L: The canonical form of the WS algorithm
starts with a 2-ring network (each node connected to 2 nodes on its right and 2 on its left). 

A small-world network emerges from the 2-ring
network by randomly rewiring pm links, where p is the rewiring probability. The
random rewiring injects a (limited) amount of randomness into the regular
network. As it turns out, a very small amount of randomness goes a long way.


Algorithm: initially construct a graph with regular structure. Next, apply rewiring to every link with probability p, such that p*m links are randomized (redirected to a randomly selected node). Parameter p is the rewiring probability, and m is the number of links in the original regular graph.

L: Rewiring probability p is similar to the link probability used to generate the Gilbert random network. However,
instead of determining whether to include a link in the network, rewiring probability p is used to determinewhether one end of a link is switched to a randomly selected node

L: The class of WS small-world networks can be generated with a small amount of
randomness (small p), or a large amount (large p), depending on the value of p.

L: increasing p also increases the randomness of the small world. This means we can produce a network with any desired level of randomness—entropy, if you will—by adjusting rewiring probability p—a low rewiring probability generates a nonrandom structure, and a high probability generates a random structure

L: Each link is visited and rewired (connected
to a randomly chosen head node), with probability p. In the end, this leaves
(1-p)m links as they were (part of the initial 2-ring network), and randomizes
the remaining pm links. The resulting small world is partly structured and partly
random—and so its degree distribution falls in between the spike of a
k-ring network, and the Poisson distribution of a random network.

</text>


<text>
Algorithm:

L: Watts and Strogatz devised the Watts-Strogatz small-world network generation procedure
in 1998; hence the name Watts-Strogatz or WS small-world network.
</text>

<text>
The WS generation procedure is simple—start with a 2-ring network and rewire
a percentage of its links to “randomize them.” The initial 2-ring network has a
and the resulting small-world network has some regular and some random structure. 
</text>



<text>
Rewiring consists
of replacing the head node of a link with a randomly selected different node. Each
link is visited and rewired with probability p; hence, a small-world network
evolves into a semistructured, semirandom network. On the average, pm links are
“random” and (1-p)m links are structured.
</text>

<text>
1. Given n, rewiring probability p, and k = 2, generate a k-ring network by
connecting each of n nodes to their immediate neighbors, and neighbor’s
neighbors. This network has m = 2n links [\lambda = 4, density = (4/n)].

2. For every link m, rewire it with probability p, as follows. If
(Math.random() &lt; p), disconnect the head(m), and rewire it to a different
randomly selected node. Avoid (v_random = head(m)), and duplicate links.
</text>

<text>
L: This generation procedure is simple, but does not guarantee a connected network.
If all links connecting a node to the network are rewired, it is possible for that node to
become isolated. Therefore, a number of enhancements (proposed by a variety of
researchers) can be applied to the basic algorithm to remove this deficiency.For
example, we can modify the WS procedure to avoid rewiring when it would
remove the final link from a node. This is similar to the anchored random network
modification applied to the Erdos-Renyi procedure described in the previous
chapter.
</text>

</document>





<document>
<tag>formation-watts-strogatz</tag>
<title>Generalized Watts-Strogatz model (k-WS)</title>


<text>
L: The density of a small world can be adjusted by modifying the initialization procedure
of WS. Instead of starting with a 2-ring network, we can start with a k-ring
network, where k = m/n. 
</text>

<text>
L: The WS generative procedure assumes an initial 2-ring
network, but we generalize the procedure to allow density to vary, which is achieved
by setting k = (n/m), and starting with a k-ring network (\lambda = 2k).
</text>



<text>
1. Given n, rewiring probability p, and k =m/n, generate a k-ring network by
connecting each of n nodes to their immediate neighbors, and neighbor’s
neighbors. This network has m = 2kn links [l = 2k, density = (2k/n)].

2. For every link m, rewire it with probability p, as follows. If
(Math.random() &lt; p), disconnect the head(m), and rewire it to a different
randomly selected node. Avoid (v_random = head(m)), and duplicate links.
</text>


<text>
Alternative method:

L: round-robin algorithm for inserting links into the k-ring starting network. The value of k depends on the number of nodes and links specified by the user. This requires insertion of k = m/n rings to generate the initial k-ring network.
</text>

<text>
L: The k-WS model is used to study changes in smallworld properties as a function of rewiring probability p and density d.
</text>

<text>
L: ... the reader should be aware of the biases introduced into the small-world effect by the WS generative procedure. In particular, it is not necessary to use a k-regular lattice as the starting point of a small world. Any sparse and regular network will do. However, properties such as... 
will be affected...
</text>

</document>



<document>
<tag>formation-nsws</tag>
<title>Newman and Watts model (NW)</title>

<text>
L: Newman et al. modified the procedure to avoid isolated nodes and components,
which led to the NSWS model (Newman, 2000a, 2000b). The Newman et al. generation
procedure is similar to the Gilbert random network generation procedure
because it uses a similar "anchoring" algorithm to avoid the separation of the network
into components. 
</text>

<text>
Differences to Watts-Strogatz model
- Added shortcuts
- No links removed from the underlying lattice
- No disconnected parts of the graph
- Easier to analyze as no distance is infinite
</text>

<text>
ref.
[Newman, M. E. J., Models of the small world: A review, J. Stat. Phys. 101:819-841 (2000).]
[Newman, M. E. J., Small worlds, the structure of social networks, J. Stat. Phys. 101(3/4)(2000).]
</text>

</document>


</document>


<!-- Properties -->

<document>
<tag>small-worlds-properties</tag>
<title>Structural properties of small-world networks</title>

<text>
Watts-Strogatz networks are hybrids — part k-rings and part random. Therefore, the topology of a small-world network should fall somewhere between that of a k-ring network and random network.
</text>

<text>
Link rewiring... 

L: The dramatic impact that a relatively small amount of
randomness has on path length, clustering, and entropy is the most impressive
attribute of a small-world network... that introduction of a small
amount of randomness or entropy into a structured network leads to a significant
change in the properties of a structured network (


L:  has a dramatic impact on several properties
of interest: degree distribution, diameter, radius, and average path length.
For small rewiring probability p, most of the network remains structured. Because
the k-ring network has a high cluster coefficient, the resulting small-world
network also has a high cluster coefficient. But even a small amount of rewiring
radically decreases network diameter, radius, and average path length, while
retaining most of the clustering inherent in the k-ring network. The
dramatic decrease in diameter, radius, and average path length is known as the
small-world effect.
</text>

<text>
L: Small-world networks are indeed structured networks with the addition of a small
amount of randomness. Some properties of the small-world network are inherited
from the structured network underlying the small world, and others are a consequence
of rewiring. Small worlds owe their average path length to the introduction of randomness,
but other properties, such as cluster coefficient, are due to starting
network topology.
</text>

<text>
WS small-world networks are sparse, yet they exhibit short average path lengths. They also have high clustering coefficients and their degree distribution is similar to that of random networks.

L: Generally, a slightly smallworld
network has a high cluster coefficient and lower average path length than
does its underlying regular network.

L: A small-world graph, G(small world), is a graph with relatively small average path
length, and a relatively high cluster coefficient, CC(G). Generally, the average path
length of a small world grows proportional to O(log(n)/log(lambda)), where where lambda is the mean node degree,
and the clustering coefficient tends to be greater than 50%.

</text>


<text>
L: Watts and Strogatz: small worlds as networks with relatively short distances (hops) between node pairs chosen at random, even as the size of the network grows. Specifically, the diameter of a network increases as ln(n) while its size increases by O(n), where n is number of nodes.
</text>

ref.
Newman, M. E. J., C. Moore, and D. J. Watts, Mean-field solution of the small-world network model, Phys. Rev. Lett. 84(14):3201-3204 (2000).
Barrat, A., Comment on Small-world networks: Evidence for a crossover picture, preprint 9903323 available from http://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/ (1999).
Barrat, A. and M. Weigt, On the properties of small-world network models, Eur. Phys. J. B 13:547 (2000); available as Condensed Matter/9903411.


<!-- Degree distribution -->

<document>
<tag>small-worlds-properties-degree</tag>
<title>Degree distribution</title>

<text>
L: A small-world network ... is a slightly structured and partially random network that is closer to the structured end of the spectrum than to the class of random networks that have no discernable structure or topology.

... [expect something between k-ring networks and random networks] ... In this case, intuition is correct, as the degree distribution
of a small-world network is taller and thinner than the distribution of an equivalent random network.

L: The degree distribution of a WS-generated small world is taller and thinner than an equivalent random network
</text>

<text>
L: The degree of all nodes of the initial k-ring network is 2k. Therefore,
the degree distribution is a spike at d = 2k, but this spike begins to
flatten out and spread wider as links are rewired.
</text>

<text>
L:... (1-p)m links as they were (part of the initial 2-ring network), and randomizes
the remaining pm links. The resulting small world is partly structured and partly
random—and so its degree distribution falls in between the spike of a
k-ring network, and the Poisson distribution of a random network.
</text>


<text>
L: Barrat and Weigt (Barrat, 2000) derived a closed-form expression for degree distribution of small worlds by observing the following:
</text>

<list>

<item>
The degree of a typical node u stays the same if none of its links are rewired, and increases if other node's links are redirected to u.
</item>

<item>
The probability that links are not rewired follows a binomial distribution, B(k,i,(1-p)), where k = m/n, i = number of links not rewired, and p = rewiring probability.
</item>

<item>
The probability that another node's links are redirected to node u follows a Poisson distribution, P(\lambda_1, d - k - i); d \geq k, where \lambda_1 = pk is the expected value of redirected links, d = degree, and i = number of links redirected to u
</item>

<item>
The probability of increasing the degree of node u is equal to the joint probability, B(k,i,(1-p))P(\lambda,d-k-i).
</item>

<item>
The degree distribution h(d) is equal to the sum of joint probabilities over i = 1, 2, 3, . . . min{d-k,k} links.
</item>

</list>


<text>
The distribution of nodes with d links after rewiring is the sum:
</text>

<equation>
h(d) = \sum_{i=1}^{min\{d-k,k\}} B(k,i,1-p) P(\lambda_1,d-k-i)
</equation>

<text>
where
</text>

<equation>
\lambda_1 = pk
</equation>

<equation>
B(k,i,1-p) = {k \choose i} (1-p)^i p^{k-i}
</equation>

<equation>
P(\lambda_1,d-k-i) = (pk)^{d-k-i} e^{ \frac{-pk}{(d-k-i)!} }
</equation>

<text>
The above expression is valid for <eqn>d \geq k</eqn> but it is undefined for <eqn>d &lt; k</eqn> and all the values of <eqn>i</eqn> outside the interval <eqn>[k, min\{d-k, k\}]</eqn>, where we assume it to be zero.
</text>

<text>
Generally, the Barrat-Weigt equation provides vales that are slightly lower than those observed in actual small-world networks.
</text>


<!-- Entropy -->


<document>
<tag>small-worlds-properties-entropy</tag>
<title>Entropy</title>

<text>
L: Entropy of the class of small-world networks is scalable from nearly structured
(low entropy) to fully random networks (high entropy). Entropy can be
adjusted by the designer through selection of the WS rewiring probability
p or number of links (density).

</text>

<text>
Starting with a k-ring network k = m/n, with density 2k/(n-1),
</text>

<text>
Varying the rewiring probability from 0 to 100% (constant size and densities):
</text>

<text>
- Nearly one-half of the increase in entropy occurs between 1% and 10% (confirming that a little randomness goes a long way toward dramatically changing the properties of a small-world or random network).

- For sufficiently large rewiring probabilities, 
the experimentally derived semilog plot of entropy versus rewiring probability fits a straight line almost exactly: 
2-ring WS small-world entropy is proportional to log_2 (p)
L: This is intuitively satisfying because it says that the number of bits of entropy in a small world is directly proportional to
rewiring probability p: # bits of entropy \propto p

++ the number of bits of randomness rises from 0 (at p=0%) to approximately 2.9 (at p=100%)
vs. 6.64 bits of information in a random message with 100 symbols, occurring with equal probability 1/100
i.e. no more than half the bits of information in a sequence of random numbers
L: When p = 100%, a WS small-world network is identical, in terms of entropy, to
an equivalent random network with the same number of nodes and links. Unlike a random network, we can “tune” a small world to match the randomness that we want.
</text>

<text>
Varying the density (constant size and rewiring probability):
</text>

<text>
- Entropy rises very slowly with density according to the logarithmic function: H_{WS} \propto \log(density, i.e. H_{WS} \propto \log \left( \frac{kç}{n}  \right). 

- Once again, the number of bits of entropy grows linearly with density: # bits of entropy \propto density
L: ... agrees with intuition because it says that entropy in small-world networks increases to the same extent, regardless of the source of randomness (either rewiring or adding links).
</text>

</document>

</document>


<!-- Clustering coefficient -->

<document>
<tag>small-worlds-properties-clustering</tag>
<title>Clustering coefficient</title>

<text>
The small-world graph has the largest cluster coefficient even though its
degree distribution is very similar to that of a random graph....
The class of small-world graphs is characterized by an unexpectedly large cluster
coefficient when compared to the class of random graphs, but it also has some properties
in common with the class of random graphs. For example, small-world and
random graphs have similar degree distributions and diameters.

The cluster coefficient of a small world can be several orders of magnitude
larger that that of an equivalent random graph of the same size and with an equivalent
number of links.
</text>


<text>
The cluster coefficient of WS networks varies by changing density, rewiring probability, or both. 

First, suppose that we hold density constant while varying rewiring probability p. What happens to a 2-regular WS network when entropy is
increased? Surprisingly, the cluster coefficient decreases as entropy increases!

Alternatively, the cluster coefficient increases with network density because the number of links available to form triangular subgraphs also increases.
</text>

<text>
L: Intuition says that the small-world cluster coefficient should approximate the (high) cluster coefficient of the class of regular networks at one extreme and the (low) cluster coefficient of the class of random networks at the other extreme.
For low rewiring probability, a WS network is mostly regular, and for high probability p, the network is mostly random.

</text>

<text>
Initially, before any rewiring, the cluster coefficient of every node in a 2-ring WS network is the same. The cluster coefficient of the initial k-ring network, CC(WS_0), is equal to the ratio of number of triangles attached to each node, divided by one-third of the number of connected triples:
</text>

<equation>
CC(WS_0) = CC(k-ring) = 3 \frac {\#\text{triangles}} {\#\text{connected triples}} = 3 \frac {k(k-1)} {2k(2k-1)} =  \frac{3}{2} \frac {k-1} {2k-1}
</equation>

<text>
L: For example, k = 2 in the initial network, CC(WS_0) = 1/2. As k increases, the highest possible cluster coefficient is 3/4 because
CC(WS_0) \sim 3k / 4k = 3/4. Therefore, the cluster coefficient of the initial regular WS network will fall in the interval [0.5,0.75].
</text>

<text>
L: When the small world emerges from rewiring, pm links will be rewired, which means that some links have been diverted from triangular subgraphs while
others remain as they were, initially. This causes clustering to decline with corresponding increases in rewiring probability p. When p=1.0, the WS small-world cluster coefficient equals that of a random network. Newman and Watts derived a complex equation for cluster coefficient using a
combinatorial approach (Albert, 2000???): 
</text>

[Albert, R., H. Jeong, and A. L. Barabasi, The Internet’s Achilles’ heel: Error and attack tolerance of complex networks, Nature 406:378-382 (2000).]
++ <cite>Albert and Barabasi 2002</cite>

<equation>
CC(WS_p) = \frac {3k(k-1)} {2k(2k-1) + 8pk^2 + 4p^2k^2}
</equation>



<text>
L: Barrat and Weigt made an elegant and simple assumption that gives a more accurate result: the cluster coefficient is
proportional to the probability that a triangular subgraph will not be rewired (Barrat, 2000):
</text>

[Barrat, A. and M. Weigt, On the properties of small-world network models, Eur. Phys. J. B
13:547 (2000); available as Condensed Matter/9903411.]

<equation>
CC(WS_p) = CC(k-ring) * (1-p)^3
</equation>

<text>
where, as above,
</text>

<equation>
CC(k-ring) = \frac{3}{2} \frac {k-1} {2k-1}
</equation>

<text>
L: When p=0, the initial cluster coefficient is that of the underlying regular network. When p&gt;0, rewiring simply destroys triangles with probability p, and leaves them intact with probability (1-p).  Failure to rewire one link occurs with probability (1-p). Failure to rewire all three links occurs with probability (1-p)^3. All three links have to survive rewiring; otherwise, the triangular subgraph is destroyed. Therefore, rewiring has to fail 3 times. The probability of three failures is (1-p)^3  == the triangular sub-graph remains intact with probability (1-p)^3.
</text>

<text>
Whereas the Newman-Watts  approximation overestimates cluster coefficient, the Barrat-Weigt approximation fits the data much better, but slightly
underestimates the actual clustering coefficient.
</text>

<text>
L: Clustering decreases as randomness increases because clustering is a form of structure (order), whereas rewiring links is a form of randomness (disorder). Increasing rewiring probability increases disorder, which decreases clustering.
</text>

<text>
++ Now let us hold rewiring probability constant and let density vary. Cluster coefficient slowly rises with increase in density because increasing density moves any network closer to a complete network. We know that the cluster coefficient of a complete network is 1.0, so the cluster coefficient must asymptotically approach 1.0 as density approaches 100%. Notice that the bounds on cluster coefficient are increased: 0.5 = CC(density) = 1.0, which seems to contradict to the Barrat-Weigt approximation. In this case k \rightarrow n/2, since (k=n density / 2), so there is no contradiction.
Therefore, the cluster coefficient slowly rises with rising density...
... more links means more triangular subgraphs to begin with, and relatively fewer rewired links for a fixed probability p. As density increases, so does the number of triangular subgraphs, which increases cluster coefficient. 
</text>


<text>
NOTE:  this clustering coefficient is more a property of the underlying regular network than an inherent property of all small worlds. For instance, clustering coefficients would be higher if we started with hypercube or toroidal networks ranteher than a simple k-ring.

Experiment <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>

Start with a 5x5 toroidal network, and apply the same rewiring microrule used in the WS generation procedure. What are the
properties of the resulting network?... The results suggest that initial configuration has some impact on entropy and average path length, but the cluster coefficient is much lower in networks generated by the WS microrule that starts with a toroidal network than with a 2-ring network. The standard WS network model starts and ends with high clustering. The toroidal WS network procedure starts and ends with less clustering.
i.e. the starting network matters = the WS network generation algorithm produces small worlds with the cluster coefficient determined by the topology of the 2-ring network. In general, the underlying k-ring network determines the cluster coefficient of the resulting small world!

L: The topology of a small-world network includes relatively high clustering, but this property is inherited from the initial k-regular network in
the WS generative procedure. If the small-world effect is desired in a network with low cluster coefficient, then start rewiring from a low-cluster regular network such as a grid or toroid. 

++ We conclude that small-world clustering is a consequence of two factors: the inherent clustering of the initial network and the manner of rewiring. The WS procedure preserves a certain amount of clustering because one end of each rewired link is anchored at a high-cluster-coefficient node. The Gilbert procedure does not preserve anchors; hence the inherent clustering of its initial complete network is lost.
</text>

</document>


<!-- Average path lentgh -->

<document>
<tag>small-worlds-properties-path-length</tag>
<title>Average path length</title>

<text>
... relatively low average path length... 

long-haul nature of random links... 
+ dramatic influence of shorcuts on the average path length
+ average path length declines at least as fast as a power law (the essence of the small-world effect)
</text>

<text>
Path length rapidly declines as the rewiring probability, and thus the randomness, increases...

With respect to the underlying lattice, the diameter of the small-world is expected to be np/\ln(np) times smaller than the lattice <cite>Dorogotsev 2010</cite>.
</text>

<text>
L: Does a small world become even smaller as more links are “randomized”? 

Actually, the average path length of a WS small-world network decreases exponentially as entropy increases, but it never shrinks below that of an equivalent random network... a small world does indeed become smaller as more links are randomized

As rewiring increases, a small world becomes more randomized and its average path length
approaches that of a random network. But the average path length of a small-world
network is no less than that of an equivalent random network.
</text>


<text>
L: Newman, Moore, and Watts (Newman, 1999a) derived an estimate for describing the average path length of a  small-world based on the following reasoning:
</text>

<list>

<item>
When rewiring is nonexistent, and the initial network is a 2-ring, average path length is n/4k.
</item>

<item>
For very small rewiring probability p, average path length begins a rapid decline, after <eqn>p \geq 1/m</eqn>.
</item>

<item>
At some (early) point <eqn>p^*</eqn>, rewiring is sufficiently large that the network transitions from mostly regular, to mostly random. This is known as the crossover point <eqn>p^*</eqn>, and indicates a phase transition in the network.
</item>

</list>

<text>
Newman, Moore, and Watts (Newman, 1999b; Newman, 2000a) argued that average path length declines from an initial (p=0) value of n/4k according to a scaling function f(r), where r is 2 times the average number of rewired links, r = 2pm, which act as shortcuts:
</text>

<equation>
f(r) = \frac{4}{\beta} tanh^{-1} \left( \frac{r}{\beta} \right)
</equation>

<text>
where <eqn>tanh^{-1}</eqn> is the inverse hypertangent function <eqn>arc tanh</eqn> and
</text>

<equation>
\beta = \sqrt{r^2+4r}
</equation>

<text>
Therefore, the average path length of a 2-ring WS small world is approximated by the Newman-Moore-Watts equation:
</text>

<equation>
L(WS) = n \frac{f(r)}{2k} = \frac{2 n}{\beta k} tanh^{-1} \left( \frac{r}{\beta} \right)
</equation>

<text>
with <eqn>r = 2pm</eqn> and <eqn>\beta = \sqrt{r^2+4r}</eqn>.
</text>

<text>
L: The Newman-Moore-Watts equation is proportional to 1/p for large, sparse networks. 

L: The Newman-Moore-Watts expression overestimates average path length, especially as rewiring probability p decreases. However, its underlying assumptions that path length shrinks as rewiring increases suggests an intuitive approach for an alternative appromxation <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>. 
</text>

<text>
L: Average path length is n/4k initially, but as links are rewired, they introduce shortcut
links that divide the network into smaller and smaller subgraphs. Specifically, one
random link cuts the network in half, on average, and two links cut it into one-fourth,
and so on. However, shortcuts overlap, and  addition of rewired links cuts the network into a fraction of 1/2.
The effect on the logarithm of average path length is a logarithmic function of rewired links.
Let r = pm = pkn shortcut links reduce logarithmic growth in path length by
\log_2 (pm), on average, because of the partial bisecting that occurs. Therefore,
the logarithm of the average path length is equal to the logarithm of the path
length of the initial 2-ring network, minus the effects of partial bisection:
</text>

<equation>
\log_2 L(r) =  \log_2 \left( \frac{n}{4k} \right) - q \log (r)
</equation>

<text>
where <eqn>q</eqn> is constant. This expression fits a straight line on a log-log plot, where the exponent <eqn>q</eqn> can be approximated by curve fitting. For 2-ring WS networks, <eqn>q_2 \approx 1/3</eqn>, whereas for 4-ring WS networks, <eqn>q_4 \approx 1/6</eqn>. We might conjectture that doubling k halves q...
</text>

<text>
Rearranging the terms in the expression above, we get an approximation for the average path length of WS networks that is simpler than the Newman-Moore-Watts equation and valid for small values of p:
</text>

<equation>
L(WS) = \frac { n } { 4 k r^q}
</equation>

<text>
where <eqn>r = pm = pkn</eqn> and <eqn>q></eqn> is a constant obtained by curve fitting.
</text>

<text>
When <eqn>k=2</eqn>, average path length is inversely proportional to the cube root of the rewiring probability <eqn>p</eqn>, i.e.
</text>

<equation>
L(WS_2) = \frac { n } { 4 k  \sqrt[3]{q}} = \frac { n } { 4 k  \sqrt[3]{pm}} \propto \frac{1}{ \sqrt[3]{p} }
</equation>

<text>
This power law tends to underestimate, while the Newman-Moore-Watts equation tends to overestimate path length.
</text>



<text>
L: WS networks exhibit the small-world effect because of the abrupt
decline in average path length while maintaining the cluster coefficient of
the underlying regular network. 

vs. random networks of equal density

L: An equivalent random network is really an asymptotic extreme of a small-world network with an
average path length less than or equal to an equivalent small world. Small-world
path length shrinks with increasing probability of link rewiring, reaching p =
100% as a limit. At low rewiring probability values, the WS small-world network
path length is similar to that of a 2-ring network (higher than that of a random
network). At high rewiring probability values, the path length of the class of WS
small-worlds and the class of random networks are similar (low).

NOTE: cluster coefficient and path length move in opposite directions, as density increases. when the density of a k-regular WS network approaches
100%...  Cluster coefficient slowly rises to 100%, and path length rapidly drops to 1. (Cluster coefficient for small values of p is determined by the underlying k-regular network, not by the small-world effect)
</text>



</document>



<document>
<tag>small-worlds-properties-betweenness</tag>
<title>Betweenness</title>

<text>
L: ...the average betweenness of a small-world network rises, falls, and then rises again, according to density d, size n, mean degree \lambda, and rewiring probability p:
</text>

<equation>
betweenness(WS) \propto \rho \lambda^r
</equation>

<text>
where 
</text>

<equation>
r \propto \frac { \lambda log (n - (1 - p)) } { \log(\lambda) }
</equation>

<text>
L: betweenness in a small-world, unlike a random, network is correlated
with both density and the underlying regularity of the initial k-ring
network.

++ Contrary to intuition, betweenness of a node does not improve the
ability of a message to rapidly find its way through a small-world network.
</text>

<text>
++ L (p.154-156):

Intuitively, average betweenness of nodes in a small world should follow the same
pattern as betweenness in a random network, especially as rewiring probability increases.
But this turns out to be false because of the WS small-world generative procedure,
which has a k-ring network as its underpinning. As density increases, small
worlds become more regular and asymptotically approach a complete network just
as does a random network. But the transition is not smooth... 

In fact, the transition dramatically follows a lazy-Z-shaped curve—completely
unexpected compared to the average betweenness of random and small-world
networks. The small-world network’s cluster coefficient undergoes a nonlinear
transformation at approximately 50% density.

betweenness increases with increasing density—up to a point—and then dips as the
network begins to act more like a k-ring network than a small-world network. After
the dip, regularity takes over, and betweenness once again rises until reaching a peak
near 100% density. A very rough approximation to this nonlinear behavior is obtained
by performing a mean-field analysis, as with random networks.

Here is the strategy:

1. Modify the mean-field approximation obtained in the previous
chapter, betweenness(random) = O((1 - density)z), to accommodate the impact
of regularity on the network, where z = lr, l = mean degree, and
r(random) = O( log (n)= log (l)):

a. Replace (1-density) with density because small worlds increase betweenness as
density increases—up to a point (50%),

b. Note that the transformation from small-world to k-ring network occurs
around r = 1.

c. Use the fact that a direct path of length 1 contributes zero betweenness because
of the way betweenness is defined.

2. Estimate curve-fit parameters C1 and C2

A small-world network of arbitrary density is generated by first constructing a
k-ring lattice. Then, a percentage
of links p are randomly rewired. This random rewiring injects shortcuts through the
network, which leads to a reduction in the number of nodes eligible to lie on a path
between any other pair of nodes. The effect of rewiring pm links is modeled as a
reduction in number of paths, as follows:

r = ( A log2 (n - (1 - p)\lambda) ) / log2 (\lambda)

The mean-field number of paths through a typical node is proportional to z, as before: z = \lambda^r.

When r &lt; 1, the small world ceases to behave like a small world, and becomes
more like a k-ring network, as far as betweenness is concerned. Therefore, we
require a different model for z when r , 1. In fact, the dense small world behaves
more like a k-ring network with k ¼ l=2 direct paths, instead. Therefore, only
k = \lambda / 2 paths run through a typical node: z = k = \lambda / 2

Combining these two effects, we obtain
z = \lambda^r if r &gt; 1 1
z = 2 otherwise

There is a major difference between the betweenness properties of random and small-world
networks. Random networks have no regularity until density approaches 100%. Hence
average betweenness is (mainly) a function of average path length and sparseness. On the
other hand, small-world networks have a great amount of regularity regardless of
density—and the impact of regularity on average betweenness increases as density
increases. A “tipping point” is reached around 50% density, which results in the small
world behaving more like a k-ring network than a random network. This regularity
becomes the most significant factor in determining betweenness. Generally, clustering
tends to increase average betweenness, while randomizing tends to decrease it, beyond
~20% density. 

L: The topology of a small-world network includes relatively high betweenness, but this property is inherited from the initial k-regular network in
the WS generative procedure. If a higher degree of betweenness is desired, start with a high-average-betweenness network such as a hypercube

</text>

</document>



</document>




<document>
<tag>small-worlds-examples</tag>
<title>Small-world networks in the real world</title>


<text>
... a small-world architecture that values economy of links and neighborhood clustering above all else...

Real-world graphs show clustering effects (Your friends are usually friends with each other as well) but random graph do not exhibit clustering properties
</text>

<text>
L: Very sparse networks with small diameter (small worlds) at diverse phenomena such as phase transitions in materials, functionality of biological organisms, and behavior of electrical power grids.
e.g. database of film actors, the electric power grid of the western United States, and the neural network of the nematode worm C. elegans (Caenorhabditis elegans)

Network C Crandom
movie actors 0.79 0.00027
neural network 0.28 0.05
power grid 0.08 0.0005

L: Sparse small-world networks appear to model human social networks, because humans have limited capacity to know a large number of other humans.

K: Jure Leskovec and Eric Horvitz [273]. They analyzed 30 billion conversations among 240 million active user accounts on Microsoft Instant Messenger (IM): a giant component containing almost all of the nodes, with an estimated average distance of 6.6 and an estimated median of 7 (over a random sample, due to the huge size of the graph)
@SNAP: Largest network we analyzed so far using the library was the Microsoft Instant Messenger network from 2006 with 240 million nodes and 1.3 billion edges. WWW 2008
[Planetary-Scale Views on a Large Instant-Messaging Network by J. Leskovec, E. Horvitz. International World Wide Web Conference (WWW), 2008. ]
extended version @
[Jure Leskovec and Eric Horvitz (June 2007). Planetary-Scale Views on an Instant-Messaging Network. arXiv:0803.0939.]
http://arxiv.org/abs/0803.0939

W: algorithm finds an average degree of separation of 3.43 between two random Twitter users, requiring an average of only 67 requests for information over the Internet to Twitter. A near-optimal solution of length 3.88 can be found by making an average of 13.3 requests.
[Reza Bakhshandeh, Mehdi Samadi, Zohreh Azimifar, Jonathan Schaeffer, "Degrees of Separation in Social Networks", Fourth Annual Symposium on Combinatorial Search, 2011] 
http://www.aaai.org/ocs/index.php/SOCS/SOCS11/paper/view/4031

W: Facebook's data team released two papers in November 2011 which document that amongst all facebook users at the time of research (721 million users with 69 billion friendship links) there is an average distance of 4.74. Probabilistic algorithms were applied on statistical metadata to verify the accuracy of the measurements.[23] It was also found that 99.91% of facebook users were interconnected, forming a large connected component.[24]
- Backstrom, Lars; Boldi, Paolo; Rosa, Marco; Ugander, Johan; Vigna, Sebastiano (2011-11-19). "Four Degrees of Separation". ArXiv. Retrieved 23 November 2011.
- Ugander, Johan; Karrer, Brian; Backstrom, Lars; Marlow, Cameron. "The Anatomy of the Facebook Social Graph". ArXiv. Retrieved 23 November 2011.


Common Examples of Small-World Networks <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>

Graph, n, Small-World Cluster Coefficient, Random Cluster Coefficient
World Wide Web            153,127 0.11 0.00023
Internet                    6,209 0.30 0.00100
Actors in same movie      225,226 0.79 0.00027
Coauthor scientific papers 52,909 0.43 0.00018
Western US power grid       4,941 0.08 0.00200
C. elegans neural network     282 0.28 0.05000
Foodweb (ecological chain)    134 0.22 0.06000

several order of magnitude larger clustering coefficients than equivalent random networks!!!

Albert and Barabasi summarize a number of real-world networks with high cluster
coefficients (Albert, 2002).  For example, the social network formed by movie actors
who appeared in the same movie has a cluster coefficient of 0.79; coauthorship
network of scholarly papers, CC = 0.72; the chemical reaction network of the
Escherichia coli organism, CC = 0.59; and network formed by linking synonyms
in an English language thesaurus, CC = 0.7. 
[Albert, R. and A.-L. Barabasi, Statistical mechanics of complex networks, Rev. Mod. Phys.
74:47-97 (2002).]

</text>

<text>
<cite>Uzzi et al. 2007</cite>
</text>

<text>
Dorogovtsev, Mendes, Samukhim, Krapivsky, and Redner derived
an exact formula for the power law of a purely scale-free network and showed that
it describes many biological systems (Dorogovtsev, 2000; 2002a; 2002b; 2003).
</text>

<text>
Networks are considered to be small worlds when they have a high clustering coefficient but exhibit a similar path length when compared to random networks with the same number of nodes and links.
</text>

<text>
Small-world-ness measure <cite>Humphries and Gurney 2008</cite>: The small-world index = ratio of the clustering coefficient to the path length after normalizing by the corresponding values for random networks.
</text>


<text>
A different class of small-world networks <cite>Sporns 2006</cite>: modular small-world networks (generated from isolated modules by gradually redistributing connections from within modules to between modules).
</text>


<text>
2001 Yung Taxonomy of applications of small-world theory to: SNA, collaboration, Internet, business, life sciences
[Yung, V. J. An exploration in the small world networks, available as Condensed Matter 0004214 (2000/2001)]
</text>

<text>
Several studies use small-world structures instead of regular lattices
in dynamical systems problems:
- Cellular automata: density classi?cation becomes easier
- In simple games: e.g. multi-player Prisoner’s dilemma is more di?cult
- In oscillators: Small-world topology helps oscillators to synchronize
- Solution for the ferromagnetic Ising model for d=1 with a phase transition in a ?nite temperature
- Small-world graph as a model of a neural network: able to produce fast responses to external stimuli and coherent oscillation.
- Model of species coevolution

e.g. spread of diseases
Small-world graphs are suitable for modeling spread of disease (or information) in a population 

First idea: use the approximate distribution of the average path length as a simple model.
- Disease spreads from neighborhoods of the infected people
- Number of people n infected after t time steps: those t steps away from the initial carrier.

More complex idea: Only a certain fraction q is susceptible What does the fraction q need to be to make disease an epidemic?

Transition from large-world to small-world implication: disease for information spreads first as a power of time, then changes to exponential increase and flattens off when the graph becomes saturated
</text>

</document>



<document>
<tag>small-worlds-dynamics</tag>
<title>The dynamics of small-world networks</title>


<text>
...Dynamical systems behave differently on small-world graphs than on regular lattice...
</text>

<text>
L: small-world networks share some properties of random networks—such as short
path length—some researchers have jumped to the conclusion they also behave
like random networks. Some of these claims have been verified experimentally.
Some are myths.
</text>


<text>
Strogatz claimed that the beating of a human's heart, the chirping of crickets, and
other biological systems naturally sync because they are small-worlds (Strogatz,
2003). But today we know that network synchronization has little to do with small-world
topology, and everything to do with the Laplacian of the connection matrix, and
the length of circuits within the network.

... pursued the idea that small-world network behavior explained synchrony ...

L: Strogatz suggested that the synchronized chirping of a certain species of
crickets is a consequence of the small-world effect (Strogatz, 2003).

ref. Atay networks (Atay, 2006), We examine stability of Atay networks,
which have applications in marketing, as well as understanding the chirping of crickets,
and show that sync is a property of emergent networks that contain triangleshaped
subgraphs. As it turns out, small-world networks have an abundance of
triangular subgraphs! Moreover, a network can be synchronized, by adding a triangular
subgraph to one of its nodes.
</text>



<document>
<tag>small-worlds-dynamics-phase-transition</tag>
<title>Phase transition</title>


<text>
The rapid change in network properties in WS small worlds, from predominantly structured networks, to partially structured, and then fully random networks... 
</text>

<text>
The phase transition idea is related to the sudden transition from a 2-regular to random network as rewiring probability
increases. Watts argued that phase transition is a particular property of small worlds...
</text>

<text>
L: At a certain rewiring probability called the crossover point (also length scale), the network transitions from mostly structured to mostly random network. 

++ the crossover point p*, also known as the phase transition threshold
[Barthelemy, M. and L. A. N. Amaral, Small-world networks: Evidence for a crossover picture, Phys. Rev. Lett. 82:3180 (1999).]
</text>


<text>
Estimate from <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>

Define p* as the point where the slope of the avg_path_length L versus p equals -45º. This corresponds with a rate of change <eqn>\delta L / \delta r = -1</eqn>:
</text>

<equation>
\frac{\delta L}{\delta r} = - \frac { n } { 4 k r^{q+1}} = -1
</equation>

<equation>
r = \left( \frac{n q}{4 k} \right) ^ {\frac {1} {q+1} }
</equation>

<text>
Since <eqn>r=pm</eqn>, then
</text>

<equation>
r = \frac {r} {m} = \left( \frac{n q}{4 k} \right) ^ {\frac {1} {q+1} }
</equation>

<text>
L: Barrat and Weigt claim that <eqn>p \sim (1/n)</eqn> (Barrat, 2000) for similar small worlds, which yields a much smaller estimate. Visually, the Barrat–Weigt approximation makes more sense. Rewiring 0.2% of the 1000 links means redirecting only 2 links, while rewiring 1% means redirecting
10 links. Two rewired links may cause upward of a four-fold drop in path length, which means that path length declines by as much as (125 - 125/4) / 125 = 75%.  i.e. "back of the envelope" estimate

++ 2-ring WS small-world networks transition from regular to random topology near a crossover
rewiring probability p* \sim 1/n. This marks the transition from "mostly
structured” to “mostly random” topology. 
</text>


<text>
Typically, the crossover point is very small... around just 1%
</text>


<text>
The value of p* is of interest to physicists, who associate it with phase transitions in materials.
L: Watts and Strogatz attached a meaning to the crossover, suggesting that it corresponds to phase transition in materials (the crossover point is also known as the phase transition threshold).
</text>

<text>
L: Typically, the small-world transitions from purely regular to slightly random for
p* = 1-4%. This phase transition threshold, or crossover point, has taken on a number of meanings in various applications. 
It has also been used to (try to) explain why small-world networks tend to synchronize more than do purely random or purely structured networks.
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>small-worlds-dynamics-search</tag>
<title>Search on networks</title>


<text>
K: ... the way people can explore chains of social contacts for information or
referrals to others. The surprising effectiveness with which people are able to accomplish
such tasks, confirmed by both experiments and everyday experience, suggests
characteristic patterns of structure at the network level that help facilitate these types
of activities.
</text>

<text>
MOTIVATION

L: Network navigation is a search process whereby a message finds its way from a source to a destination node using only local information such as node degree, radius, or betweenness. The lengths of such search paths are much greater than average path length; this is due to the trial-and-error wayfinding made necessary because of incomplete information about shortest paths. But network navigation is an important topic because it models a number of important processes in a variety of fields such as communication. In fact, network navigation in small worlds may explain how large communication systems work—or not—depending on search efficiency.
</text>

<text>
EXAMPLES

L: The Internet, and telecommunication systems in general, carry packets of information
that must find their way through a complex network, much as the letters
sent by Stanley Milgram had to find their way from sender to recipient. 

L: Network navigation has applications in peer-to-peer file sharing. For example,
several file-sharing applications found their way into the popular culture during the
late 1990s when music files were stored on consumer’s local disks, and navigation
software was used to find them. Without a global map of the peer-to-peer network,
a search program would have to perform a depth-first search (DFS) on adjacent
servers, and expand the search until locating the desired file.
</text>

<text>
Does the structure of a communication network make any difference to their efficiency?
DIAMETER 

L: In real-world natural or synthetic systems, small-world structure is usually a consequence
of microrules that favor high clustering, low path length, or both. For
example, a communication network’s efficiency is a function of the number of
hops separating any two nodes. In a neurological network, maximum transmission
time is kept to a minimum by making the diameter of the network low. 
</text>


<text>
++ 1999 Walsh: Difficulty of search in small worlds using local properties
[Walsh, T., Search in a small world, IJCAI'99, Proc. 16th Intnatl. Joint Conf. Artificial Intelligence, Stockholm, Sweden, Morgan Kaufmann Publishers, San Francisco, 1999, Vol. 2, pp. 1172-1177.]
</text>


<text>
How to find the best path through the network?
(without some kind of global routing table)

1. Random—the next node in the navigation path is selected at random.
2. Maximum-degree—the adjacent node with the highest degree is selected next.
3. Minimum-radius—the adjacent node that is more central is selected next.
4. Maximum-betweenness—the adjacent node that has the highest betweenness rating is selected next. 

For 2-ring WS small-world networks: From worst (most hops), to best (fewest hops) gives
1. Slowest: max-betweenness
2. Slow: random
3. Medium: min-radius
4. Fast: max_degree


L: <cite>Lewis 2009</cite> Navigation of a network using local properties of nodes is faster using a
maximum-degree selection algorithm than a minimum-radius, maximum-betweenness,
or random selection algorithm. 

++ The random node selection algorithm will serve as a baseline. As each node is visited along the navigation path, the next node to be searched is randomly selected from adjacent nodes. Intuitively, the resulting navigation path will be a random walk through the network.

++ the maximum-betweenness algorithm is worse than random!
</text>

<text>
Ordered DFS: 

L: 4) Intuitively, a high-degree node is more likely to be connected to the destination node. Therefore, the maximum-degree algorithm ranks the adjacent nodes according to their degree—from highest to lowest—and then selects the link leading to the highest-degree neighbor. If the search fails, the next-highest-degree node is tried, and so forth, until all adjacent nodes have been searched, or the destination node is found.

L: 3) Intuitively, a more central node is “closer” to the destination node. In this sense, “closer” means that nodes are ranked according to their radii. Adjacent nodes are ranked according to their radii, and traversed in order from lowest to highest. If a search backtracks, the second-larger-radius neighbor is selected and traversed, and so forth, as in the random and maximum-degree search.

L: 2)  Finally, a node that is between other nodes because of its betweenness should lie on a path leading to the destination node. Therefore, adjacent nodes are ranked according to their intermediary status and tried in order: highest betweenness value, first, followed by next betweenness value, and so on. until the destination node is reached, or deadends prevent a successful search.
</text>

<text>
L: WS small-world networks are shown to be more difficult to navigate
than random or scale-free networks. While small worlds tend to have relatively
short average path length, it is more difficult to find the shortest path through a
small world using local information such as node degree, betweenness, and node
radius than equivalent random networks.

== navigation performance among the three classes of networks follows the rank order
1. Slow: small world with small rewiring probability p
2. Medium: random network
3. Fast: scale-free network
(Note that scale-free networks can be navigated much faster than can either small-world or random networks.)
++ Small worlds are the most difficult to navigate with only local information, despite their their small diameter and short characteristic path length


Why? average path length of a network is based on the shortest path between all pairs of nodes. Navigation along the path between two nodes using local information about each node does not guarantee the shortest path, i.e. finds the first path, not the shortest path. 
</text>

<text>
++ Communication networks must consider the bandwidth or capacity limitations of nodes and links.
e.g. High-degree nodes are also highly burdened nodes, because they must handle the sum total of all bandwidth converging on them.
Thus, a max-degree navigation algorithm may actually be bogged down by the bottleneck of congestion brought about by high degree nodes
</text>


<text>
++ 2000 Kleinberg: Shows  O(n) search in small world using "Manhattan distance"

L: <cite>Kleinberg 2000</cite>, not only surprisingly short paths, but also the remarkable ability of individuals to identify links that lead to those short paths...

L: Kleinberg gives a formal explanation for Milgram's experiment based on
the "Manhattan distance" between source and target nodes. The "Manhattan distance"
is defined as the number of blocks, traversed along streets in Manhattan,
New York, between source and destination intersections. Kleinberg showed that it
takes only O(n) steps to navigate such a small world


Kleinberg model
+ On Watts-Strogatz model: No simple algorithm for ?nding the path using only local information
+ For Kleinberg’s model there is a simple algorithm for finding a short path using only local information for those structures for which the exponent of the power law is the dimension of the grid
Comments from the article:
- For other values of r than r = d path-finding becomes a hard task.
- There is more to the small-world effect than the existence of short paths

Let the edges be directed.
- Model the network as a two-dimensional n x n grid and use the Manhattan distance.
- Each element has an outgoing edge to each node within distance p \geq 1.
- Each element also has q randomly selected long-range outgoing edges.
- The length of these long-range edges will be decisive.

If we just select the long-range edges uniformly at random, there will be no small-world.

Look at the nodes at most \sqrt{n} away from target t: Probability of hitting one of them is 1/\sqrt{n}. It would take O(\sqrt{n}) to get there in average. The problem here is that the closer we are to t, the more probably the long-range edges will take us to totally elsewhere.

Say we are selecting the long-range edges of u. A node v will be selected with probability proportional to d(u, v)^{-r}.
+ This r will be the concentration exponent.

The model now has parameters p, q and r, but only r has any real effect on the model’s behaviour

Decentralized algorithms:
- An entity knows only what it has been told.
- It knows the location of the target, its own links and the grid structure of the lattice.

NETWORKS WITHOUT A SMALL-WORLD

For large r, the close neighbours of t will be proportionally quite far away from everything else. 
- The links should now be more tightly concentrated.
+ Therefore getting to the neighbourhood will easily take too long, because the long links are not long enough.
(too introvert)

For small r, there are also problems
- we need precision to hit the proportionally small neighbourhood.
- Small r makes the algorithms to easily overshoot.
- This means that the long links don’t give enough advantage
(too imprecise)

r=2 (navigable network)
+ the only exponent for which the long-range links are uniformly distributed over distance scales
(navigable = a greedy algorithm provides fast navigation)
i.e. Links of length 2^{j} to 2^{j+1} have the same probabilities for all j. Thus we have enough precision in every case.

At this unique point, r=D, the average delivery time is very slow (polylogarithmic, <eqn>\sim ln^2 L</eqn> for a D-dimensional lattice of LxLx...xL nodes), while the delivery time increases as a power of L for all other values of r <cite>Carmi et al. 2009</cite> <cite>Cartozo and De Los Rios 2009</cite>. 




In a large network, one has to manage local and global relations simultaneously.



</text>



<text>
MORE
</text>

<text>
2000 Marchiori, Latora: Harmonic distance replaces path length: works for disconnected networks
[Marchiori, M. and V. Latora, Harmony in the small-world, Physica A 285(3-4):539-546 (2000).]
</text>

</document>


</document>



<document>
<tag>small-worlds-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>

<text>
+ Yung Ph.D. thesis, 2001

Kasturirangan, R.
Multiple scales in small-world graphs.
Massachusetts Institute of Technology AI Lab Memo 1663.
1999. Also cond-mat/9904055

Newman, M.E.J.
The Structure and Function of Complex Networks,
SIAM Reviews, 45(2): 167-256, 2003. Also
cond-mat/0303516

Watts, D.J. and Strogatz, S.H.
Collective dynamics of "small-world" networks.
Nature, 393, 440–442. 1998.


V. Nguyen and C. Martel. Analyzing and characterizing small-world graphs. 2005 ACM-SIAM symposium on Discrete Algorithms.

D.J. Watts. Networks, Dynamics and Small-World Phenomenon, American Journal of Sociology, Vol. 105, Number 2, 493-527, 1999

J. Leskovec, J. Kleinberg, C. Faloutsos: Graphs over time: densification laws, shrinking diameters and possible explanations. KDD 2005: 177-187

M. E. J. Newman, Models of the small world, J. Stat. Phys. 101, 819-841 (2000).
</text>

<text>
SEARCH
</text>

<text>
<cite>Kleinberg 2000</cite>: Navigation in a Small World. Nature 406(2000), 845.

J. Kleinberg. The small-world phenomenon: An algorithmic perspective. Proc. 32nd ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing, 2000

J. Kleinberg. Small-World Phenomena and the Dynamics of Information. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS) 14, 2001.

J. Kleinberg. The Small-World Phenomenon and Decentralized Search. SIAM News 37(3), April 2004

J. Kleinberg. Complex Networks and Decentralized Search Algorithms. Proceedings of the International Congress of Mathematicians (ICM), 2006.

Cécile Caretta Cartozo and Paolo De Los Rios 
Extended Navigability of Small World Networks: Exact Results and New Insights
Phys. Rev. Lett. » Volume 102 » Issue 23
Phys. Rev. Lett. 102, 238703 (2009) [4 pages]
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.102.238703
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevLett.102.238703

Shai Carmi, Stephen Carter, Jie Sun, and Daniel ben-Avraham
Asymptotic Behavior of the Kleinberg Model
Phys. Rev. Lett. » Volume 102 » Issue 23
Phys. Rev. Lett. 102, 238702 (2009) [4 pages]
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.102.238702
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevLett.102.238702


++ Searchable networks:
(when a large fraction of search chains are successful, the network is searchable)
(networks with efficient greedy routing are said to be navigable)

D. J. Watts, P. S. Dodds, and M. E. J. Newman. Identity and search in social networks, Science 296, 1302-1305 (2002).

Adamic L., Lukose R., Puniyani A., and Huberman B., Search in power law networks, Physical review Vol 64.

L. Adamic, E. Adar. How To Search a Social Network. Social Networks Journal. Vol 27, Is 3, 2005, Pages 187-203


++ Hidden metric spaces
(conjecture: presence of hidden metric spaces in many real-world networks)

M. A. Serrano, D. Krioukov, and M. Boguñá. 
Self-similarity of complex networks and hidden metric spaces. 
Physical Review Letters » Volume 100 » Issue 7, 078701 (2008)
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.100.078701
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevLett.100.078701

Navigability of complex networks
Marián Boguñá, Dmitri Krioukov, K. C. Claffy
Nature Physics 5, 74 - 80 (2009) 
doi:10.1038/nphys1130

Marián Boguñá and Dmitri Krioukov
Navigating Ultrasmall Worlds in Ultrashort Time
Physical Review Letters » Volume 102 » Issue 5, 058701 (2009)
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.102.058701
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevLett.102.058701
(hidden-metric-space models of scale-free networks are navigable for a wide range of parameters vs. Kleinberg's model single-point navigation)

</text>

</document>

</document>