<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<tag>affiliation-networks</tag>
<title>Affiliation networks</title>

<text>
Affiliation networks (a.k.a. membership networks) are a special kind of two-mode network: bipartite graph, actors + events the actor is associated to (e.g. organizations, clubs, meetings, groups...). Events, therefore define subsets of actors, whose belonging to the group can be described by means of a binary affiliation variable (for each relevant subset).
</text>

<text>
e.g. Club membership, voluntary organizations, attendance to social events, sitting on a board of directors, countries belonging to treaty organiztions...
</text>


<text>
Representation mechanism for hypergraphs:
- When sets of elements have something in common (beyond pairwise associations)
</text>

<text>
e.g. 

bipartite networks such as...

- directors sitting on Fortune 1000 boards

- human disease network: 
	nodes: human genetic disorders and all known disease genes
	links: when mutations in a gene are involved in some disorder
	goal: network analysis might uncover unknown relations
[
K.-I. Goh, M. E. Cusick, D. Valle, B. Childs, M. Vidal, A.-L. Barabási 
The human disease network 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 104:21, 8685 (2007).
PNAS May 22, 2007 vol. 104 no. 21 8685-8690
doi: 10.1073/pnas.0701361104
]

tripartite hypergraphs:

- tagged social networks, 
	nodes: users + tags + photos (Flickr) or scientific papers (CiteULike)
	hyperedges = (user,tag,document)
	+ three hyperedge distributions of different features: the user distribution decays more slowly 
	(more tagging people than popular tags or documents!)
[
Vinko Zlatic, Gourab Ghoshal, Guido Caldarelli (2009)  
Hypergraph topological quantities for tagged social networks.   
Phys Rev E Stat Nonlin Soft Matter Phys 80: 3 Pt 2. Sep  
http://link.aps.org/abstract/PRE/v80/p036118
]
	
</text>

<text>
++ Projection
</text>

<text>
e.g. interlocking boards of directors
</text>

</document>
