<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<tag>affiliation-networks</tag>
<title>Affiliation networks</title>

<text>
Affiliation networks (a.k.a. membership networks) are a special kind of two-mode network: bipartite graph, actors + events the actor is associated to (e.g. organizations, clubs, meetings, groups...). Events, therefore define subsets of actors, whose belonging to the group can be described by means of a binary affiliation variable (for each relevant subset).
</text>

<text>
e.g. Club membership, voluntary organizations, attendance to social events, sitting on a board of directors, countries belonging to treaty organiztions, IMDB database...
</text>


USN:
"a key feature of social networks is high transitivity, meaning that if A and B are connected and there is also a connection between B and C, it is likely that there is also a connection between A and C (discussed in chapter 2). This situation does not occur in physical and biological networks (Newman 2006b; Newman and Park 2003). Transitivity leads to clustering into “communities” (chapter 3) and calls for quite different models than those that work for other kinds of networks. The clustering occurs because people belong to groups and organizations of one kind or another, or write papers together, or appear in the same movies, or belong to the same boards of directors. They also live in geographically delineated neighborhoods and, as we saw in the chapter on small groups, may attend the same events. People are said to be connected when they share membership in one of these “communities”; conversely, the “communities” are linked when they share at least one person in common. This duality was first called attention to in an aptly titled paper, “The Duality of Persons and Groups” (Breiger 1974). In the mathematical language of graph theory, this duality is called a bipartite graph"

ref. Breiger, Ronald. 1974. The duality of persons and groups. Social Forces 53:181–190. 


<text>
Representation mechanism for hypergraphs:
- When sets of elements have something in common (beyond pairwise associations)
</text>

<text>
e.g. 

bipartite networks such as...

- directors sitting on Fortune 1000 boards <cite>Newman et al. 2001</cite>

- human disease network: 
	nodes: human genetic disorders and all known disease genes
	links: when mutations in a gene are involved in some disorder
	goal: network analysis might uncover unknown relations
[
K.-I. Goh, M. E. Cusick, D. Valle, B. Childs, M. Vidal, A.-L. Barabási 
The human disease network 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 104:21, 8685 (2007).
PNAS May 22, 2007 vol. 104 no. 21 8685-8690
doi: 10.1073/pnas.0701361104
]

tripartite hypergraphs:

- tagged social networks, 
	nodes: users + tags + photos (Flickr) or scientific papers (CiteULike)
	hyperedges = (user,tag,document)
	+ three hyperedge distributions of different features: the user distribution decays more slowly 
	(more tagging people than popular tags or documents!)
[
Vinko Zlatic, Gourab Ghoshal, Guido Caldarelli (2009)  
Hypergraph topological quantities for tagged social networks.   
Phys Rev E Stat Nonlin Soft Matter Phys 80: 3 Pt 2. Sep  
http://link.aps.org/abstract/PRE/v80/p036118
]
	
</text>

<text>
++ Projection
</text>

<text>
e.g. interlocking boards of directors

Fortune 1000 board membership <cite>Newman et al. 2001</cite>
+ bipartite network (boards and directors)
+ three empirical degree distributions: boards + directors + one-mode projection to the set of directors
+ an uncorrelated bipartite network with the same degree distribution, whose projection is correlated and remarkably close to the real-world data.
+ the clustering coefficient of the one-mode projection is almost the same as the measured one (a coincidence?)
</text>


++ SAGE#28

++ SAGE, p. 555: (p,q)-cores

<document>
<tag>centrality-multimodal</tag>
<title>Centrality in two-mode networks</title>

<cite>Prell 2012</cite>, pp.115-116

+ Modifications to standard measures of centrality (e.g. normalization)

refs.

Katherine Faust: "Centrality in affiliation networks", Social Networks 19:157-191, 1997
S.P. Borgatti, M.G. Everett: "Network analysis of 2-mode data", Social Networks 19:243-269


</document>

</document>
