<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<tag>connectivity</tag>
<title>Network connectivity</title>


<text>
K: Large, complex networks often have what is called a giant component, which is a deliberately informal term for a connected component that contains a significant fraction of all nodes. Moreover, when a network contains a giant component, it almost always contains only one ... why? ++ imagine that there were two giant components, each with millions of nodes. All it would take is a single edge from someone in the first of these components to someone in the second, and the two giant components would merge into a single
component. In most cases, it’s essentially inconceivable that some such edge wouldn’t
form, and hence two coexisting giant components are something one almost never
sees in real networks. When a giant component exists, it is thus generally unique and
distinguishable as a component that dwarfs all others
</text>

<text>
K: e.g. the romantic relationships in an American high school over an 18-month period [49]. Bearman, Moody, and Stovel note in their analysis of this
network, “These structures reflect relationships that may be long over, and they link individuals together in chains far too long to be the subject of even the most intense gossip and scrutiny. Nevertheless, they are real: like social facts, they are invisible yet consequential macrostructures that arise as the product of individual agency.” (++dynamic aspects)
</text>

<text>
L: <cite>Broder et al. 2000</cite> analyzed over 200 million servers in the Internet’s Webgraph, and discovered its giant component, called the giant strongly connected component (GSCC).  The Internet’s Webgraph is shaped like a “bowtie”—44 million nodes (21%) are predominantly incoming nodes that send messages such as email; another 44 million are predominantly outgoing nodes that receive messages. A larger cluster, 56 million (27%) make up the GSCC.  
</text>

<text>
Facebook <cite>Ugander at al. 2011</cite>: (1) global structure of the graph: the social network is nearly fully connected, with 99.91% of individuals belonging to a single large connected component, (2) by studying the average local clustering coefficient and degeneracy of graph neighborhoods: the Facebook graph as a whole is clearly sparse, the graph neighborhoods of users contain surprisingly dense structure; (3) assortativity patterns present in the graph by studying the basic demographic and network properties of users. We observe clear degree assortativity and characterize the extent to which "your friends have more friends than you". Furthermore, we observe a strong effect of age on friendship preferences as well as a globally modular community structure driven by nationality, but we do not find any strong gender homophily. 
</text>

<text>
++ Dunbar's number, c. 150 http://www.technologyreview.com/blog/arxiv/26824/ 
+ http://arxiv.org/abs/1105.5170 Validation of Dunbar's Number In Twitter Conversations
</text>


<text>
++ <cite>Barzel and Biham 2009</cite>
</text>

<!-- Degree distribution -->

<document>
<tag>connectivity-degree-distribution</tag>
<title>Degree distribution</title>


<text>
NOTE:
+ Binomial/Poisson degree distributions
+ Power laws
+ Power laws with exponential cut-offs (any finite network with a heavy tail necessarily includes a cut-off, i.e. an end-part of the distribution with a rapid exponential decay)
</text>

</document>


<!-- Density -->

<document>
<tag>connectivity-density</tag>
<title>Density</title>

<text>
L: Density is the ratio of the number of actual links to the maximum number possible.
</text>

<equation>
density(G) = \frac{m}{n(n-1)}
</equation>

</document>


<!-- Shortest paths -->

<document>
<tag>connectivity-shortest-paths</tag>
<title>Shortest paths in networks</title>

<text>
The strength of interactions often diminishes as node become more remote. In fact, in weighted networks, link length is inversely proportional to link weight, since weights indicate the strength of the connection between the linked nodes (a measure of similarity) whereas lengths indicate the conceptual distance between the nodes (a measure of dissimilarity).
</text>


<text>
As mentioned in the chapter on Graph Theory, the distance matrix represents the the pairwise distance corresponding to the shortest paths linking the nodes in a network. The characteristic path length of the network can be computed as the average (sometimes the median) of the graph distance matrix.
</text>

<text>
The average path length varies with the size of the network, often in what might seem non-intuitive ways. <cite>Leskovek et al. 2005</cite> found that...
</text>

<text>
<q>six degrees of separation</q>

+ Stanley Milgram (1967): 296 volunteers were asked to send a message by postcard 
 experiments reported in The Small World Problem [7] in popular science journal Psychology Today, with a more rigorous version of the paper appearing in Sociometry two years later.
<cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite>
[Stanley Milgram, "The Small World Problem", Psychology Today, 1967, Vol. 2, 60-67]


+ Facebook (2011): the average number of acquaintances separating any two people in the world was 4.74, calculating the average distance between any two people by computing a vast number of sample paths among Facebook users (721 million, more than one-tenth of the world’s population) <cite>Backstrom et al. 2011</cite>
</text>


<text>
The average path length, however, can be influenced by a small number of outliers (e.g. disconnected or remote nodes), hence a more robust measure is often employed: the global efficiency <cite>Latora and Marchiori 2001</cite>. The global efficiency is computed as the average of the inverse of the distance matrix. A fully connected network has maximum global efficiency (all pairs of nodes are connected by links), while a fully disconnected network has minimum global efficiency (all distances between nodes are infinite).
</text>

<text>
The average path length and the global efficiency are global measures of network connectivity. Low path lengths and high efficiencies indicate short shortest paths, but they do not consider other paths that might exist in the network (not even the number of different shortest paths that might exist). Alternative metrics of network integration consider them.
</text>

<text>
Communicability measures global information flow within a network based on the number of walks between nodes <cite>Estrada and Hatano 2008</cite> <cite>Crofts and Higham 2009</cite>.
</text>

</document>


<!-- Average path length -->

<document>
<tag>connectivity-path-length</tag>
<title>Average path length</title>

<text>
The path length (or distance) between two nodes is the length of the shortest path between them, a.k.a. internode distance.  The maximum internode distance corresponds to the diameter of the network.
</text>

<text>
+ average path length is the average over all shortest paths.

The average path length of a network (a.k.a. characteristic path length, mean internode distance, or mean geodesic distance) is defined as the average path length over all (shortest) direct paths between all pairs of nodes in the network, i.e. the average shortest path length over all pairs of nodes between which there is at least one connecting path.
</text>

<text>
L: Let <eqn>\ell_{i,j}</eqn> the length of the shortest path between node <eqn>v_i</eqn> and <eqn>v_j</eqn>. Then, the average over all <eqn>\ell_{i,j}</eqn> is just
</text>

<equation>
L(G) = \langle \ell_{i,j} \rangle = \sum_{i} \sum_{j} \frac{d_{i,j}}{n(n-1)}
</equation>

<text>
Since we have to find all paths between nodes in the network, we could resort to an all-pairs shortest path algorithm. However, if link costs are equal, a simple breadth-first traversal suffices and computes the average path length in quadratic time.
</text>

<text>
L: In terms of the path matrix, row v of the path matrix corresponds to starting node v, and the elements of row v correspond to the other nodes in the network. If a node is not reachable from node v, then the length of the path between them is zero. We construct the path matrix, row-by-row, and then compute the average value of the nonzero elements of the path matrix. Averaging over all paths from all pairs of nodes yields the characteristic or average path length. 
</text>

<text>
i.e. <eqn>O(n^2)</eqn> algorithm
</text>

<note>
<text>
L: While we are computing the network characteristic path legth, we can also compute its diameter and radius as a byproduct of the path length calculation. Diameter is the largest value of k in the network, and a node’s radius is the maximum distance of this node from all others. The node with the smallest radius is the central node—it is as close or closer to all nodes than any other node (i.e. computes a measure of centrality for all nodes, and designates the most central node as the network’s center). We could also calculate closeness as a byproduct of finding all paths through the
network...
</text>
</note>

</document>


<document>
<tag>connectivity-efficiency</tag>
<title>Link efficiency</title>

<text>
L: Link efficiency is used for comparing the efficiency of a network in terms of its average path length and number of links. A link-efficient
network utilizes its links in an efficient manner to reduce average path length. In many applications of network science we want the shortest average path length possible while simultaneously conserving the number of links. 

++ efficient network are sparse and efficiently utilize links to reduce average path length.

We define link efficiency E(G) as follows:
</text>

<equation>
E(G) =  \frac{m - L(G)}{m} = 1 - \frac{L(G)}{m}
</equation>

<text>
L: this metric ranges from zero, when the
average path length is m, to 100%, when the average path length is zero. In
the extreme case, E = 1.0, every link contributes to link efficiency. When E = 0,
the average path length equals m, which is the worst path length possible. Link
efficiency is a measure of how effective links are at shortening characteristic path
length. Higher values of E correspond to networks that are more efficient.
</text>

<text>
L: In general, we are interested in efficient utilization of links as the size of a network
increases. A network is scalable if link efficiency approaches 100% as network size
n approaches infinity. Otherwise, a network is non-scalable.
</text>

</document>


</document>
