<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<title>Network Structure</title>


<document>
<tag>structure-connectivity</tag>
<title>Connectivity</title>


<text>
K: Large, complex networks often have what is called a giant component, which is a deliberately informal term for a connected component that contains a significant fraction of all nodes. Moreover, when a network contains a giant component, it almost always contains only one ... why? ++ imagine that there were two giant components, each with millions of nodes. All it would take is a single edge from someone in the first of these components to someone in the second, and the two giant components would merge into a single
component. In most cases, it’s essentially inconceivable that some such edge wouldn’t
form, and hence two coexisting giant components are something one almost never
sees in real networks. When a giant component exists, it is thus generally unique and
distinguishable as a component that dwarfs all others
</text>

<text>
K: e.g. the romantic relationships in an American high school over an 18-month period [49]. Bearman, Moody, and Stovel note in their analysis of this
network, “These structures reflect relationships that may be long over, and they link individuals together in chains far too long to be the subject of even the most intense gossip and scrutiny. Nevertheless, they are real: like social facts, they are invisible yet consequential macrostructures that arise as the product of individual agency.” (++dynamic aspects)
</text>

<text>
Facebook <cite>Ugander at al. 2011</cite>: (1) global structure of the graph: the social network is nearly fully connected, with 99.91% of individuals belonging to a single large connected component, (2) by studying the average local clustering coefficient and degeneracy of graph neighborhoods: the Facebook graph as a whole is clearly sparse, the graph neighborhoods of users contain surprisingly dense structure; (3) assortativity patterns present in the graph by studying the basic demographic and network properties of users. We observe clear degree assortativity and characterize the extent to which "your friends have more friends than you". Furthermore, we observe a strong effect of age on friendship preferences as well as a globally modular community structure driven by nationality, but we do not find any strong gender homophily. 
</text>

<text>
++ Dunbar's number, c. 150 http://www.technologyreview.com/blog/arxiv/26824/ 
+ http://arxiv.org/abs/1105.5170 Validation of Dunbar's Number In Twitter Conversations
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>structure-shortest-paths</tag>
<title>Shortest paths</title>

<text>
The strength of interactions often diminishes as node become more remote. In fact, in weighted networks, link length is inversely proportional to link weight, since weights indicate the strength of the connection between the linked nodes (a measure of similarity) whereas lengths indicate the conceptual distance between the nodes (a measure of dissimilarity).
</text>


<text>
As mentioned in the chapter on Graph Theory, the distance matrix represents the the pairwise distance corresponding to the shortest paths linking the nodes in a network. The characteristic path length of the network can be computed as the average (sometimes the median) of the graph distance matrix.
</text>

<text>
The average path length varies with the size of the network, often in what might seem non-intuitive ways. <cite>Leskovek et al. 2005</cite> found that...
</text>

<text>
<q>six degrees of separation</q>

+ Stanley Milgram (1967): 296 volunteers were asked to send a message by postcard 
 experiments reported in The Small World Problem [7] in popular science journal Psychology Today, with a more rigorous version of the paper appearing in Sociometry two years later.
<cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite>
[Stanley Milgram, "The Small World Problem", Psychology Today, 1967, Vol. 2, 60-67]


+ Facebook (2011): the average number of acquaintances separating any two people in the world was 4.74, calculating the average distance between any two people by computing a vast number of sample paths among Facebook users (721 million, more than one-tenth of the world’s population) <cite>Backstrom et al. 2011</cite>
</text>


<text>
The average path length, however, can be influenced by a small number of outliers (e.g. disconnected or remote nodes), hence a more robust measure is often employed: the global efficiency <cite>Latora and Marchiori 2001</cite>. The global efficiency is computed as the average of the inverse of the distance matrix. A fully connected network has maximum global efficiency (all pairs of nodes are connected by links), while a fully disconnected network has minimum global efficiency (all distances between nodes are infinite).
</text>

<text>
The average path length and the global efficiency are global measures of network connectivity. Low path lengths and high efficiencies indicate short shortest paths, but they do not consider other paths that might exist in the network (not even the number of different shortest paths that might exist). Alternative metrics of network integration consider them.
</text>

<text>
Communicability measures global information flow within a network based on the number of walks between nodes <cite>Estrada and Hatano 2008</cite> <cite>Crofts and Higham 2009</cite>.
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>structure-degree-distributions</tag>
<title>Degree distributions</title>


<text>
++ A wide range of empirical networks – whether biological, technological, information-related or linguistic
– generically exhibit important degree-degree anticorrelations (i.e., they are disassortative), the only exceptions
usually being social ones, which tend to be positively correlated (assortative).
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>structure-clustering-coefficient</tag>
<title>Clustering coefficients</title>

<text>
The clustering coefficient of an individual node measure the density of connections among the node's neighbors <cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite>. Densely connected neighborhoods form clusters around a node.
</text>

<text>
The clustering coefficient measures how many nodes form triangular subgraphs with their adjacent nodes. In its original form, the clustering coefficient is the fraction of fully connected triangles among the node and its neighbors (a.k.a. three-node motifs). The clustering coefficient, therefore, measures how the neighbors of a node are interconnected.
</text>

<text>
L: In social network analysis, high clustering means that friends of friends are linked to one another. It is network science’s way of saying, “Birds of a feather, flock together.”
</text>

<text>
L: Suppose that we compare the number of links connecting a group of k adjacent nodes
to the maximum possible number,which is given by a complete subgraph with (k(k.))/2 links. 
Each subgraph formed around a node in this k-node neighborhood forms a triangular
subgraph if it is complete, and does not form a triangular subgraph if one or
more links is (are) missing. The amount of clustering depends on the number of triangles
found among these neighbors. Let the neighbors of node u be the nodes directly connected
to u. There are degree(u) such neighbors, which means that there are potentially
(degree(u) [degree(u)-1])/2 links among these neighbors. Suppose that the neighbors
share c links; then the cluster coefficient of node u, CC(u), is

CC(u) = 2c / ( degree(u) (degree(u) - 1) )

A more visual way to think of cluster coefficient is the following: A node u with degree(u)
neighbors may be part of c triangular subgraphs, each containing node u as one of the
triangle’s three nodes. Cluster coefficient is the ratio of the actual number of triangular
subgraphs c to the maximum possible number.
</text>

<text>
The clustering coefficient of can be interpreted as the probability that two of its neighbors are adjacent in the network. However, this probability often depends on the node degree. Hence it is often expressed as a degree-dependent function:
</text>

<equation>
C(k) = \langle CC(u)|_{degree(u)=k} \rangle
</equation>


<text>
The cluster coefficient of the whole network CC(G) is the average over all node clustering
coefficients. It is less informative, but it is often employed.
The clustering coefficient reaches it maximum for complete graphs CC(K_n) = 1 and its minimum for trees CC(T)=0 (e.g. stars).
</text>

<text>
Sometimes, the clustering coefficient just counts (three times) the number of triangles in the network, a measure known as transitivity by sociologists:
</text>

<equation>
transitivity(G) = 3 \frac{ \#triangles }{ \#connectedTriples }
</equation>

<text>
It should be noted that each triangle consists of three connected triples, hence the constant 3 in the expression above. The number of connected triples of nodes equals <eqn>\sum_i d_i(d_i-1)/2</eqn> <eqn>= n ( \langle d^2 \rangle - \langle d \rangle)/2</eqn>. Finally, the number of triangles <eqn>T</eqn> can be computed from the adjacency matrix as follows:
</text>

<equation>
T = \frac{1}{6} \sum_i a_{ii}^{(3)} = \frac{1}{6} Tr A^3
</equation>

<text>
where <eqn>Tr A^3</eqn> is the trace (the sum of the diagonal elements) of the cube of the graph adjacency matrix.
</text>


<text>
Low-degree nodes can disproportionately influence their neighbors' clustering coefficients, a problem solved by transitivity <cite>Newman 2003</cite>... a collectively normalized variant of the clustering coefficient.
</text>


<text>
Clustering coefficients and trasitivity have been generalized for weighted and directed networks <cite>Onnela et al. 2005</cite> <cite>Fagiolo 2007</cite>.
</text>

<text>
Clustering (segregation) - efficiency (integration) trade-off... Optimal clustering and modularity are incompatible with optimal global efficiency (separate communities do not communicate too much). Local vs. global order (e.g. specialization of subsystems).
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>structure-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>
</document>

</document>
