<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<tag>connectivity</tag>
<title>Network connectivity</title>


<text>
K: Large, complex networks often have what is called a giant component, which is a deliberately informal term for a connected component that contains a significant fraction of all nodes. Moreover, when a network contains a giant component, it almost always contains only one ... why? ++ imagine that there were two giant components, each with millions of nodes. All it would take is a single edge from someone in the first of these components to someone in the second, and the two giant components would merge into a single
component. In most cases, it’s essentially inconceivable that some such edge wouldn’t
form, and hence two coexisting giant components are something one almost never
sees in real networks. When a giant component exists, it is thus generally unique and
distinguishable as a component that dwarfs all others
</text>

<text>
K: e.g. the romantic relationships in an American high school over an 18-month period [49]. Bearman, Moody, and Stovel note in their analysis of this
network, “These structures reflect relationships that may be long over, and they link individuals together in chains far too long to be the subject of even the most intense gossip and scrutiny. Nevertheless, they are real: like social facts, they are invisible yet consequential macrostructures that arise as the product of individual agency.” (++dynamic aspects)
</text>

<text>
L: <cite>Broder et al. 2000</cite> analyzed over 200 million servers in the Internet’s Webgraph, and discovered its giant component, called the giant strongly connected component (GSCC).  The Internet’s Webgraph is shaped like a “bowtie”—44 million nodes (21%) are predominantly incoming nodes that send messages such as email; another 44 million are predominantly outgoing nodes that receive messages. A larger cluster, 56 million (27%) make up the GSCC.  
</text>

<text>
Facebook <cite>Ugander at al. 2011</cite>: (1) global structure of the graph: the social network is nearly fully connected, with 99.91% of individuals belonging to a single large connected component, (2) by studying the average local clustering coefficient and degeneracy of graph neighborhoods: the Facebook graph as a whole is clearly sparse, the graph neighborhoods of users contain surprisingly dense structure; (3) assortativity patterns present in the graph by studying the basic demographic and network properties of users. We observe clear degree assortativity and characterize the extent to which "your friends have more friends than you". Furthermore, we observe a strong effect of age on friendship preferences as well as a globally modular community structure driven by nationality, but we do not find any strong gender homophily. 
</text>

<text>
++ Dunbar's number, c. 150 http://www.technologyreview.com/blog/arxiv/26824/ 
+ http://arxiv.org/abs/1105.5170 Validation of Dunbar's Number In Twitter Conversations
</text>


<text>
++ <cite>Barzel and Biham 2009</cite>
</text>

<!-- Degree distribution -->

<document>
<tag>connectivity-decomposition</tag>
<title>Network decomposition</title>


+ Strongly-connected components O(m) [Cormen 2001 pp. 552-556]
+ Weakly-connected components O(m) [Cormen 2001 pp. 499-501]
+ Biconnected componens O(m) [Cormen 2001, pp. 558-559]

In a directed graph, if we shrink every strong component into a single vertex, an acyclic graph results
+ Symmetric connectivity [Doreian et al.: "Symmetric acyclic decomposition of networks", Journal of Classification 17(1):3-28]
+ Short cycle connectivity [Batagelj and Zaversnik: 

e.g. Bow-tie decomposition [Kleinberg

Different kinds of connectivities
++ [Matula: "Graph theoretic techniques for cluster analysis algorithms", in J. Van Ryzin (ed.) "Classification and Clustering", pp. 95-127, Academic Press, 1977]
++ [Esfahanian: "On the evolution of graph connectivity algorithms". In Selected Topics in Graph Theory (Wilson and Beteke, eds), Cambridge University Press, 2008] @ SAGE p.552


Decomposition

k-core decomposition
++ [Alvarez-Hamelin et al.: "k-core decomposition: A tool for the visualization of large networks", arXiv, 2005]
Modular decomposition
++ [Habib and Paul: "A survey of algorithmic aspects of modular decomposition", arXiv, 2009]
++ [Papadopoulos and Voglis: "Drawing graphs using modular decomposition", GD'05, LNCS 3842:343-354, 2005]
Split decomposition
++ [Joeris et al: "O(m log n) split decomposition of strongly-connected graphs", LNCS 5420:158-171, 2009]

</document>

<!-- Degree distribution -->

<document>
<tag>connectivity-degree-distribution</tag>
<title>Degree distribution</title>


<text>
NOTE:
+ Binomial/Poisson degree distributions
+ Power laws
+ Power laws with exponential cut-offs (any finite network with a heavy tail necessarily includes a cut-off, i.e. an end-part of the distribution with a rapid exponential decay)
</text>

</document>


<!-- Density -->

<document>
<tag>connectivity-density</tag>
<title>Density</title>



<text>
L: Density is the ratio of the number of actual links to the maximum number possible.

For directed networks:
</text>

<equation>
density(G) = \frac{m}{n(n-1)}
</equation>


For undirected networks: twice that...


++ Density (the number of connections contained within the network) and its opposite, Structural Holes (concerned with the lack of connections)

[White, Douglas R., and Frank Harary. 2001. The cohesiveness of blocks in social networks: Node connectivity and conditional density. Sociological Methodology 31:305–359.]


USN'2012: 

"Density is at the heart of community, social support, and high visibility (when people in a network can see what others are doing and monitor and sanction their behavior). Density facilitates the transmission of ideas, rumors, and diseases. Other things being equal, the greater the density, the more likely is a network to be considered a cohesive community, a source of social support, and an effective transmitter. Classic agricultural communities or villages have greater density than modern cities, and people tend to know one another in many contexts—as relatives, coworkers, church attendees, and so forth. Given the human limitation on the number of sustainable connections, smaller networks will have greater density. It is easier to know everyone in a small group than in a large community. In comparing different networks in terms of density, one therefore has to take into account their size.




Warning! Density depends on network size, so it cannot be used for comparing networks of different size (average node degree is the preferred choice)



Density
++ [Seidman: "Network structure and minimum degree", Social Networks 5:269-287, 1983]

</document>

<document>
<tag>connectivity-centralization</tag>
<title>Centralization</title>

Degree centralization score <cite>Freeman 1978</cite>

Evaluating the extent to which network density depends on individual nodes (akin to standard deviation vs. mean in descriptive statistics)
i.e. different networks with the same density can still have very different structures (e.g. interconnectedness/distribution vs. centralization)

<equation>
centralization(G) = \frac{ \sum_{i=1}^{n} [ degree(max) - degree(i) ] }{ \max \sum_{i=1}^{n} [ degree(max^*) - degree(i^*) ]}
</equation>

where <eqn>degree(max)</eqn> is the largest node degree in the network and <eqn>\max \sum_{i=1}^{n} [ degree(max^*) - degree(i^*) ]</eqn> is the maximum possible sun of differences in node degree for any network of size n.

The maximum node degree for a network of size n is n-1. In a star network, the differences will be (n-1)-1 = n-2. Hence, The difference sum will be (n-1)(n-2) = n^2 - 3n + 2 for a star network. 

+ Any additional link in the network cannot involve the center of the star. Therefore, the difference corresponding to the nodes involved will be (n-1)-2 = n-3.   

- The removal of a link to the star network, likewise, will result in a disconnected node (whose different will still be n-2) and n-2 nodes with reduced differences: n-3.

+ A change in a link in the star network will also result in reduced differences, since the hub degree will be n-2 and the differences will be reduced to n-3 for those nodes with degree 1

Therefore, the star is the most centralized graph and yields the largest difference sum: n^2 - 3n + 2.

<note>
Approach valid for any centrality measure.
</note>

</document>


<document>
<tag>connectivity-structuralº-holes</tag>
<title>Structural holes</title>





"STRUCTURAL HOLES: 
Density is based on the idea of connection. But one can turn the idea on its head and focus on the lack of a connection (Burt 1992).
[Burt, Ronald S. 1982. Toward a structural theory of action: Network models of social structure, perception and action. New York: Academic Press.]
Ronald Burt calls the situation in which a node Ego connects individuals who are themselves connected but who, without the presence of Ego would have no connection with one another, a “structural hole.” 
e.g. In the karate club sociogram, nodes 1 and 34 are the key linkers, and their actions are the least constrained by others in the network.

"Like structural holes, “weak ties” also focuses on holes in the network. 

[Granovetter, Mark S. 1973. The strength of weak ties. American Journal of Sociology 78:1360–1380.]
[Granovetter, Mark S. 1982. The strength of weak ties: A network theory revisited. In Social structure and network analysis, edited by P. Marsden and N. Linn. Beverly Hills, Calif.: Sage.]


Ron Burt developed the notion of structural holes (absence of ties) to analyze how certain network structures give individuals strategic advantage over others <cite>Prell 2012</cite>. In Burt's terms, structural holes are <q>the empty spaces in social structure</q> (Burt: "Brokerage and closure: An introduction to social capital", Oxford University Press, 2005).

Structural holes allow for the existence of brokers or intermediaries (tertius gaudens)
ref. 
Georg Simmel: Conflict and the web of group affiliations, 1922 (English translation: Free Press, 1955)
Robert K. Merton: "The role-set: Problems in sociological theory". British Journal of Sociology, 8:106-120, 1957

Potential infuence of brokerage: status, profit, performance evaluations, higher salaries, good ideas (exposure to more diverse sources of information), innovation capacity in organizations...

Broker roles (Gould and Fernandez 1989): coordinator, consultant, representative, gatekeeper, liaison
<cite>Prell 2012</cite>, pp. 125-129
ref.
R.V. Gould, R.M. Fernandez: "Structures of mediation: A formal approach to brokerage in transaction networks". Sociological Methodology, 19:89-126, 1989

</document>



<!-- Shortest paths -->

<document>
<tag>connectivity-shortest-paths</tag>
<title>Shortest paths in networks</title>

<text>
The strength of interactions often diminishes as node become more remote. In fact, in weighted networks, link length is inversely proportional to link weight, since weights indicate the strength of the connection between the linked nodes (a measure of similarity) whereas lengths indicate the conceptual distance between the nodes (a measure of dissimilarity).
</text>


<text>
As mentioned in the chapter on Graph Theory, the distance matrix represents the the pairwise distance corresponding to the shortest paths linking the nodes in a network. The characteristic path length of the network can be computed as the average (sometimes the median) of the graph distance matrix.
</text>

<text>
The average path length varies with the size of the network, often in what might seem non-intuitive ways. <cite>Leskovek et al. 2005</cite> found that...
</text>

<text>
<q>six degrees of separation</q>

+ Stanley Milgram (1967): 296 volunteers were asked to send a message by postcard 
 experiments reported in The Small World Problem [7] in popular science journal Psychology Today, with a more rigorous version of the paper appearing in Sociometry two years later.
<cite>Travers and Milgram 1969</cite>
[Stanley Milgram, "The Small World Problem", Psychology Today, 1967, Vol. 2, 60-67]


+ Facebook (2011): the average number of acquaintances separating any two people in the world was 4.74, calculating the average distance between any two people by computing a vast number of sample paths among Facebook users (721 million, more than one-tenth of the world’s population) <cite>Backstrom et al. 2011</cite>
</text>


<text>
The average path length, however, can be influenced by a small number of outliers (e.g. disconnected or remote nodes), hence a more robust measure is often employed: the global efficiency <cite>Latora and Marchiori 2001</cite>. The global efficiency is computed as the average of the inverse of the distance matrix. A fully connected network has maximum global efficiency (all pairs of nodes are connected by links), while a fully disconnected network has minimum global efficiency (all distances between nodes are infinite).
</text>

<text>
The average path length and the global efficiency are global measures of network connectivity. Low path lengths and high efficiencies indicate short shortest paths, but they do not consider other paths that might exist in the network (not even the number of different shortest paths that might exist). Alternative metrics of network integration consider them.
</text>

<text>
Communicability measures global information flow within a network based on the number of walks between nodes <cite>Estrada and Hatano 2008</cite> <cite>Crofts and Higham 2009</cite>.
</text>

</document>


<!-- Average path length -->

<document>
<tag>connectivity-path-length</tag>
<title>Average path length</title>

<text>
The path length (or distance) between two nodes is the length of the shortest path between them, a.k.a. internode distance.  The maximum internode distance corresponds to the diameter of the network.
</text>

<text>
+ average path length is the average over all shortest paths.

The average path length of a network (a.k.a. characteristic path length, mean internode distance, or mean geodesic distance) is defined as the average path length over all (shortest) direct paths between all pairs of nodes in the network, i.e. the average shortest path length over all pairs of nodes between which there is at least one connecting path.
</text>

<text>
L: Let <eqn>\ell_{i,j}</eqn> the length of the shortest path between node <eqn>v_i</eqn> and <eqn>v_j</eqn>. Then, the average over all <eqn>\ell_{i,j}</eqn> is just
</text>

<equation>
L(G) = \langle \ell_{i,j} \rangle = \sum_{i} \sum_{j} \frac{d_{i,j}}{n(n-1)}
</equation>

<text>
Since we have to find all paths between nodes in the network, we could resort to an all-pairs shortest path algorithm. However, if link costs are equal, a simple breadth-first traversal suffices and computes the average path length in quadratic time.
</text>

<text>
L: In terms of the path matrix, row v of the path matrix corresponds to starting node v, and the elements of row v correspond to the other nodes in the network. If a node is not reachable from node v, then the length of the path between them is zero. We construct the path matrix, row-by-row, and then compute the average value of the nonzero elements of the path matrix. Averaging over all paths from all pairs of nodes yields the characteristic or average path length. 
</text>

<text>
i.e. <eqn>O(n^2)</eqn> algorithm
</text>

<note>
<text>
L: While we are computing the network characteristic path legth, we can also compute its diameter and radius as a byproduct of the path length calculation. Diameter is the largest value of k in the network, and a node’s radius is the maximum distance of this node from all others. The node with the smallest radius is the central node—it is as close or closer to all nodes than any other node (i.e. computes a measure of centrality for all nodes, and designates the most central node as the network’s center). We could also calculate closeness as a byproduct of finding all paths through the
network...
</text>
</note>

</document>


<document>
<tag>connectivity-efficiency</tag>
<title>Link efficiency</title>

<text>
L: Link efficiency is used for comparing the efficiency of a network in terms of its average path length and number of links. A link-efficient
network utilizes its links in an efficient manner to reduce average path length. In many applications of network science we want the shortest average path length possible while simultaneously conserving the number of links. 

++ efficient network are sparse and efficiently utilize links to reduce average path length.

We define link efficiency E(G) as follows:
</text>

<equation>
E(G) =  \frac{m - L(G)}{m} = 1 - \frac{L(G)}{m}
</equation>

<text>
L: this metric ranges from zero, when the
average path length is m, to 100%, when the average path length is zero. In
the extreme case, E = 1.0, every link contributes to link efficiency. When E = 0,
the average path length equals m, which is the worst path length possible. Link
efficiency is a measure of how effective links are at shortening characteristic path
length. Higher values of E correspond to networks that are more efficient.
</text>

<text>
L: In general, we are interested in efficient utilization of links as the size of a network
increases. A network is scalable if link efficiency approaches 100% as network size
n approaches infinity. Otherwise, a network is non-scalable.
</text>

</document>




<document>
<tag>connectivity-assortativity</tag>
<title>Assortativity</title>


<text>
Mixing in social networks
- assortative: people prefer to associate with others who are like them
- disassortative: people prefer to associate with others who are different

In general mixing is defined in terms of node attributes

Mixing with respect of node degree (degree-degree correlations):
- assortative: high degree nodes tend to be connected to high degree nodes
- disassortative: high degree nodes tend to be connected to low degree nodes

Focus on edge i, denote the excess in-degree of its starting point with ji and the excess out-degree of its endpoint with ki
Mixing is quantified by the assortativity coefficient characterizing the correlation between ji and ki over all i
Similar to a Pearson correlation coefficient
- Positive correlation - assortative,
- Negative correlation - disassortative
</text>

<text>
A measure based on degree <cite>Newman 2002</cite>, defined as the correlation coefficient for the degrees of neighboring nodes, indicates whether edges tend to link nodes of similar degrees (positive assortativity) or high-degree nodes preferentially connect to low-degree nodes (negative assortativity).
</text>


<text>
Empirical data
[
Characterization of complex networks: A survey of measurements
by Luciano Da F Costa, Francisco A Rodrigues, Gonzalo Travieso, P R Villas Boas
Advances in Physics (2005)
Volume: 56, Issue: 1, Publisher: Taylor &amp; Francis, Pages: 78
DOI: 10.1080/00018730601170527
arXiv: cond-mat/0505185
]


++ A wide range of empirical networks – whether biological, technological, information-related or linguistic
– generically exhibit important degree-degree anticorrelations (i.e., they are disassortative), the only exceptions
usually being social ones, which tend to be positively correlated (assortative).

Social networks tend to be assortative, technological and biological networks tend to be disassortative.

Mechanisms that influence mixing properties
In social relationships there is a documented attraction between individuals of similar temperament
- Group affiliations can create assortativity
On the WWW or Internet service relationships (directories, connectivity providers) can create disassortativity
- Constraints on the network assembly process (e.g. no multiple edges among pairs of nodes) can cause disassortativity
[M. E. J. Newman, Phys. Rev. E (2003)]


Effects
- enhacement of resilience due to assortative correlations (split the strongly connected code is not easy)
</text>

</document>



</document>
