<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<title>Network Motifs</title>



<document>
<tag>motifs</tag>
<title>Network building blocks</title>

<text>
Large networks can be decomposed into smaller <q>building blocks</q> or <q>networks-within-networks</q>, commonly referred to as <b>motifs</b>.
</text>

<text>
Every network can be uniquely decomposed into a set of motifs, and the number and distribution of individual motifs can reflect some functional characteristics of the network <cite>Sporns 2011</cite>.
</text>

++
R. Milo, S. Shen-Orr, S. Itzkovitz, N. Kashtan, D. Chklovskii and U. Alon
Network Motifs: Simple Building Blocks of Complex Networks
Science 25 October 2002: 
Vol. 298 no. 5594 pp. 824-827 
DOI: 10.1126/science.298.5594.824

e.g. 
only two different 3-node connected motifs in undirected networks
13 different 3-node connected motifs in directed networks

NAIVE IDEA: Network function explained in terms of the repeated appearances of the most significant motifs?
If that were true, motifs could explain not just network structure, but also determine its behavior.


network effects:
- homophily (the tendency of pairs of nodes to share the same characteristics) 
- balance (the tendency of the third in a triad to share or have a characteristic that complements the other two)

++ empirical study of network motifs

cf.

Kim Baskerville, Peter Grassberger, Maya Paczuski
Graph animals, subgraph sampling, and motif search in large networks.
Phys. Rev. E » Volume 76 » Issue 3, 036107, 2007
DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevE.76.036107 
URL: http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevE.76.036107

A. Vazquez, R. Dobrin, D. Sergi, J.-P. Eckmann, Z. N. Oltvai, A.-L. Barabási 
The topological relationship between the large-scale attributes and local interactions patterns of complex networks 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 101, 17940-17945 (2004).


<document>
<tag>motifs-dyads</tag>
<title>Dyads</title>

<text>
= Two actors and their ties
</text>

<text>
At the most basic level, a link establishes a relationship between two nodes. The link is a property of the pair, not of any single node...
</text>

The simplest network is a dyad. Relationships in a dyad can be undirected, mutual, or directed. When there is more than one relationship between a pair, such as coworkers and friends, it is called multiplex.

<text>
Dyadic analysis focuses on the properties of pairwise relationships,

DYAD CENSUS: MAN (Mutual, Asymmetric, Null)
+ In SNA, mutual dyads are viewed as more stable ties (e.g. reciprocal friendship), e.g. Facebook (undirected) vs. Google+ (directed)
+ Friendship networks contain a large number of asymmetric dyads !
+ Advice relations are even more likely to contain asymmetric dyads
</text>


<document>
<tag>motifs-dyads-propinquity</tag>
<title>Propinquity</title>

Propinquity (social networks): Nodes are more likely to be connected with one another if they are geographically close.

e.g. 

- friends and neighbors @ a pioneering study of the propinquity effect, Festinger, Schacter, and Back (1950)
[Festinger, L., S. Schacter, and K. Back. 1950. Social pressures in informal groups: A study of human factors in housing. Stanford, Calif.: Stanford University Press.]

- “interlocking directorates”: people who serve together on several different corporate boards of directors... “[i]nterlocks are concentrated in firms headquartered in the same locale” (Kono et al. 1998). 
[Kono, Clifford, Donald Palmer, Roger Friedland, and Matthew Zafonte. 1998. Lost in space: The geography of corporate interlocking directorates. American Journal of Sociology 103 (4): 863–911.]

- Common interests (e.g., music) and common arenas or foci for meeting (e.g., mothers at the playground) are another mode for drawing people together
[Feld, Scott L. 1981. The focused organization of social ties. American Journal of Sociology 86 (5): 1015–1035]

- Trade between countries, other things being equal, is more likely if the countries have common borders. But, for example, “averaged over all EU countries, intranational trade is about ten times as high as international trade with an EU partner country of similar size and distance” (Volker 2000). Economists tend to define propinquity in terms of cost of transportation rather than the actual number of miles between nodes or sheer border crossings when tariff is not an issue (Krugman and Obstfeld 2000)
[Volker, Nitsch. 2000. National borders and international trade: Evidence from the European Union. Canadian Journal of Economics 33 (4): 1091–1105.]
[Krugman, Paul R., and Maurice Obstfeld. 2000. International economics: Theory and policy. Reading, Mass.: Addison-Wesley.]

</document>

<document>
<tag>motifs-dyads-homophily</tag>
<title>Homophily</title>


Homophily, a different kind of propinquity.

USN'2012: (from the Greek, “love of the same”) is a concept introduced into social theory by Lazarsfeld and Merton (1978 [1955]) that embeds a folk proposition: “birds of a feather flock together.” More formally, if two people have characteristics that match in a proportion greater than expected in the population from which they are drawn or the network of which they are a part, then they are more likely to be connected (Verbrugge 1977). The converse is also true: if two people are connected, then they are more likely to have common characteristics or attributes. There is also an implied feedback: over time, relationships tend to sort out so that they become more homophilous.

[Lazarsfeld, Paul F., and Robert K. Merton. 1978 [1955]. Freedom and control in modern society. In Friendship as a social process: A substantive and methodological analysis, edited by M. Berger, T. Abel, and C. H. Page. New York: Octagon Books.]
[Verbrugge, Lois M. 1977. The structure of adult friendship choices. Social Forces 56:576–597.]


Lazarsfeld and Merton distinguished between status-homophily, which can be ascribed (e.g., age, race, sex) or acquired (e.g., marital status, education, occupation), and value-homophily (e.g., attitudes, stereotypes), which has also been termed homogeneity (Hall and Wellman 1985).
[Hall, Alan, and Barry Wellman, 1985. Social networks and social support. In Social support and health, edited by Sheldon Cohen and S. Leonard Syme. Orlando: Academic Press.]

e.g.
- dating and matching services offer checklists through which they attempt to bring people together.

There are two kinds of causes of homophily. 

1) Common norms or values may bring nodes with common attributes together, or the reverse, common attributes and contacts may lead to common norms, and this holds true for both individuals and collectivities
e.g. behaviors such as binge eating, alcohol use, dietary restraint, and so on. 

While common norms are promoted through common attributes, so are common attributes likely when association or friendship occurs as a result of co-location and commonly situated activities...
Chicken-and-egg situation: we do not know whether people hang around together because they share similar habits (homophily), or they have become similar to each other while hanging around with one another (peer effects)


2) Structural location. Two nodes may have the same attributes because both operate in the same arena, and again, vice versa 
e.g. email interactions, over a year, of a population of over 30,000 students and staff in a university, Kossinets and Watts (2009) were able to determine that individual preferences for like persons and common social location both produced homophily. But modest initial preferences for similar others became amplified over many email exchanges into stronger patterns of homophily; similar interests led to similar locations in which similar interests were more available. The feedback between network structure and individual preference thus becomes especially noticeable over time.
[Kossinets, Gueorgi, and Duncan J. Watts. 2009. Origins of homophily in an evolving social network. American Journal of Sociology 115 (2): 405–450.]


Quantification: Ratio of homophilous ties in ego networks (UCINET: Ego network homophily) = Ties in the ego network that are homophilous / Ties in the ego network

Support for homophily in actual networks: Age, sex, race, education, status, attitudes, behaviors...
</document>


<document>
<tag>motifs-dyads-reciprocity</tag>
<title>Reciprocity</title>

USN'2012: ...  in directed graphs or networks, there can be four possible relationships: none at all (they are not connected), A relates to B, B relates to A, and A and B both relate to one another. We are concerned here with the fourth relationship, reciprocity or mutuality.


The concept of mutuality implies first, that relations are reciprocal, that is, they involve a give and take between the two parties; and second, that power or asymmetry in the relationship is of little or no consequence.

e.g.
- husband-wife relationship (even when their roles might be unequal in practice)
- mutuality is strong factor in the formation of children’s friendships (Schaefer et al. 2010)
[Schaefer, David R., John M. Light, Richard A. Fabes, Laura D. Hanish, and Carol Lynn Martin. 2010. Fundamental principles of network formation among preschool children. Social Networks 32 (1): 61–71.]
- in elementary school, girls are more likely to reciprocate friendship choice than are boys
- doctor-patient relationship can be a close one, but the relationship is inherently anti-symmetric.
- trade (between individuals and organizations)
- trade relations between nations
- reciprocity between countries in the global telecom network was found to have increased between 1989 and 1999 (Monge and Matei 2004)
[Monge, Peter, and Sorin Adam Matei. 2004. The role of the global telecommunications network in bridging economic and political divides, 1989 to 1999. Journal of Communication 54 (3): 511–531.]

+ “coalition building” consists of creating mutual flows between pairs that do not share many attributes
e.g. 
- public health and in drug-and alcohol-addiction-prevention programs

Social engineering efforts... "bringing pairs together in the long term when they have quite different characteristics is difficult and rare" (USN'2012)


</document>

<text>
<cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>: chapters 13, 15 &amp; 16...
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>motifs-triads</tag>
<title>Triads</title>

<text>
= Three actors and their ties
</text>

Network analysis really begins with triads, for they are the beginnings of a “society” that is independent of the ties between a dyad (USN'2012):




... <q>no matter how close a triad may be, there is always the occasion on which two of the three members regard the third as an intruder</q> (Simmel 1950, 135) 
In Simmel’s view, the third can be non-partisan and a mediator, but can also be “the Tertius Gaudens” (the third who enjoys; Simmel 1950, 154).
[Georg Simmel: 1950. The sociology of Georg Simmel. New York: Free Press.]


Simmel noted that two people in a dyadic relationship tend to share a stronger, more durable tie if their dyad is embedded in a triad <cite>Prell 2012</cite> = what has become to be known as "Simmelian ties"

The third can line up with one of the two others and thereby gain his or her own advantage or can act as a broker between them and make a broker’s profit === ref. structural hole (Burt 1992)
[Burt, Ronald S. 1982. Toward a structural theory of action: Network models of social structure, perception and action. New York: Academic Press.]



Each connected triad is composed of three dyads—within the pair the choices or connections are either reciprocated or not.

There are actually 16 possible configurations of triads...


TRIAD CENSUS
ref. 
P.W. Holland and S. Leinhardt: "A method for detecting structure in sociometric data", American Journal of Sociology, 76:492-512, 1970
P.W. Holland and S. Leinhardt: "Transitivity in structural models of small groups", Small Group Research, 2:107-124, 1971


The triad census is thus a ‘periodic table of social elements’ and similarly able to categorize and build social structures.” (USN'2012)

ID:
1) The first character in the triad name gives the number of mutual dyads.
2) The second character gives the number of asymmetric dyads.
3) The third character gives the number of null dyads
4) The fourth character, if present, distinguishes between triads which are otherwise identical. 
e.g.
- 003 (disconnected)
- 012 (single link)
- 102 (mutual link)
- three 021 triads: source (021D), sink (021U), and path (021C)
- two 111 triads: mutual link + outgoing link (111U), mutual link + ingoing link (111D)
- two 030 triads: transitive link (030T) and cycle (030C)
- 201 (two mutual links)
- three 120 triads: mutual link + outgoing links (120U), mutual link + ingoing links (120D), mutual link + path (120C)
- 210 (two mutual links + single link)
- 300 (three mutual links)


USN'2012: ... the census or count of configurations can be compared with the chance distributions of these configurations in any network and yield important insights about the network. 

In general, the triad census, that is, the distribution of the 16 types of triads in an actual network, the “local” processes in the network, has been very useful in evaluating theories about the global attributes of the entire network, especially since some theoretical structures of a network may be contradicted by the distribution of the triad types in a particular network. 


While the distribution of triads seems at first to be a limited idea, the prevalence of different combinations of triads can reveal a great deal about the entire network. 



The distribution of reciprocated or unreciprocated dyads, centrality, and overall network density may account for most of the variance in the distribution of triads in human sociability networks (Faust 2007).
[Faust, Katherine. 2007. Very local structure in social networks. Sociological Methodology 37:209–256.]


CATEGORIZATION
- Transitive triads: All (6) triples within the triad are transitive (i tied to j, j tied to k, i tied to k), i.e. "a friend of my friend is also my friend" = 030T, 120U, 120D, 300
- Vacuously transitive: Either i is not tied to j and/or j is not tied to k = 003, 012, 021U, 021D, 102
- Intransitive: One or more intransitive triples within the triad (i tied to j, j tied to k, but i not tied to k) = 021C, 030C, 111D, 111U, 120C, 201, 210 

Note: Networks can contain vacuously transitive triads and still have the property of transitivity.


STRUCTURAL CONCEPTS
Different kinds of triads can be linked to to different structural concepts:
- Structural Balance: 300, 102
- Clustering:         300, 102, 003
- Ranked clustering:  300, 102, 003, 120D, 120U, 021U, 030T
- Transitivity:       300, 102, 003, 120D, 120U, 021U, 030T, 012
- Cycles			  120C

refs.

Clustering and structural balance
[J.A. Davis: "Clustering and structural balance in graphs", Human Relations, 20:181-187, 1967]
- Balance as a constrained form of transitivity (300, 102, but not all transitive triads are considered to be balanced)
- All balanced graphs are clusterable (a network is clusterable if it contains no cycle with a negative tie)

Ranked clustering
[J.A. Davis, S. Leinhardt: "The structure of positive interpersonal relations in small groups". In M. Berger, J. Zelditch, B. Anderson (eds.): "Sociological theories in progress", Houghton-Mifflin, 1972
- The role of asymmetric ties: Actors that hold mutual ties are not only in the same cluster, they are also in the same rank. An asymmetric tie implies that one actor is in a different rank than the other (the receiver is viewed in a higher position than the sender, since the receiver can afford not to reciprocate <cite>Prell 2012</cite>).

Cycles
[P.S. Bearman: "Generalized exchange", American Journal of Sociology, 102:1383-1415, 1997]
- Cyclic triads as "generalized exchange", where favors are done with the hope of being, indirectly, returned


No real network is perfectly balanced, ranked, nor transitive, but looking at the triad census you can observe the tendency that a network exhibits towards balance, ranked clustering, or transitivity.

e.g. UCINET (Triad census), Pajek (Triadic census)



There is a class of network models that utilize the dependence of types of dyads and triads on various attributes of the actors within the network that are extremely useful in shedding light on the social processes within these networks, though work in this field is just beginning to receive wide application (Robins and
Pattison 2005; Snijders, van de Bunt, and Steglich 2010; Wasserman and Robins 2005). 

[Robins, Garry, and Phillipa Pattison. 2005. Interdependencies and social processes: Dependence graphs and generalized dependence structures. In Models and methods in social network analysis, edited by P. Carrington, J. Scott, and S. Wasserman. New York: Cambridge University Press.]
[Snijders, Tom A. B., Gerhard G. van de Bunt, and Christian E. G. Steglich. 2010. Introduction to stochastic actor-based models for network dynamics. Social Networks 32 (1): 44–60.]
[Wasserman, Stanley, and Garry Robins. 2005. An introduction to random graphs, dependence graphs, and p*. In Models and methods in social network analysis, edited by P. Carrington, J. Scott, and S. Wasserman. New York: Cambridge University Press.]



++ Number of nonisomorphic graphs
http://mathworld.wolfram.com/SimpleGraph.html
http://mathworld.wolfram.com/SimpleDirectedGraph.html


<document>
<tag>motifs-triads-transitivity</tag>
<title>Transitivity</title>

<text>
++ Transitivity (if A likes B and B likes C, then A will like C)

Triad 030T contains one transitive relationship, triad 120D contains two, and triad 300 contains six transitive relationships. In contrast, triad 021C is intransitive. 

Statistical tests “are very supportive of the proposition that interpersonal choices tend to be transitive” (Wasserman and Faust, 598). Intransitive triads are very rare.


Transitivity defines the boundaries of a small group if we follow the heuristic that networks are built up from smaller components.

</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>motifs-triads-balance</tag>
<title>Structural balance</title>

<text>
Stuctural balance, postulated by Fritz Heider in the 1940's <cite>Heider 1946</cite> and Theodore M. Newcomb in the 1950's <cite>Newcomb 1953</cite>, led to research on triples of individuals, since balanced relations are common in empirical work...
</text>

<text>
<cite>Cartwright and Harary 1956</cite> were among the first to quantify structural balance...
</text>

<text>
Balance theory influenced the development of other structural theories, such as transitivity...
</text>


<text>
++ Balance (if A and B like each other, they will have a similar opinion of C; if they dislike each other, they will not agree on C)

the balance between the three members of a triad and leads to the classic “Balance Hypothesis”: “a friend of my friend is a friend of mine” and “an enemy of my friend is an enemy of mine.

“In the case of three entities, a balanced state exists if all three relations are positive in all respects, or if two are negative and one is positive” (Heider 1946, 110).
[Heider, Fritz. 1946. Attitudes and cognitive organization. Journal of Psychology 21:107–112]
+ tendency over time toward balance: "[i]f a not balanced state exists, then forces towards this state will arise.” 
+ “[i]f a change is not possible, the state of imbalance will produce tension.”

+ “my enemy’s friend is my enemy. It is a poor sort of enemy who allows himself to be guided by this maxim” (Martin 2009, 45). Martin explains that if A and B are enemies, it is good strategy for A to try to make friends with B’s friend C and all of B’s friends, thus leaving B completely isolated.


e.g.

- A network of interpersonal choices must have only certain kinds of triads. From the balance hypothesis, it follows that friends are likely to agree about a third party—if one of them likes a third party, both will like that person. And close friends agree more strongly about a third party than friends who are not particularly close. Configurations 111D and 111U that conform to this hypothesis should be statistically more frequent in a social network than configurations that do not. This balance tends to be supported in a wide variety of social networks in which the nodes are people <cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>, p.596

- International alliances also seem to follow the hypothesis 

[Antal, T., P. L. Krapivsky, and S. Redner. 2006. Social balance on networks: The dynamics of friendship and enmity. Physica D: Nonlinear Phenomena 224 (1–2): 130–136.]


USN'2012: Bbalance is only one theory about choice in a network and does have its limitations by postulating rigorous rules for relations that in messy social life do not always hold. Homophily and peer effects are another cause of connections and, though related to balance, homophily takes account of the social and cultural structures in which a network is embedded. 

</text>

</document>

<text>
<cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>: chapters 6 and 14...
</text>
</document>


<document>
<tag>motifs-cliques</tag>
<title>Cliques, plexes &amp; cores</title>

<text>
A <term>k-clique</term> is a fully-connected subgraph with k nodes.

e.g. triangles are 3-cliques (and two connected nodes always form a 2-clique)


++ two k-cliques are adjacent if they share k-1 nodes 

cf.
Imre Derényi, Gergely Palla, Tamás Vicsek:
Clique Percolation in Random Networks
Physical Review Letters, Volume 94, Issue 16, 160202 (2005)
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.94.160202
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevLett.94.160202

IDEA (D): One can replace a network by the complete set of its cliques connected in accordance to the definition of adjacent cliques

</text>


<text>
A <term>k-core</term> is a maximal subgraph whose nodes have at least k connections within the subgraph.

- k-cores are typically nested, as Russian matrioshka dolls.

- 1-cores are connected components.

- 2-cores are connected components without dangling chains.
e.g. trees have no k-cores with k \geq 2.

cf.
The architecture of randomly damaged uncorrelated networks as a set of successively enclosed substructures...
as random damage increases, the highest k-cores disappear (i.e. the best connected areas within the network)

Sergey N. Dorogovtsev, Alexander V. Goltsev, J. F. F. Mendes: 
k-Core Organization of Complex Networks
Phys. Rev. Lett. » Volume 96 » Issue 4
Phys. Rev. Lett. 96, 040601 (2006)
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.96.040601
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevLett.96.040601

Sergey N. Dorogovtsev, Alexander V. Goltsev, J. F. F. Mendes: 
k-core organization of complex networks CoRR abs/cond-mat/0509102: (2005)
http://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/0509102

Alexander V. Goltsev, Sergey N. Dorogovtsev, J. F. F. Mendes: k-core (bootstrap) percolation on complex networks: Critical phenomena and nonlocal effects CoRR abs/cond-mat/0602611: (2006)
http://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/0602611

</text>

<text>
CLIQUES <cite>Skiena 2008</cite>:

1) finding a maximum clique is NP-complete <cite>Karp 1972</cite>. A simple upper bound on the maximum clique in G is the highest vertex degree plus 1. A better upper bound comes from sorting the vertices in order of decreasing degree. Let j be the largest index such that degree of the jth vertex is at least j - 1. The largest clique in the graph contains no more than j vertices, since no vertex of degree &lt; (j - 1) can appear in a clique of size j. To speed our search, we should delete all such useless vertices from G.
SOLUTION: backtracking/branch-and-bound, simulated annealing (approximate solution)

2) "A maximal clique is a clique that cannot be enlarged by adding any additional vertex. This doesn’t mean that it has to
be large relative to the largest possible clique, but it might be. To find a nice maximal (and hopefully large) clique, sort the vertices from highest degree to lowest degree, put the first vertex in the clique, and then test each of the other vertices to see whether it is adjacent to all the clique vertices added thus far. If so, add it; if not, continue down the list. By using a bit vector to mark which vertices are currently in the clique, this can be made to run in O(n+m) time. An alternative approach might incorporate some randomness into the vertex ordering, and accept the largest maximal clique you find after a certain number of trials."


3) DENSE SUBGRAPHS: "Insisting on cliques to define clusters in a graph can be risky, since a single missing edge will eliminate a
vertex from consideration. Instead, we should seek large dense subgraphs - i.e. , subsets of vertices that contain a large number of edges between them. Cliques are, by definition, the densest subgraphs possible. 

The largest set of vertices whose induced (defined) subgraph has minimum vertex degree ge k can be found with a simple linear-time algorithm. Begin by deleting all the vertices whose degree is less than k. This may reduce the degree of other vertices below k, if they were adjacent to sufficiently deleted low-degree vertices. Repeating this process until all remaining vertices have degree ge k constructs the largest high-degree subgraph. This algorithm can be implemented in O(n+m) time by using adjacency lists and a suitable priority queue. If we continue to delete the lowest-degree vertices, we eventually end up with a clique or set of cliques, but they may be as small as two vertices.

- The densest subgraph problem seeks the subset of vertices whose induced subgraph has the highest average vertex degree. The
problem is NP-complete


4) PLANAR GRAPHS cannot have cliques of a size larger than four, or else they cease to be planar. Since each edge defines a clique of size 2, the only interesting cases are cliques of three and four vertices. Efficient algorithms to find such small cliques consider the vertices from lowest to highest degree. Any planar graph must contain a vertex of at most 5 degrees, so there is only a constant-sized neighborhood to check exhaustively for a clique containing it. We then delete this vertex to leave a smaller planar graph, containing another low-degree vertex. Repeat this check and delete processes until the graph is empty.
</text>

<text>
APPLICATIONS:

- Application of densest subgraph, namely detecting link spam on the Web.
[GKT05] D. Gibson, R. Kumar, and A. Tomkins. Discovering large dense subgraphs
in massive graphs. In Proc. 31st Int. Conf on Very Large Data Bases, pages
721–732, 2005.

- <cite>Skiena 2008</cite>: "Internal Revenue Service (IRS) developed to detect organized tax fraud. In this scam, large groups of phony tax returns are submitted in the hopes of getting undeserved refunds. But generating large numbers of different phony tax returns is hard work. The IRS constructs graphs with vertices corresponding to submitted tax forms and edges between any two forms that appear suspiciously similar. Any large clique in this graph points to fraud"
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>motifs-components</tag>
<title>Components &amp; k-components</title>
</document>

</document>



<document>
&bibliography;
<tag>clustering-coefficient</tag>
<title>Clustering coefficients</title>

<text>
The clustering coefficient of an individual node measure the density of connections among the node's neighbors <cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite>. Densely connected neighborhoods form clusters around a node.
</text>

<text>
The clustering coefficient measures how many nodes form triangular subgraphs with their adjacent nodes. In its original form, the clustering coefficient is the fraction of fully connected triangles among the node and its neighbors (a.k.a. three-node motifs). The clustering coefficient, therefore, measures how the neighbors of a node are interconnected.
</text>

<text>
L: In social network analysis, high clustering means that friends of friends are linked to one another. It is network science’s way of saying, “Birds of a feather, flock together.”
</text>

<text>
L: Suppose that we compare the number of links connecting a group of k adjacent nodes
to the maximum possible number,which is given by a complete subgraph with (k(k.))/2 links. 
Each subgraph formed around a node in this k-node neighborhood forms a triangular
subgraph if it is complete, and does not form a triangular subgraph if one or
more links is (are) missing. The amount of clustering depends on the number of triangles
found among these neighbors. Let the neighbors of node u be the nodes directly connected
to u. There are degree(u) such neighbors, which means that there are potentially
(degree(u) [degree(u)-1])/2 links among these neighbors. Suppose that the neighbors
share c links; then the cluster coefficient of node u, CC(u), is

CC(u) = 2c / ( degree(u) (degree(u) - 1) )

A more visual way to think of cluster coefficient is the following: A node u with degree(u)
neighbors may be part of c triangular subgraphs, each containing node u as one of the
triangle’s three nodes. Cluster coefficient is the ratio of the actual number of triangular
subgraphs c to the maximum possible number.


In directed networks, the formula is modified...

CC(u) = 2c / ( degree(u) (degree(u) - 1) )


In SNA, the clustering coefficient as defined above is also known as the ego density in ego networks (networks composed of a focal node [ego], its immediate neighbors [alters/altria], and the ties between ego and alters, as well as between the alters).
</text>




<text>
The clustering coefficient of can be interpreted as the probability that two of its neighbors are adjacent in the network. However, this probability often depends on the node degree. Hence it is often expressed as a degree-dependent function:
</text>

<equation>
C(k) = \langle CC(u)|_{degree(u)=k} \rangle
</equation>


<text>
The cluster coefficient of the whole network CC(G) is the average over all node clustering
coefficients. It is less informative, but it is often employed.
The clustering coefficient reaches it maximum for complete graphs CC(K_n) = 1 and its minimum for trees CC(T)=0 (e.g. stars).
</text>

<text>
Sometimes, the clustering coefficient just counts (three times) the number of triangles in the network, a measure known as transitivity by sociologists:
</text>

<equation>
transitivity(G) = 3 \frac{ \#triangles }{ \#connectedTriples }
</equation>

<text>
It should be noted that each triangle consists of three connected triples, hence the constant 3 in the expression above. The number of connected triples of nodes equals <eqn>\sum_i d_i(d_i-1)/2</eqn> <eqn>= n ( \langle d^2 \rangle - \langle d \rangle)/2</eqn>. Finally, the number of triangles <eqn>T</eqn> can be computed from the adjacency matrix as follows:
</text>

<equation>
T = \frac{1}{6} \sum_i a_{ii}^{(3)} = \frac{1}{6} Tr A^3
</equation>

<text>
where <eqn>Tr A^3</eqn> is the trace (the sum of the diagonal elements) of the cube of the graph adjacency matrix.
</text>


<text>
Low-degree nodes can disproportionately influence their neighbors' clustering coefficients, a problem solved by transitivity <cite>Newman 2003</cite>... a collectively normalized variant of the clustering coefficient.
</text>


<text>
Clustering coefficients and trasitivity have been generalized for weighted and directed networks <cite>Onnela et al. 2005</cite> <cite>Fagiolo 2007</cite>.
</text>

<text>
Clustering (segregation) - efficiency (integration) trade-off... Optimal clustering and modularity are incompatible with optimal global efficiency (separate communities do not communicate too much). Local vs. global order (e.g. specialization of subsystems).
</text>


</document>



<document>
<tag>modularity</tag>
<title>Modularity</title>


<text>
Networks with high levels of clustering are often composed of local communities or modules, which consist of densely connected sets of nodes. A module is separated from other modules in the sense that most links connect nodes within the module and only a few links extend beyond the module boundaries. </text>

i.e. modules without joint nodes (overlapping is absent by definition)
+ many links within modules
+ few links between nodes in different modules

Modular organization = about large-scale clustering of nodes within a network 


<text>
A measure of network modularity characterizes the balance of within-module and between-modules connections.
</text>



<text>
Modularity Q for a given partition of the network (finding the optimal partition is the problem addressed by community detection algorithms):
</text>

<cite>Girvan and Newman 2002</cite>

Network of m links divided into k modules, with m_i links in module i

Maximum modularity when modules are clearly separated from each other and minimum modularity when the network is homogeneous (imperceptible modules)

Idea: Compare two networks, the given one and its zero-modularity counterpart (an uniform random network with the same degree sequence)

Quantity: Ratio of the total number of links within modules and the number of links in the network

<equation>
Q = \frac{1}{m} \sum_{r=1}^{k} m_r \bigg|_{network} - \frac{1}{m} \sum_{r=1}^{k} m_r \bigg|_{uniform}
</equation>


For the uniform random counterpart, the ratio involved in the modularity measure can be computed from the node degrees. Let <eqn>q_r</eqn> be the total degree of the nodes in module <eqn>r</eqn>, i.e. <eqn>\sum_r q_r = 2m</eqn>. Then, the modularity <eqn>Q</eqn> can be computed as:


<equation>
Q = \sum_{r=1}^{k} \left[ \frac{m_r}{m} - \left( \frac{q_r}{2m} \right)^2 \right]
</equation>

Q will be close to 1 when the partition exhibits a strong community structure and close to 0 (even negative) when it does not.
Warning: A chain will yield non-zero modularity (hardly a modular network)

An equivalent expression in terms of the adjacency matrix is often employed:


<equation>
Q = \frac{1}{2m} \sum_{r=1}^{k} \sum_{i,j \in r} \left( a_{ij} - \frac{d_i d_j}{2m} \right)^2
</equation>

<text>
where the second sum is computed over all pairs of nodes within module <eqn>r</eqn> and the term <eqn>a_{ij} - d_i d_j / 2m</eqn> defines the so-called modularity matrix.
</text>

<text>
++  <cite>Newman 2006</cite> reports modularity values between 0.3 and 0.8 for some real-world networks (for their optimal partitions). It is hard to find a real network with a low modularity value... 
</text>

</document>





<document>
<tag>equivalence</tag>
<title>Equivalence</title>


<document>
<tag>equivalence-structural</tag>
<title>Structural equivalence</title>
</document>

<document>
<tag>equivalence-regular</tag>
<title>Regular equivalence</title>
</document>

</document>





<document>
<tag>motifs-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>


SNA: <cite>Kadushin 2012</cite>, <cite>Prell 2012</cite> chapter on analysis at the dyad and triad levels... 

<text>
Motif analysis extended to weighted networks <cite>Onnela et al. 2005</cite>.
</text>

<text>
Motif composition => profile of local processing capacity <cite>Sporns and Kotter 2004</cite>, <cite>Sporns et al. 2007</cite>.
</text>

<text>
<cite>Milo et al. 2002</cite>
<cite>Milo et al. 2004a</cite>
<cite>Milo et al. 2004b</cite>
</text>

</document>

</document>
