<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<title>Network Motifs</title>



<document>
<tag>motifs</tag>
<title>Network building blocks</title>

<text>
Large networks can be decomposed into smaller <q>building blocks</q> or <q>networks-within-networks</q>, commonly referred to as <b>motifs</b>.
</text>

<text>
Every network can be uniquely decomposed into a set of motifs, and the number and distribution of individual motifs can reflect some functional characteristics of the network <cite>Sporns 2011</cite>.
</text>

++
R. Milo, S. Shen-Orr, S. Itzkovitz, N. Kashtan, D. Chklovskii and U. Alon
Network Motifs: Simple Building Blocks of Complex Networks
Science 25 October 2002: 
Vol. 298 no. 5594 pp. 824-827 
DOI: 10.1126/science.298.5594.824

e.g. 
only two different 3-node connected motifs in undirected networks
13 different 3-node connected motifs in directed networks

NAIVE IDEA: Network function explained in terms of the repeated appearances of the most significant motifs?
If that were true, motifs could explain not just network structure, but also determine its behavior.


++ empirical study of network motifs

cf.

Kim Baskerville, Peter Grassberger, Maya Paczuski
Graph animals, subgraph sampling, and motif search in large networks.
Phys. Rev. E » Volume 76 » Issue 3, 036107, 2007
DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevE.76.036107 
URL: http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevE.76.036107

A. Vazquez, R. Dobrin, D. Sergi, J.-P. Eckmann, Z. N. Oltvai, A.-L. Barabási 
The topological relationship between the large-scale attributes and local interactions patterns of complex networks 
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 101, 17940-17945 (2004).


<document>
<tag>motifs-dyads</tag>
<title>Dyads</title>

<text>
= Two actors and their ties
</text>

<text>
At the most basic level, a link establishes a relationship between two nodes. The link is a property of the pair, not of any single node...
</text>

<text>
Dyadic analysis focuses on the properties of pairwise relationships, e.g. reciprocity.
</text>

<text>
<cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>: chapters 13, 15 &amp; 16...
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>motifs-triads</tag>
<title>Triads</title>

<text>
= Three actors and their ties
</text>

<text>
++ Transitivity (if A likes B and B likes C, then A will like C)
</text>

<text>
++ Balance (if A and B like each other, they will have a similar opinion of C; if they dislike each other, they will not agree on C)
</text>


<text>
<cite>Wasserman and Faust 1994</cite>: chapters 6 and 14...
</text>
</document>


<document>
<tag>motifs-cliques</tag>
<title>Cliques, plexes &amp; cores</title>

<text>
A <term>k-clique</term> is a fully-connected subgraph with k nodes.

e.g. triangles are 3-cliques (and two connected nodes always form a 2-clique)


++ two k-cliques are adjacent if they share k-1 nodes 

cf.
Imre Derényi, Gergely Palla, Tamás Vicsek:
Clique Percolation in Random Networks
Physical Review Letters, Volume 94, Issue 16, 160202 (2005)
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.94.160202
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevLett.94.160202

IDEA (D): One can replace a network by the complete set of its cliques connected in accordance to the definition of adjacent cliques

</text>


<text>
A <term>k-core</term> is a maximal subgraph whose nodes have at least k connections within the subgraph.

- k-cores are typically nested, as Russian matrioshka dolls.

- 1-cores are connected components.

- 2-cores are connected components without dangling chains.
e.g. trees have no k-cores with k \geq 2.

cf.
The architecture of randomly damaged uncorrelated networks as a set of successively enclosed substructures...
as random damage increases, the highest k-cores disappear (i.e. the best connected areas within the network)

Sergey N. Dorogovtsev, Alexander V. Goltsev, J. F. F. Mendes: 
k-Core Organization of Complex Networks
Phys. Rev. Lett. » Volume 96 » Issue 4
Phys. Rev. Lett. 96, 040601 (2006)
URL:	http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.96.040601
DOI:	10.1103/PhysRevLett.96.040601

Sergey N. Dorogovtsev, Alexander V. Goltsev, J. F. F. Mendes: 
k-core organization of complex networks CoRR abs/cond-mat/0509102: (2005)
http://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/0509102

Alexander V. Goltsev, Sergey N. Dorogovtsev, J. F. F. Mendes: k-core (bootstrap) percolation on complex networks: Critical phenomena and nonlocal effects CoRR abs/cond-mat/0602611: (2006)
http://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/0602611

</text>

<text>
CLIQUES <cite>Skiena 2008</cite>:

1) finding a maximum clique is NP-complete <cite>Karp 1972</cite>. A simple upper bound on the maximum clique in G is the highest vertex degree plus 1. A better upper bound comes from sorting the vertices in order of decreasing degree. Let j be the largest index such that degree of the jth vertex is at least j - 1. The largest clique in the graph contains no more than j vertices, since no vertex of degree &lt; (j - 1) can appear in a clique of size j. To speed our search, we should delete all such useless vertices from G.
SOLUTION: backtracking/branch-and-bound, simulated annealing (approximate solution)

2) "A maximal clique is a clique that cannot be enlarged by adding any additional vertex. This doesn’t mean that it has to
be large relative to the largest possible clique, but it might be. To find a nice maximal (and hopefully large) clique, sort the vertices from highest degree to lowest degree, put the first vertex in the clique, and then test each of the other vertices to see whether it is adjacent to all the clique vertices added thus far. If so, add it; if not, continue down the list. By using a bit vector to mark which vertices are currently in the clique, this can be made to run in O(n+m) time. An alternative approach might incorporate some randomness into the vertex ordering, and accept the largest maximal clique you find after a certain number of trials."


3) DENSE SUBGRAPHS: "Insisting on cliques to define clusters in a graph can be risky, since a single missing edge will eliminate a
vertex from consideration. Instead, we should seek large dense subgraphs - i.e. , subsets of vertices that contain a large number of edges between them. Cliques are, by definition, the densest subgraphs possible. 

The largest set of vertices whose induced (defined) subgraph has minimum vertex degree ge k can be found with a simple linear-time algorithm. Begin by deleting all the vertices whose degree is less than k. This may reduce the degree of other vertices below k, if they were adjacent to sufficiently deleted low-degree vertices. Repeating this process until all remaining vertices have degree ge k constructs the largest high-degree subgraph. This algorithm can be implemented in O(n+m) time by using adjacency lists and a suitable priority queue. If we continue to delete the lowest-degree vertices, we eventually end up with a clique or set of cliques, but they may be as small as two vertices.

- The densest subgraph problem seeks the subset of vertices whose induced subgraph has the highest average vertex degree. The
problem is NP-complete


4) PLANAR GRAPHS cannot have cliques of a size larger than four, or else they cease to be planar. Since each edge defines a clique of size 2, the only interesting cases are cliques of three and four vertices. Efficient algorithms to find such small cliques consider the vertices from lowest to highest degree. Any planar graph must contain a vertex of at most 5 degrees, so there is only a constant-sized neighborhood to check exhaustively for a clique containing it. We then delete this vertex to leave a smaller planar graph, containing another low-degree vertex. Repeat this check and delete processes until the graph is empty.
</text>

<text>
APPLICATIONS:

- Application of densest subgraph, namely detecting link spam on the Web.
[GKT05] D. Gibson, R. Kumar, and A. Tomkins. Discovering large dense subgraphs
in massive graphs. In Proc. 31st Int. Conf on Very Large Data Bases, pages
721–732, 2005.

- <cite>Skiena 2008</cite>: "Internal Revenue Service (IRS) developed to detect organized tax fraud. In this scam, large groups of phony tax returns are submitted in the hopes of getting undeserved refunds. But generating large numbers of different phony tax returns is hard work. The IRS constructs graphs with vertices corresponding to submitted tax forms and edges between any two forms that appear suspiciously similar. Any large clique in this graph points to fraud"
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>motifs-components</tag>
<title>Components &amp; k-components</title>
</document>

</document>



<document>
&bibliography;
<tag>clustering-coefficient</tag>
<title>Clustering coefficients</title>

<text>
The clustering coefficient of an individual node measure the density of connections among the node's neighbors <cite>Watts and Strogatz 1998</cite>. Densely connected neighborhoods form clusters around a node.
</text>

<text>
The clustering coefficient measures how many nodes form triangular subgraphs with their adjacent nodes. In its original form, the clustering coefficient is the fraction of fully connected triangles among the node and its neighbors (a.k.a. three-node motifs). The clustering coefficient, therefore, measures how the neighbors of a node are interconnected.
</text>

<text>
L: In social network analysis, high clustering means that friends of friends are linked to one another. It is network science’s way of saying, “Birds of a feather, flock together.”
</text>

<text>
L: Suppose that we compare the number of links connecting a group of k adjacent nodes
to the maximum possible number,which is given by a complete subgraph with (k(k.))/2 links. 
Each subgraph formed around a node in this k-node neighborhood forms a triangular
subgraph if it is complete, and does not form a triangular subgraph if one or
more links is (are) missing. The amount of clustering depends on the number of triangles
found among these neighbors. Let the neighbors of node u be the nodes directly connected
to u. There are degree(u) such neighbors, which means that there are potentially
(degree(u) [degree(u)-1])/2 links among these neighbors. Suppose that the neighbors
share c links; then the cluster coefficient of node u, CC(u), is

CC(u) = 2c / ( degree(u) (degree(u) - 1) )

A more visual way to think of cluster coefficient is the following: A node u with degree(u)
neighbors may be part of c triangular subgraphs, each containing node u as one of the
triangle’s three nodes. Cluster coefficient is the ratio of the actual number of triangular
subgraphs c to the maximum possible number.
</text>

<text>
The clustering coefficient of can be interpreted as the probability that two of its neighbors are adjacent in the network. However, this probability often depends on the node degree. Hence it is often expressed as a degree-dependent function:
</text>

<equation>
C(k) = \langle CC(u)|_{degree(u)=k} \rangle
</equation>


<text>
The cluster coefficient of the whole network CC(G) is the average over all node clustering
coefficients. It is less informative, but it is often employed.
The clustering coefficient reaches it maximum for complete graphs CC(K_n) = 1 and its minimum for trees CC(T)=0 (e.g. stars).
</text>

<text>
Sometimes, the clustering coefficient just counts (three times) the number of triangles in the network, a measure known as transitivity by sociologists:
</text>

<equation>
transitivity(G) = 3 \frac{ \#triangles }{ \#connectedTriples }
</equation>

<text>
It should be noted that each triangle consists of three connected triples, hence the constant 3 in the expression above. The number of connected triples of nodes equals <eqn>\sum_i d_i(d_i-1)/2</eqn> <eqn>= n ( \langle d^2 \rangle - \langle d \rangle)/2</eqn>. Finally, the number of triangles <eqn>T</eqn> can be computed from the adjacency matrix as follows:
</text>

<equation>
T = \frac{1}{6} \sum_i a_{ii}^{(3)} = \frac{1}{6} Tr A^3
</equation>

<text>
where <eqn>Tr A^3</eqn> is the trace (the sum of the diagonal elements) of the cube of the graph adjacency matrix.
</text>


<text>
Low-degree nodes can disproportionately influence their neighbors' clustering coefficients, a problem solved by transitivity <cite>Newman 2003</cite>... a collectively normalized variant of the clustering coefficient.
</text>


<text>
Clustering coefficients and trasitivity have been generalized for weighted and directed networks <cite>Onnela et al. 2005</cite> <cite>Fagiolo 2007</cite>.
</text>

<text>
Clustering (segregation) - efficiency (integration) trade-off... Optimal clustering and modularity are incompatible with optimal global efficiency (separate communities do not communicate too much). Local vs. global order (e.g. specialization of subsystems).
</text>


</document>



<document>
<tag>modularity</tag>
<title>Modularity</title>


<text>
Networks with high levels of clustering are often composed of local communities or modules, which consist of densely connected sets of nodes. A module is separated from other modules in the sense that most links connect nodes within the module and only a few links extend beyond the module boundaries. </text>

i.e. modules without joint nodes (overlapping is absent by definition)
+ many links within modules
+ few links between nodes in different modules

Modular organization = about large-scale clustering of nodes within a network 


<text>
A measure of network modularity characterizes the balance of within-module and between-modules connections.
</text>



<text>
Modularity Q for a given partition of the network (finding the optimal partition is the problem addressed by community detection algorithms):
</text>

<cite>Girvan and Newman 2002</cite>

Network of m links divided into k modules, with m_i links in module i

Maximum modularity when modules are clearly separated from each other and minimum modularity when the network is homogeneous (imperceptible modules)

Idea: Compare two networks, the given one and its zero-modularity counterpart (an uniform random network with the same degree sequence)

Quantity: Ratio of the total number of links within modules and the number of links in the network

<equation>
Q = \frac{1}{m} \sum_{r=1}^{k} m_r \bigg|_{network} - \frac{1}{m} \sum_{r=1}^{k} m_r \bigg|_{uniform}
</equation>


For the uniform random counterpart, the ratio involved in the modularity measure can be computed from the node degrees. Let <eqn>q_r</eqn> be the total degree of the nodes in module <eqn>r</eqn>, i.e. <eqn>\sum_r q_r = 2m</eqn>. Then, the modularity <eqn>Q</eqn> can be computed as:


<equation>
Q = \sum_{r=1}^{k} \left[ \frac{m_r}{m} - \left( \frac{q_r}{2m} \right)^2 \right]
</equation>

Q will be close to 1 when the partition exhibits a strong community structure and close to 0 (even negative) when it does not.
Warning: A chain will yield non-zero modularity (hardly a modular network)

An equivalent expression in terms of the adjacency matrix is often employed:


<equation>
Q = \frac{1}{2m} \sum_{r=1}^{k} \sum_{i,j \in r} \left( a_{ij} - \frac{d_i d_j}{2m} \right)^2
</equation>

<text>
where the second sum is computed over all pairs of nodes within module <eqn>r</eqn> and the term <eqn>a_{ij} - d_i d_j / 2m</eqn> defines the so-called modularity matrix.
</text>

<text>
++  <cite>Newman 2006</cite> reports modularity values between 0.3 and 0.8 for some real-world networks (for their optimal partitions). It is hard to find a real network with a low modularity value... 
</text>

</document>





<document>
<tag>equivalence</tag>
<title>Equivalence</title>


<document>
<tag>equivalence-structural</tag>
<title>Structural equivalence</title>
</document>

<document>
<tag>equivalence-regular</tag>
<title>Regular equivalence</title>
</document>

</document>


<document>
<tag>structural-balance</tag>
<title>Structural balance</title>


<text>
Stuctural balance, postulated by Fritz Heider in the 1940's <cite>Heider 1946</cite> and Theodore M. Newcomb in the 1950's <cite>Newcomb 1953</cite>, led to research on triples of individuals, since balanced relations are common in empirical work...
</text>

<text>
<cite>Cartwright and Harary 1956</cite> were among the first to quantify structural balance...
</text>

<text>
Balance theory influenced the development of other structural theories, such as transitivity...
</text>

</document>



<document>
<tag>motifs-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>

<text>
Motif analysis extended to weighted networks <cite>Onnela et al. 2005</cite>.
</text>

<text>
Motif composition => profile of local processing capacity <cite>Sporns and Kotter 2004</cite>, <cite>Sporns et al. 2007</cite>.
</text>

<text>
<cite>Milo et al. 2002</cite>
<cite>Milo et al. 2004a</cite>
<cite>Milo et al. 2004b</cite>
</text>

</document>

</document>
