<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>

<!-- Ranking -->

<document>
&bibliography;
<tag>ranking</tag>
<title>Ranking</title>


<text>
PROBLEM: Arrange a set of items in order of importance

RELATED
- Ranking (a rank-ordered list of items = a permutation of items)
- Rating (a numerical score assigned to each item)

Any rating scheme can be used to produce a ranking list
</text>


<text>
EXAMPLES

- Web search: 
PageRank (Google) and HITS (Ask.com)...  10-30 links from millions of web pages containing some given words

- Product recommendation: 
Netflix, 
IMDb (Internet Movie Database), 
Amazon...

- Economics: 
United Nations HDI (Human Development Index), http://hdr.undp.org/en/statistics/
Index of Economic Freewdom (Heritage Foundation), http://www.heritage.org/index/

- Education:
US News ranking of colleges and universities (http://www.usnews.com/rankings), 
Financial Times business school rankings (http://rankings.ft.com/businessschoolrankings/), 
The Times Higher Education Suplement ranking of World universities (http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/), 
the Academic Ranking of World Universities from the Shanghai Jiao Tong University a.k.a Shanghai ranking (http://www.arwu.org/), 
Webometrics ranking of the web presence of 20000 higher education institutions (http://www.webometrics.info/), 

- Sports: 
BCS (Bowl Championship Series) ratings for college football teams (invitations to bowl games), 
RPI (Rating Percentage Index) for college basketball teams (invitations to the March Madness tournament), 
ATP World Tour ranking of tennis players, http://www.atpworldtour.com/Rankings/Singles.aspx
FIDE chess ratings, http://ratings.fide.com/

- Politics, i.e. voting

Other domains: citation databases (scientific papers, patents, legal cases,...), social networks...
</text>


<text>
CAVEAT: Arrow's Impossibility Theorem

A perfect voting system does not exist

Incompatible requirements, from Kenneth Arrow's 1951 Ph.D. dissertation:

- Every voter ranks the candidates in the order he desires (unrestristed domain)

- If all voters prefer A over B, A should be ranked ahead of B (Pareto principle)

- When, within a subset of candidates, voters choose A over B, this relative order should be maintained over the whole set of candidates. Changes in the order of other candidates outside the subset should not affect the relative ranking of A and B (independence of irrelevant alternatives)

- No voter should have a disproportionate control over the election (non-dictatorship)

No voting system with three or more candidates can simultaneously satisfy these four (reasonable) criteria.
</text>


<document>
<tag>ranking-pagerank</tag>
<title>PageRank</title>

<text>
++ <cite>Page et al. 1998</cite> <cite>Brin and Page 1998</cite>
</text>

<text>
IDEA: The popularity of a web page is proportional to the number of times a web surfer would visit  the page when randomly surfing the Web. Since the WWW is a directed network, random walks could be trapped into dead ends (out-components). Therefore, we must allow random restarts...
</text>

<equation>
r_i = \frac{p}{n} + (1-p) \sum_{j: j \rightarrow i} \frac{r_j}{d_{out,j}}
</equation>

<text>
where <eqn>n</eqn> is the size of the network, <eqn>d_{out,j}</eqn> is the out-degree of node <eqn>j</eqn>, and <eqn>p</eqn> is the probability that the web surfer jumps to a node chosen uniformly at random (claimed to be about 0.15).
</text>

<text>
Typically, the higher the number of incoming links, the higher the PageRank of a given page. In uncorrelated networks (i.e. without node-degree correlations), the PageRank value for a node with a given number of links can be computed as <cite>Fortunato et al. 2008</cite>
</text>

<equation>
r(d_{in}, d_{out}) = \frac{p}{n} + \frac{1-p}{n} \frac{d_{in}}{\langle d_{in} \rangle}
</equation>


++ Random walks and Markov chains... e.g. www.whydomath.com video describing PageRank teleportation, dangling nodes, and random surfers to a non-mathematical audience



cf.
Santo Fortunato
Marián Boguñá
Alessandro Flammini
Filippo Menczer:
Approximating PageRank from In-Degree
Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 2008, Volume 4936/2008, 59-71, 
Fourth International Workshop on Algorithms and Models for the Web-Graph, WAW 2006, Banff, Canada, November 30 - December 1, 2006. Revised Papers
DOI: 10.1007/978-3-540-78808-9_6
ISBN: 978-3-540-78807-2 


<text>
However, the rank of the pages providing incoming links is what determines the rank of a given page... and this is hard to manipulate for high PageRank values.
</text>




<text>
++ Facebook has its own algorithm, EdgeRank, which (in conjunction with September’s addition, GraphRank) determines which items appear at the top of an individual's news feed. EdgeRank is based on many variables, including who Facebook thinks are a user's closest friends and how many people have interacted with a piece of content.

++ The social network's news feed sorting filter is called EdgeRank. It helps Facebook keep users updated on friends' activity without overwhelming them with every single post, "like," and comment spilling out of their social graph.

In 2010, *the company first provided public details on how it curates users' news feeds... The details are few, but what's known is that the EdgeRank formula is based on how Facebook judges the closeness of two people (or a person and a brand), how valuable an activity is (sharing a photo is better than clicking "like," for instance), and how long ago it took place. Precisely how these factors are measured is not revealed, and, like Google, Facebook is constantly making tweaks.

@ FT Tech Hub:
The unexpected impact of Facebook’s <q>seamless sharing</q> on newspaper sites.
November 18, 2011 4:52 pm by Tim Bradshaw.

 <url>http://blogs.ft.com/fttechhub/2011/11/unexpected-impact-facebook-newspaper-sites</url>
 <url>http://econsultancy.com/uk/blog/7885-edgerank-the-most-important-algorithm-you-ve-never-heard-of</url>


 "Climbing to the top of Google's search results—by tweaking the structure and contents of a Web page—is the basis for the multibillion dollar industry known as search-engine optimization. It's an industry that has boomed over the last decade because businesses of all sizes can gain and lose a fortune depending on where their Web pages rank. Scammers also came in droves, seeking to trick Google's algorithms into showing pages hawking their unsavory wares when searchers enter common queries. 

 "The rise of Facebook as a destination of businesses as well as people poses a new problem for tech-savvy marketers. Many companies have attracted thousands or even millions of "fans" to their Facebook page, but because Facebook filters the posts that people see in their news feed—using its own mysterious algorithm—those companies aren't reaching many of their Facebook fans with updates. 

 http://www.technologyreview.com/news/428230/marketers-try-to-master-facebooks-feed

</text>

<text>
++ Other ranking method, based on the user search log: BrowseRank (SIGIR'2008)
++ TrustRank (VLDB'2004).
</text>

<text>
++ Considering time (recency search): TS-Rank, time-sensitive ranking (ICDM'2008) and chapter in <cite>Yu et al. 2010</cite> @ p.187-209, also described within a subsection in <cite>Liu 2011</cite> @ p. 286-288.
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>ranking-HITS</tag>
<title>HITS</title>

<text>
++ <cite>Kleinberg 1998</cite> <cite>Kleinberg 1999a</cite> <cite>Kleinberg 1999b</cite>
</text>

<text>
CITATION ANALYSIS: Top authorities are like influential research papers cited by many other papers. Top hubs correspond to relevant surveys citing many influential papers. 
</text>


<text>
Sometimes, we might be interested in finding hubs and authorities within densely-linked collections (HITS returns just the major cluster corresponding to top-ranked hubs and authorities). These might correspond to non-principal eigenvectors, which can be computed using other numerical computing algorithms, such as orthogonal iteration or QR iteration. Examples: polysemic words, controversial issues (reflected as polarized groups within a network).
</text>

<text>
NOTE: Minor perturbations on the network can greatly influcence hub and authority scores, whereas they have little effect on PageRank scores 
</text>

<text>
(ref. Ng, Zheng, Jordan: "Stable algorithms for link analysis", SIGIR'2001) introduced the random jump step of PageRank into HITS to improve its stability.
</text>

<text>
(ref. Lempel, Moran: "The stochastic approach for link-structure analysis (SALSA) and the TKC effect." Computer Networks 33(1-6):387-401, 2000 ) proposed SALSA, a stochastic algorithm for link structure analysis that combines PageRank and HITS features to improve authority and hub computation by using two Markov chains: one for hubs and a different one for authorities.
</text>


<note>
<title>The offense-defense rating method</title>

A nonlinear cousin of Kleinberg's HITS algorithm, ref. <cite>Langville and Meyer 2012</cite>, chapter 7

++ Park-Newman method: direct and indirect wins (discounting parameter)
ref. Juyong Park and M.E.J. Newman: A network-based ranking system for US college football. Journal of Statistical Mechanics: Theory and Experiment, October 2005
</note>

</document>

<document>
<tag>ranking-blocks</tag>
<title>Block-level link analysis</title>

<text>
Multi-topic pages... (+ the problem of topic drifting, i.e. returning pages that have nothing to do with the topic search just because they are collected due to the presence of out-links that connect to them or even spamming in-links).
</text>

<text>
(ref. Chakrabarti: "Integrating the document object model with hyperlinks for enhanced topic distillation and information extraction" WWW'2001, 221-220) segments the page based on its DOM tree structure to identify the subtrees that are more related to a query topic.
</text>

<text>
(ref. Cai, Yu, Wen, Ma: "Block-based web search", SIGIR'2004) segments each Web page into different blocks, which are given importance value according, for instance, to their location. This importance value is then used to weight the links in the HITS or PageRank computation, thus reducing the impract of unimportant links.
</text>

</document>



<document>
<tag>ranking-evaluation</tag>
<title>Rank evaluation</title>

How far apart are two ranked lists?
e.g. comparing to a known standard, an agreed-upon yardstick (a.k.a. gold standard)

++ An alternative = Retroactive scoring: click-through rate, predictions of the past, A/B tests...

<document>
<tag>ranking-evaluation-kendall</tag>
<title>Kendall's tau</title>

ref. Maurice Kendall: A new measure for rank correlation. Biometrika, 30, 1938

Kendall's <eqn>\tau</eqn> correlation measure:

<equation>
\tau = \frac { n_c - n_d } { \binom{n}{2} }
</equation>

where <eqn>n_c</eqn> is the number of concordant pairs and <eqn>n_d</eqn> is the number of discordant pairs. Since <eqn>\binom{n}{2} = n(n-1)/2</eqn> is just the number of pairs of items in the list, <eqn>-1 \leq \tau \leq 1</eqn>. 

Perfect agreement: <eqn>\tau = 1</eqn>

Perfect disagreement: <eqn>\tau = -1</eqn>

Computation:
ref. Ronald Fagin, Ravi Kumar, D. Sivakumar: Comparing top k lists. ACM SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms, 2003, 28-36

Variations for dealing with partial lists, lists of varying size, and lists containing ties
ref. Cynthia Dwork, Ravi Kumar, Moni Naor, D. Sivakumar: Rank aggregation methods for the Web, WWW Conference, 2001
ref. Cynthia Dwork, Ravi Kumar, Moni Naor, D. Sivakumar: Rank aggregation revisited, CiteseerX
ref. Ronald Fagin, Ravi Kumar, D. Sivakumar: Comparing top k lists. SIAM 17, 2003

e.g. 

<equation>
\tau_{partial} = \frac { n_c - n_d - n_u } { \binom{n}{2} - n_u }
</equation>

where <eqn>n</eqn> is the number of unique items in all the lists under consideration (otherwise, we could not make pairwise comparisons of the resulting <eqn>\tau_{partial}</eqn> values) and <eqn>n_u</eqn> is the number of unlabeled pairs. Hence, 

<equation>
\frac { - \binom{n}{2} } { \binom{n}{2} - n_u } \leq \tau_{partial} \leq = \frac { \binom{n}{2} } { \binom{n}{2} - n_u }
</equation>

Intuitive feature: <eqn>\tau_{partial}</eqn> penalizes disjoint partial lists more than reverse partial lists.



Drawback: Disagreements at the bottom of the list incur the same penalties that disagreements at the top (typically, errors at the bottom are less important)

</document>


<document>
<tag>ranking-evaluation-spearman</tag>
<title>Spearman's footrule</title>

Charles Spearman

Spearman's measure weighs disagreements according to their position in the lists:

<equation>
\rho = \| l - \tilde{l} \|_1 = \sum_{i=1}^n | l(i) - \tilde{l}(i)|
</equation>


Taking the particular position within the ranked lists  into account, we can define a weighted footrule measure <cite>Langville and Meyer 2012</cite>:

<equation>
\rho_{weighted} = \sum_{i=1}^n \frac { | l(i) - \tilde{l}(i)| } { min \{ l(i), \tilde{l}(i)\} }
</equation>

Extension to partial lists @ <cite>Langville and Meyer 2012</cite>, pages 207-209
</document>


</document>



<document>
<tag>ranking-aggregation</tag>
<title>Rank aggregation</title>


<cite>Langville and Meyer 2012</cite>, chapters 14-15, pages 159-200:

e.g. meta-search engines

- Arrow's criteria (not all of them are always required...)

- Aggregation methods:

<list>

<item>Borda count (ref. J.C. Borda: Mémoire sur les élections au scrutin. Histoire de l'Académe Royales des Sciences, 1781)</item>

<item>Average rank</item>

<item>Simulated data</item>

<item>Graph-based approach</item>

<item>MRV = Minimum Violation Ranking</item>

</list>


<note>
<title>Rating aggregation</title>

+ Matrix form
+ Matrix normalization
+ Aggregation (e.g. weighted average)
+ Rating vectors from rating aggregation matrices

</note>



Aggregation refinement: O(n) local Kemenization
ref. Cynthia Dwork, Ravi Kumar, Moni Naor, D. Sivakumar: Rank aggregation revisited, CiteseerX
- An aggregated list is locally Kemeny optimal is there are no pair-wise swaps of items that reduce the sum of Kendall tau measures between each input list and the aggregated list


Effect of aggregation: Reducing the impact of outliers (e.g. anti-spam method for Google bombs and link farms)

</document>



<document>
<tag>ranking-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>

<text>
Despite their overlap and partial redundancy, different rankjing metrics provide unique information about individual nodes and their neighborhoods, hence each one is suitable for particular applications...
</text>

<text>
Both HITS and PageRank were presented in 1998: HITS at the 9th ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms in January and PageRank at the 7th International World Wide Web Conference in April.
</text>


<text>
Popular Science books
++ <cite>Langville and Meyer 2012</cite>
(ranking methods and evaluation techniques)
++ <cite>Langville and Meyer 2006</cite>
(PageRank + HITS)
</text>


<note>
<title>Spectral ranking</title>

<text>
Even though made famous by Google, eigenvalues and eigenvectors have been used in ranking techniques for more than 50 years. Collectively, such techniques are known as spectral ranking techniques.

ref. Sebastiano Vigna: Spectral Ranking, arXiv, December 2009, http://arxiv.org/abs/0912.0238/


Theory (origin): Study of nonnegative matrices by Oskar Perron (1880-1975) and Ferdinand George Frobenius (1849-1917). In fact, the unique largest eigenvalue of a real square matrix with positive entries and its corresponding eigenvector are also known as Perron value and Perron vector, respectively.

ref. Perron, Oskar (1907), "Zur Theorie der Matrices", Mathematische Annalen 64 (2): 248–263, doi:10.1007/BF01449896
ref. Frobenius, Georg (1912), "Ueber Matrizen aus nicht negativen Elementen", Sitzungsber. Königl. Preuss. Akad. Wiss.: 456–477

Practice (application to ranking):
fundamental contributions of Seeley and Wei (the dominant eigenvector, possibly with stochastic normalisation), Katz (damping) and Hubbell (boundary condition)

ref. John R. Seeley. The net of reciprocal influence: A problem in treating sociometric data. Canadian Journal of Psychology, 3:234–240, 1949.

ref. T.H. Wei: The algebraic foundations of ranking theory, Ph.D. Thesis, Cambridge University, 1952


ref. Leo Katz. A new status index derived from sociometric analysis. Psychometrika, 18(1):39-43, 1953.
== if M has spectral radius smaller than one, that is, |\lambda_0| &lt; 1, an attenuation or damping factor is introduced to guarantee convergence

ref. Maurice G. Kendall: Further contributions to the theory of paired comparisons, Biometrics 11, 1955

ref. Charles H. Hubbell. An input-output approach to clique identification. Sociometry, 28(4):377–399, 1965.
== initial preference, or boundary condition (preference vector in PageRank terms) 

ref. T.L. Saaty: Rank according to Perron: A new insight, Mathematics Magazine 60(4):211-213, 1967

++ Bonacich proposes to use spectral ranking on zero-one matrices representing entities and their relationships to identify the most important entities
ref. Phillip Bonacich. Factoring and weighting approaches to status scores and clique identi?cation. Journal of Mathematical Sociology, 2(1):113–120, 1972.

++ Mark E. Frisse. Searching for information in a hypertext medical handbook. Communications of the ACM, 31(7):880-886, 1988.

James Keener's ranking method for sports @ <cite>Langville and Meyer 2012</cite>, 29-52 
ref. James P. Keener. 1993. The Perron-Frobenius theorem and the ranking of football teams. SIAM Rev. 35, 1 (March 1993), 80-93. DOI=10.1137/1035004 http://dx.doi.org/10.1137/1035004



"PageRank is the damped Markovian spectral ranking of the adjacency matrix of a web graph. The boundary condition is called preference vector, and it can be used to bias PageRank with respect to a topic, to personal preferences, or to generate trust scores" 
ref. 

</text>


</note>



++
RANKING

- HITS, as an IBM research report <cite>Kleinberg 1997</cite>, SODA conference paper <cite>Kleinberg 1998</cite>, and JACM paper <cite>Kleinberg 1999a</cite>

- Google <cite>Brin and Page 1998</cite>: PageRank <cite>Page et al. 1998</cite>

++
Link analysis + Spectral analysis:

A. Borodin, J. S. Rosenthal, G. O. Roberts, P. Tsaparas, Finding Authorities and Hubs From Link Structures on the World Wide Web. 10th International World Wide Web Conference, May 2001.
A. Borodin, G. Roberts, J. Rosenthal, P. Tsaparas, Link Analysis Ranking: Algorithms, Theory and Experiments, ACM Transactions on Internet Technologies (TOIT), 5(1), 2005
Dimitris Achlioptas, Amos Fiat, Anna Karlin, Frank McSherry, Web Search via Hub Synthesis. 42nd IEEE Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science, 2001, p.611-618.
R. Lempel and S. Moran, Rank Stability and Rank Similarity of Link-Based Web Ranking Algorithms in Authority Connected Graphs, Information Retrieval 8 (special issue on advances in mathematics/formal methods in information retrieval), pp. 245-264, 2005.

Pedro Domingos, Matt Richardson. The Intelligent Surfer: Probabilistic Combination of Link and Content Information in PageRank. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 14, 2002.
Taher H. Haveliwala. Topic-Sensitive PageRank. 11th International World Wide Web Conference, 2002.
Alon Altman and Moshe Tennenholtz. Ranking Systems: The PageRank Axioms. Proceedings of ACM EC 2005.


P. Tsaparas, Using Non-Linear Dynamical Systems for Web Searching and Ranking, Principles of Database Systems (PODS), Paris, 2004


Davood Rafiei, Alberto Mendelzon. What is this Page Known for? Computing Web Page Reputations. Proc. WWW9 Conference, Amsterdam, May 2000


A. Y. Ng, A. X. Zheng, and M. I. Jordan. Link analysis, eigenvectors, and stability. International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI), 2001.
A. Y. Ng, A. X. Zheng, and M. I. Jordan. Stable algorithms for link analysis. 24th International Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR 2001).


S. Chien, C. Dwork, R. Kumar, D. Simon, and D. Sivakumar, Link Evolution: Analysis and Algorithms


Soumen Chakrabarti, Mukul Joshi, Kunal Punera, and David M. Pennock. The structure of broad topics on the Web. 11th World Wide Web conference, May 2002.


L. Lovasz. Random Walks on Graphs: A Survey. Combinatorics: Paul Erdos is Eighty (vol. 2), 1996, pp. 353-398.
Ziv Bar-Yossef, Alexander Berg, Steve Chien, Jittat Fakcharoenphol, and Dror Weitz. Approximating Aggregate Queries about Web Pages via Random Walks. 26th International Conference on Very Large Databases (VLDB), 2000, pages 535-544.


Ron Fagin, Ravi Kumar and D. Sivakumar. Comparing top k lists, Extended abstract in 2003 ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms (SODA '03), pp. 28-36.


J. Cho, S. Roy, Impact Of Search Engines On Page Popularity, WWW 2004
T. Joachims. Optimizing Search Engines Using Clickthrough Data. Eighth International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining, KDD-2002.
Zoltán Gyöngyi, Hector Garcia-Molina. Link Spam Alliances. 31st International Conference on Very Large Data Bases (VLDB), Trondheim, Norway, 2005.


Weiyi Meng, Clement Yu, King-Lup Liu. Building Efficient and Effective Metasearch Engines. ACM Computing Surveys 34(2002).


D. Liben-Nowell, J. Kleinberg. The Link Prediction Problem for Social Networks. Proc. 12th International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM), 2003.


++ 
Rank aggregation
Cynthia Dwork, Ravi Kumar, Moni Naor, D. Sivakumar. Rank Aggregation Methods for the Web. 10th International World Wide Web Conference, May 2001.
Ron Fagin, Ravi Kumar and D. Sivakumar, Efficient similarity search and classification via rank aggregation, Proc. 2003 ACM SIGMOD Conference (SIGMOD '03), pp. 301-312.

++ 
Rank clustering
[Sun, Y.;  Han, J.;  Zhao, P.;  Yin, Z.;  Cheng, H.;  Wu, T.,  RankClus: Integrating clustering with ranking for heterogeneous information network analysis,   In:  Proc. 2009 Int. Conf. Extending Data Base Technology (EDBT’09)  Saint Petersburg, Russia.  (Mar. 2009), pp.  565–576.]


++
Ranking based on network optimization (e.g. Dorit Hochbaum)
ref. R.K. Ahuja, Dorit S. Hochbaum, J.B. Orlin: Solving the convex cost integer dual of minimum cost network flow problem. Management Science, 49:950-964, 2003
ref. Dorit S. Hochbaum: Ranking sports teams and the inverse equal paths problem. LNCS 4286:307-318, 2006
ref. Dorit S. Hochbaum, A. Levin: Methodologies for the group rankings decision. Management Science, 52:1394-1408, 2006
ref. Dorit S. Hochbaum, E. Moreno-Centeno: Country credit-risk rating aggregation via the separation-deviation model. Optimization Methods and Software, 23:741-762, 2008





</document>


</document>
