<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>

<!-- Ranking -->

<document>
&bibliography;
<tag>ranking</tag>
<title>Ranking</title>

<text>
e.g. Web search (10-30 links from millions of web pages containing some given words)
</text>

<document>
<tag>ranking-pagerank</tag>
<title>PageRank</title>

<text>
++ <cite>Page et al. 1998</cite> <cite>Brin and Page 1998</cite>
</text>

<text>
IDEA: The popularity of a web page is proportional to the number of times a web surfer would visit  the page when randomly surfing the Web. Since the WWW is a directed network, random walks could be trapped into dead ends (out-components). Therefore, we must allow random restarts...
</text>

<equation>
r_i = \frac{p}{n} + (1-p) \sum_{j: j \rightarrow i} \frac{r_j}{d_{out,j}}
</equation>

<text>
where <eqn>n</eqn> is the size of the network, <eqn>d_{out,j}</eqn> is the out-degree of node <eqn>j</eqn>, and <eqn>p</eqn> is the probability that the web surfer jumps to a node chosen uniformly at random (claimed to be about 0.15).
</text>

<text>
Typically, the higher the number of incoming links, the higher the PageRank of a given page. In uncorrelated networks (i.e. without node-degree correlations), the PageRank value for a node with a given number of links can be computed as <cite>Fortunato et al. 2008</cite>
</text>

<equation>
r(d_{in}, d_{out}) = \frac{p}{n} + \frac{1-p}{n} \frac{d_{in}}{\langle d_{in} \rangle}
</equation>

cf.
Santo Fortunato
Marián Boguñá
Alessandro Flammini
Filippo Menczer:
Approximating PageRank from In-Degree
Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 2008, Volume 4936/2008, 59-71, 
Fourth International Workshop on Algorithms and Models for the Web-Graph, WAW 2006, Banff, Canada, November 30 - December 1, 2006. Revised Papers
DOI: 10.1007/978-3-540-78808-9_6
ISBN: 978-3-540-78807-2 


<text>
However, the rank of the pages providing incoming links is what determines the rank of a given page... and this is hard to manipulate for high PageRank values.
</text>

<text>
++ Facebook has its own algorithm, EdgeRank, which (in conjunction with September’s addition, GraphRank) determines which items appear at the top of an individual's news feed. EdgeRank is based on many variables, including who Facebook thinks are a user's closest friends and how many people have interacted with a piece of content.

++ The social network's news feed sorting filter is called EdgeRank. It helps Facebook keep users updated on friends' activity without overwhelming them with every single post, "like," and comment spilling out of their social graph.

In 2010, *the company first provided public details on how it curates users' news feeds... The details are few, but what's known is that the EdgeRank formula is based on how Facebook judges the closeness of two people (or a person and a brand), how valuable an activity is (sharing a photo is better than clicking "like," for instance), and how long ago it took place. Precisely how these factors are measured is not revealed, and, like Google, Facebook is constantly making tweaks.

@ FT Tech Hub:
The unexpected impact of Facebook’s <q>seamless sharing</q> on newspaper sites.
November 18, 2011 4:52 pm by Tim Bradshaw.

 <url>http://blogs.ft.com/fttechhub/2011/11/unexpected-impact-facebook-newspaper-sites</url>
 <url>http://econsultancy.com/uk/blog/7885-edgerank-the-most-important-algorithm-you-ve-never-heard-of</url>


 "Climbing to the top of Google's search results—by tweaking the structure and contents of a Web page—is the basis for the multibillion dollar industry known as search-engine optimization. It's an industry that has boomed over the last decade because businesses of all sizes can gain and lose a fortune depending on where their Web pages rank. Scammers also came in droves, seeking to trick Google's algorithms into showing pages hawking their unsavory wares when searchers enter common queries. 

 "The rise of Facebook as a destination of businesses as well as people poses a new problem for tech-savvy marketers. Many companies have attracted thousands or even millions of "fans" to their Facebook page, but because Facebook filters the posts that people see in their news feed—using its own mysterious algorithm—those companies aren't reaching many of their Facebook fans with updates. 

 http://www.technologyreview.com/news/428230/marketers-try-to-master-facebooks-feed

</text>

<text>
++ Other ranking method, based on the user search log: BrowseRank (SIGIR'2008)
++ TrustRank (VLDB'2004).
</text>

<text>
++ Considering time (recency search): TS-Rank, time-sensitive ranking (ICDM'2008) and chapter in <cite>Yu et al. 2010</cite> @ p.187-209, also described within a subsection in <cite>Liu 2011</cite> @ p. 286-288.
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>ranking-HITS</tag>
<title>HITS</title>

<text>
++ <cite>Kleinberg 1998</cite> <cite>Kleinberg 1999a</cite> <cite>Kleinberg 1999b</cite>
</text>

<text>
CITATION ANALYSIS: Top authorities are like influential research papers cited by many other papers. Top hubs correspond to relevant surveys citing many influential papers. 
</text>


<text>
Sometimes, we might be interested in finding hubs and authorities within densely-linked collections (HITS returns just the major cluster corresponding to top-ranked hubs and authorities). These might correspond to non-principal eigenvectors, which can be computed using other numerical computing algorithms, such as orthogonal iteration or QR iteration. Examples: polysemic words, controversial issues (reflected as polarized groups within a network).
</text>

<text>
NOTE: Minor perturbations on the network can greatly influcence hub and authority scores, whereas they have little effect on PageRank scores 
</text>

<text>
(ref. Ng, Zheng, Jordan: "Stable algorithms for link analysis", SIGIR'2001) introduced the random jump step of PageRank into HITS to improve its stability.
</text>

<text>
(ref. Lempel, Moran: "The stochastic approach for link-structure analysis (SALSA) and the TKC effect." Computer Networks 33(1-6):387-401, 2000 ) proposed SALSA, a stochastic algorithm for link structure analysis that combines PageRank and HITS features to improve authority and hub computation by using two Markov chains: one for hubs and a different one for authorities.
</text>

</document>

<document>
<tag>ranking-blocks</tag>
<title>Block-level link analysis</title>

<text>
Multi-topic pages... (+ the problem of topic drifting, i.e. returning pages that have nothing to do with the topic search just because they are collected due to the presence of out-links that connect to them or even spamming in-links).
</text>

<text>
(ref. Chakrabarti: "Integrating the document object model with hyperlinks for enhanced topic distillation and information extraction" WWW'2001, 221-220) segments the page based on its DOM tree structure to identify the subtrees that are more related to a query topic.
</text>

<text>
(ref. Cai, Yu, Wen, Ma: "Block-based web search", SIGIR'2004) segments each Web page into different blocks, which are given importance value according, for instance, to their location. This importance value is then used to weight the links in the HITS or PageRank computation, thus reducing the impract of unimportant links.
</text>

</document>




<document>
<tag>metrics-notes</tag>
<title>Bibliographic notes</title>

<text>
Despite their overlap and partial redundancy, different rankjing metrics provide unique information about individual nodes and their neighborhoods, hence each one is suitable for particular applications...
</text>

<text>
Both HITS and PageRank were presented in 1998: HITS at the 9th ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms in January and PageRank at the 7th International World Wide Web Conference in April.
</text>


<text>
Popular Science books
++ "Who's #1? The Science of Rating and Ranking", by Amy N. Langville and Carl D. Meyer, Princeton University Press, 2012. ISBN 0691154228
(ranking methods and evaluation techniques)
++ "Google PageRank and Beyond: The Science of Search Engine Rankings", by Amy N. Langville and Carld D. Meyer, Princeton University Press, 2006. ISBN 0691122024 (2012 paperback edition, ISBN 0691152667)
(PageRank + HITS)
</text>


++
RANKING
[Brin, S.;  Page, L.,  The anatomy of a large-scale hypertextual web search engine,   In:  Proc. 7th Int. World Wide Web Conf. (WWW’98)  Brisbane, Australia.  (Apr. 1998), pp.  107–117]
[Kleinberg, J.M.,  Authoritative sources in a hyperlinked environment,   J. ACM  46  (1999) 604–632.]
[Sun, Y.;  Han, J.;  Zhao, P.;  Yin, Z.;  Cheng, H.;  Wu, T.,  RankClus: Integrating clustering with ranking for heterogeneous information network analysis,   In:  Proc. 2009 Int. Conf. Extending Data Base Technology (EDBT’09)  Saint Petersburg, Russia.  (Mar. 2009), pp.  565–576.]




</document>


</document>
