<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE sys-ents [ <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "bibliography.xml"> ]> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../book.xsl"?>


<document>
&bibliography;
<tag>dynamics</tag>
<title>Network Dynamics</title>

<text>
++ <cite>Barrat et al. 2008</cite> <cite>Bar-Yam 2003</cite>  <cite>Ganguly et al. 2009</cite>
</text>

<text>
++ Classics <cite>Newman et al. 2006</cite>
</text>

<text>
++ Evolution <cite>Leskovek et al. 2005</cite> <cite>Dorogovtsev and Mendes 2002</cite> <cite>Dorogovtsev and Mendes 2003</cite> <cite>Pastor-Satorras and Vespignani 2007</cite>
</text>

<text>
Chapter 7 @ <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>: <q>Emergence,</q> introduces new self-organizing principles
for networks and shows how to custom-design networks of arbitrary degree sequence
distribution; 
</text>

<text>
Chapter 12 @ <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>, <q>Netgain,</q> is an exploration of business
models - relating the famous Schumpeter creative destruction process to an emergent
process, and mapping the Bass and Fisher-Pry equations onto networks. It is comforting
to verify the Bass-Fisher-Pry equations for networks, but furthermore, I
show how these classical models may be extended to multi-product markets and oligopolies.
</text>

<document>
<tag>diffusion</tag>
<title>Diffusion through networks (i.e. signal propagation)</title>

<text>
L: Chapter 8 @ <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>, <q>Epidemics,</q> extends the elegant work of Z. Wang,
Chakrabarti, C. Wang, and Faloutsos, to the exciting new endeavor of designing
antigen countermeasures for the Internet. This work can be used to explain human
epidemics as well as epidemics that sweep across the Internet. 
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>search</tag>
<title>Search on networks</title>
</document>


<document>
<tag>synchronization</tag>
<title>Synchronization and stabilization (i.e. conflicts and consensus)</title>

<text>
++ <cite>Arenas et al. 2008</cite>
</text>

<text> 
L: Chapter 9 @ <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>, <q>Synchrony,</q> pushes the early work of Watts to new levels—claiming that
network synchronization is merely a special case of linear system stability. Simple
eigenvalue tools can be used to determine the stability and synchrony of almost
any linear network. 
</text>

<text>
L: Chapter 10 @ <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>, <q>Influence Networks,</q> is mostly new material and
suggests what conditions must be met in order for a social network to come to consensus.
As it turns out, it is not easy for groups to agree! 
</text>

</document>


<document>
<tag>robustness</tag>
<title>Robustness / Vulnerability (i.e. percolation &amp; network resilience)</title>


<text>
++ <cite>Motter 2004</cite> <cite>Huang et al. 2011</cite>
</text>

<text>
++ Internet <cite>Cohen et al. 2000</cite> <cite>Cohen et al. 2001a</cite> <cite>Cohen et al. 2001b</cite>
</text>


<text>
L: Chapter 11 @ <cite>Lewis 2009</cite>, <q>Vulnerability,</q>
builds on the PhD dissertation of Waleed Al-Mannai, who formalized and extended
my own work on network risk. Al Mannai’s theory is being used on a daily basis to
evaluate critical infrastructure systems and protect them against natural and synthetic
(anthropogenic, humanmade) attacks. This has made a profound impression on the
practice of homeland security. 
</text>

</document>


</document>
